<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-12T17:16:11+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Blog of Andrey Lepekhin</title><subtitle>Thoughts on life improvement</subtitle><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><entry><title type="html">Web comics category</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Web comics category" /><published>2099-01-01T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2099-01-01T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category">&lt;p&gt;Beware, comics posted here tend to be profane and some are even NSFW.&lt;br /&gt;
Have fun! and ignore the ‘continue reading’ link (there’s nothing inside).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">Beware, comics posted here tend to be profane and some are even NSFW. Have fun! and ignore the ‘continue reading’ link (there’s nothing inside).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">I Tried to Build a Soundproof Sleep Capsule</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2026/02/10/Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Tried to Build a Soundproof Sleep Capsule" /><published>2026-02-10T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2026-02-10T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2026/02/10/Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2026/02/10/Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule">&lt;p&gt;Sound leaves no evidence. There’s no stain on the ceiling, no crack in the plaster — nothing you can point at and say &lt;em&gt;there&lt;/em&gt;. An apartment can feel silent at noon and turn hostile at 2 a.m., when a bass note rolls through the wall, not loud enough to complain about, just loud enough that your body is now &lt;em&gt;awake&lt;/em&gt;. Your jaw clenches. Not because the sound is dangerous, but because someone else — unknowingly — just decided how your next day is going to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For years I tried the usual arsenal — earplugs, white noise, therapy, bargaining with neighbors. Nothing worked. Actual silence is rare when you rent in a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suffice to say, I did not jump to &lt;em&gt;designing a soundproof sleep capsule&lt;/em&gt; right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/egg-carton-lined-walls.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Egg carton-lined walls&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pillows-on-the-bathroom-tiles&quot;&gt;Pillows on the Bathroom Tiles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rage was selective. Wind didn’t bother me. But if a &lt;em&gt;human&lt;/em&gt; made the noise — a hot spike of adrenaline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I stopped trusting daylight viewings. Before signing a lease, I’d ask realtors to let me sleep there for a night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One night stands out. I found a spacious apartment near a park that seemed perfect — until 11 p.m., when the building’s central heating pipes began to vibrate. A low, periodic hum seeped into the walls, the bedframe, my chest. I waited for it to stop. It didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I dragged my bedding onto the cold bathroom tiles — the only room without dedicated heating — queued a ten-hour “Brown Noise” track, and tried to convince myself this was fine. Looking from the toilet bowl to my pillow, I wondered how I ended up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-half-ton-hypothesis&quot;&gt;The Half-Ton Hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I couldn’t control the building, maybe I could control the boundary between it and my bed. The plan: solve this mechanically, once and for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recording studios solved this decades ago. The question was whether I could get studio-grade isolation in a renter-friendly, bed-sized package. I grabbed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/913144.Home_Recording_Studio&quot;&gt;the industry bible&lt;/a&gt; of studio construction, and immediately learned I had a lot of misconceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mental image was egg cartons and acoustic foam — the YouTube studio look. But that stuff is &lt;em&gt;absorption&lt;/em&gt;: it reduces reflections and makes a room less echoey. What I needed was &lt;em&gt;isolation&lt;/em&gt;: stopping my neighbor’s bass from reaching my pillow. Foam barely matters there; low-frequency energy just plows right through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bass was the target—the hardest to stop, and my main sleep problem. A bass note really does vibrate a cement wall. The amplitudes are nanometers, invisible, but enough: the whole slab rocks back and forth like a piston, re-radiating the bass on the other side. Higher frequencies I could solve with earplugs and closed windows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To stop low-frequency waves, acoustical engineering offers only two expensive tools: &lt;strong&gt;mass&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;decoupling&lt;/strong&gt;. Mass is brute force — a heavier wall is harder to shake, the same way it’s harder to push a parked truck than a shopping cart. Acousticians call this the mass law. Double the wall’s mass, and you gain about 6 dB&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:decibels&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:decibels&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of extra isolation — noticeable, but not dramatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a deep unfairness in acoustics: making noise costs nothing, but stopping it costs a fortune. A neighbor’s footstep is free; the mass required to block it weighs hundreds of kilograms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decoupling is sneakier: you build an inner structure that floats free of the outer one, so vibrations lose their path. Hold a tuning fork in the air and it hums quietly; press it against a table and the whole surface becomes a speaker. Decoupling keeps the tuning fork in the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canonical approach is a “room within a room.” In studios, the inner shell sits on rubber pads and doesn’t touch the outer walls, floor, or ceiling — a box floating inside another box. In my case, I thought: what if the inner room is just… bed-sized?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/early-sketchup-prototype.png&quot; alt=&quot;Early draft design prototype sketch&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;SketchUp prototype I used to look for contractors.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the requirements took shape, I hired Fehim — an engineer I found on Upwork — because I didn’t actually know how to design physical objects at this scale. The mass needed for real attenuation (reduction) pushed the estimate past half a ton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 100 kg door is not furniture; it’s a crushing hazard. In my sketch it was a rectangle. In reality it was a lever arm waiting to rip hinges out — or tip the structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t just “hang” a slab of mass-loaded vinyl (a thin, dense rubber sheet) and plywood; you build a steel cage to contain it. The deeper I dug, the more obvious my ignorance became.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d assumed plywood, drywall, and mineral wool were “cheap.” They are, until you need &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of them. Fehim pushed for a prototype first. I’d somehow become the “perfect on the first try” client, and he had to talk me into cutting scope. I’m glad he did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; preload=&quot;metadata&quot; loop=&quot;&quot; autoplay=&quot;&quot; muted=&quot;&quot; playsinline=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/prototype-cad-spinning.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;CAD of the cube prototype&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-uncutting-a-board&quot;&gt;No Uncutting a Board&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I ran into a harder problem: air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sealed box is quiet. It’s also a coffin.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:co2-risk&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:co2-risk&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The moment you add ventilation, you add openings—and sound treats openings like invitations. It floods through the tiniest crack.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:gap-isolation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:gap-isolation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the project stopped being “build heavy walls.” It became “build heavy walls &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; somehow let air in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grime accumulation, emergency exit… Hermetic seal? A submarine CO₂ scrubber?&lt;/em&gt; My project folder kept growing. But everything else would matter only if I could get the walls right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with basics: a half-meter prototype cube with heavy, decoupled double walls.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:cube-specs&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:cube-specs&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I bought mineral wool for the cavities, but after realizing the hair-thin glass fibers would coat my apartment, I stuffed them with old clothes instead. The goal was simple — test whether mass + decoupling + sealing = real attenuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t have the tools, so I asked in a local chat. A stranger — Alex (thank you!)—offered his backyard and his workshop, helped source materials, and taught me a few saw tricks on the spot. Without him, the cube might’ve stayed a sketch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/building-prototype-in-workshop.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Building the prototype in Alex&apos;s workshop&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assumed a plywood cube would be trivial. Then reality showed up: blades have thickness, wood has knots, and tiny errors add up until your “square” box needs quotation marks. And every fix removes more material — there’s no uncutting a board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/cube-prototype-assembled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;The finished test cube prototype&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the cube built, I set up a calibrated Dayton Audio mic and a flat-response speaker at 85 decibels (sound pressure level),&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:measurement-rig&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:measurement-rig&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; played pink noise — a signal that hits every frequency at equal loudness — and recorded. Then I placed the mic inside the cube, played the same noise, and compared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Subtract the two curves and you get the cube’s sound transmission loss (TL): how many decibels it blocked at each frequency. Everything above zero means the cube blocked sound. Below zero means it amplified it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/chart-transmission-loss-cube-vs-room-door.png&quot; alt=&quot;Transmission loss of the cube vs. a regular room door&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This wasn’t a lab-grade measurement — the test room had its own reflections and modes. But the result was unambiguous enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to slam the laptop shut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the low frequencies I cared about, the cube wasn’t just ineffective — it was ~10 dB&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:decibels:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:decibels&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; than no cube at all. I’d built a giant guitar body: a resonance chamber that grabbed the bass and hummed along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I blamed my construction, then my testing setup. Later, theory explained one of the dips: at certain frequencies, the sound waves bounced back and forth inside the cube at exactly the right spacing to reinforce each other — like pushing a kid on a swing at just the right moment. The cube’s internal dimensions were accidentally &lt;em&gt;tuned&lt;/em&gt; to amplify the very frequencies I wanted to block.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:acoustic-modes&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:acoustic-modes&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I never figured out the second, sub-300 Hz dip.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that graph, I went into avoidance mode. For weeks the designs sat untouched, and “ambitious” started to feel like “delusional.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, the pivot to metamaterials was partly genuine curiosity and partly a refusal to sit with the failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;thousands-of-tiny-bottles&quot;&gt;Thousands of Tiny Bottles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually I went looking for a different lever — something smarter than “add more plywood.” That’s how I found &lt;strong&gt;acoustic metamaterials&lt;/strong&gt; — materials whose behavior comes less from what they’re made of and more from how they’re shaped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jet engines can’t be sealed, so they reduce noise with honeycomb structures that act like thousands of tiny &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helmholtz_resonance&quot;&gt;Helmholtz resonators&lt;/a&gt; tuned to eat specific tones. A Helmholtz resonator is simpler than it sounds: blow across a bottle top and you hear a note. That note is the air in the neck bouncing against the air trapped in the body, and the bottle absorbs energy at exactly that frequency. Change the bottle’s shape, change the frequency it eats. Now imagine thousands of precisely shaped “bottles” embedded in a wall — each one swallowing a different slice of the noise spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read acoustics papers and kept running into the same seductive idea: attenuation without the weight. Could geometry replace some of what I’d been trying to purchase with sheer mass? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mdpi.com/2683028&quot;&gt;One paper (Hedayati et al., 2024)&lt;/a&gt; had enough data for me to reproduce the build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This led to a delightful detour into parametric CAD — design software where every dimension is a variable you can tweak, then regenerate the whole model. Unlike the cube, this could iterate without sawdust: tweak a dimension, regenerate, print again. I ended up designing and 3D-printing an array of Helmholtz resonators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/3d-printed-helmholtz-resonators.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;3D-printed Helmholtz resonator prototypes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holding the first print felt like a victory — until I did the math. To cover a capsule, I’d need hundreds. Filament cost and print time ballooned into months. I never tested a single one. The prototype now holds spent batteries on my shelf — a monument to parametric CAD, if nothing else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-last-paper&quot;&gt;The Last Paper&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I found &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.15216&quot;&gt;a paper by Krasikova et al. (2023)&lt;/a&gt; that captured my imagination. The authors used plastic plumbing tubes with cleverly cut holes to create paired Helmholtz resonators, and reported attenuation across a broad range. Most metamaterials target narrow bands (like a specific engine frequency), but my goal was broad attenuation. This paper promised exactly that — and claimed it didn’t even require a hermetic seal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I emailed the author with clarifying questions (she replied!). Plastic tubes were light, cheap, and targeted the needed frequency range. For the first time in months, I fell asleep picturing the finished build — not cataloging problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After three months and six emails, I was ready to build. I opened a spreadsheet to finalize the Bill of Materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each resonator tube needed a specific length to target a particular frequency. To cover a bed-sized enclosure — say, 5 meters of perimeter and 1 meter tall — I’d need six resonators per block, eight blocks per meter of wall. The sum at the bottom of the column stared back at me: &lt;strong&gt;250 meters of PVC&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2026-02-10-Soundproof-Sleep-Capsule/250-m-of-pvc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;250 m of PVC pipes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d optimized for “lightweight” while ignoring “how much.” The resulting structure would still weigh over 500 kg, but now it would be made of thousands of glued tubes instead of simple plywood. I’d spent months on acoustic metamaterials only to arrive back at the same brute-force truth: mass laws are non‑negotiable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I closed the spreadsheet and, for the first time, didn’t open another paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-door-slammed-at-2am&quot;&gt;The Door Slammed at 2 a.m.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a recurring problem disappears without you changing anything, you don’t relax — you brace for its return.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My sleep improved, though I never isolated the variable. Recently a door slammed at 2 a.m. I noticed. I rolled over. A year earlier, I would have stayed awake, jaw clenched.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Finland’s lower ambient stress finally settled into my nervous system&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:relocation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:relocation&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Or maybe the act of building — even building things that failed — gave back what I’d actually lost: not quiet, but &lt;em&gt;agency&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I disassembled the cube, reclaimed the plywood, and reused the CAD skills on my &lt;a href=&quot;/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings&quot;&gt;next hobby project&lt;/a&gt;. In total I spent under 1,000 euros — about 300 on the engineer, the rest on materials and tools — and a solid month of full-time effort. None of it produced silence. All of it mattered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sound leaves no evidence. But the sawdust did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:decibels&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Decibels are logarithmic. 6 dB means roughly four times the sound energy, though your ears perceive it as only a moderate change. 10 dB is about twice as loud subjectively. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:decibels&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:decibels:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:co2-risk&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;In a sealed capsule roughly 2 m × 0.8 m × 0.8 m (about 1.28 m³), a sleeping adult exhaling ~0.2 L/min of CO₂ would push concentration past 1% — the threshold for headaches and impaired cognition — in about 2.5 hours. Past 4–5% you risk unconsciousness. Any real build would need forced ventilation, which means holes, which means sound leaks. The leaks are solvable with a baffle box — a zigzag channel lined with absorptive material that lets air through but forces sound to bounce and die — but designing one that moves enough air quietly is a project in itself. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:co2-risk&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:gap-isolation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Even a tiny gap dramatically undermines isolation — an opening of just 0.01% of a wall’s area can halve its effective sound blocking. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:gap-isolation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:cube-specs&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Outer walls 45 cm, inner cavity 20 cm. Each outer wall was two sheets of 15 mm birch plywood. Inner and outer shells were decoupled with Gyproc XR 95 resilient channels — thin metal strips that flex, so the inner wall doesn’t rigidly touch the outer one. The old clothes likely reduced high-frequency absorption compared to mineral wool, but shouldn’t have affected the resonance problem. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:cube-specs&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:measurement-rig&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Measurement rig: EarFun UBOOM L speaker (chosen for its flat frequency response — important so the test signal doesn’t favor any pitch), Dayton Audio iMM-6 calibrated measurement mic, placed 1 m from the speaker at 85 ±3 dB SPL. Recorded in Audacity; TL graph generated with a Python script using the mic’s factory calibration file. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:measurement-rig&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:acoustic-modes&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The inner cube was 170×200×200 mm. Two acoustic modes collided at 857.5 Hz — one of the valleys on the graph. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:acoustic-modes&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:relocation&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Moved there in 2024, &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; starting this project. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:relocation&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">Sound leaves no evidence. There’s no stain on the ceiling, no crack in the plaster — nothing you can point at and say there. An apartment can feel silent at noon and turn hostile at 2 a.m., when a bass note rolls through the wall, not loud enough to complain about, just loud enough that your body is now awake. Your jaw clenches. Not because the sound is dangerous, but because someone else — unknowingly — just decided how your next day is going to go.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">DIY Door Fan to Fix My Groggy Mornings</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DIY Door Fan to Fix My Groggy Mornings" /><published>2025-06-22T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2025-06-22T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings">&lt;p&gt;It all started with a comment from my doctor. He told me that, ideally, I should wake up like Mickey Mouse: bright, energetic, and ready to leap out of bed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/pseudo-Mickey.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Animated mouse waking up, looking chipper. Generated by ChatGPT.&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Legally distinct, chipper morning mouse.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought about my own mornings. The reality was a slow, groggy 30-minute crawl out of sleep. Mickey Mouse? I was more like a grumpy bear waking up from a long hibernation&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then one day, the ventilation failed in my office. After a few hours in the stuffy air, I had the exact same groggy feeling and a splitting headache. The pieces clicked into place. My office felt just like my bedroom in the morning. The enemy was CO2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bedroom was the perfect trap. As a light sleeper in the city, I seal it for silence. The window is closed to block out seagulls, and the door is shut to mute the rest of the apartment. Ventilation-wise my room has only a “trickle vent” – a small slit above the window to suck in fresh air based on pressure difference. But it didn’t feel like it was enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so, a new obsession was born. I have a habit of looking for a “silver bullet”, a single fix that I believe will solve &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. If I could just lower the CO2 in my bedroom, I’d be more productive, make better decisions, and be happier. These waves of inspiration are my favorite part of any project. The bullet never solves all the problems, but the process is usually worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was time to build a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;measuring-the-problem&quot;&gt;Measuring the Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I could solve the problem, I had to measure it. I remembered &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28457135&quot;&gt;a Hacker News post&lt;/a&gt; about a DIY CO2 monitor and ordered the parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My soldering skills were rusty, so a helpful stranger at the local maker space coached me through pin soldering without frying the sensors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/diy_v4_assembled.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Assembled DIY Air quality monitor by AirGradient&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airgradient.com/documentation/diy-v4/&quot;&gt;AirGradient DIY monitor&lt;/a&gt;, licensed under &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 4.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put the new sensor on my nightstand. The next morning, the results were bad. While fresh air sits at 400 ppm and stuffiness symptoms begin around 1,000 ppm, my room was peaking at &lt;strong&gt;1,700 ppm&lt;/strong&gt;.  &lt;br /&gt;
While it isn’t &lt;em&gt;dangerous&lt;/em&gt;, it still might’ve been the reason for my morning grogginess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Overnight CO2&quot; aria-label=&quot;Interactive line chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-SpOXU&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/SpOXU/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;396&quot; data-external=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var e=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var t in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][t]+&quot;px&quot;;r.style.height=d}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-main-idea&quot;&gt;The Main Idea&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My rental agreement meant I couldn’t drill holes in walls. The only way for air to get in or out was the 18mm gap under my door. This led to my main idea: &lt;strong&gt;if I could actively push stale air &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt; from under the door, the negative pressure in the room would pull fresh air &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; through the trickle vent.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The heart of this system would be a fan. It needed to be powerful enough but also quiet. My mind went straight to Noctua, a brand PC builders use for silent fans. I chose the NF-F12 PWM model, which has high static pressure (good for pushing air through tight spaces) and low noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now for the main design challenge: how to funnel the air from a round 120mm fan into a long, thin gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-pizza-box-prototype&quot;&gt;The Pizza Box Prototype&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started designing a duct in &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/CadQuery/cadquery&quot;&gt;CadQuery&lt;/a&gt;, a Python library for making 3D models. I hoped current LLMs could create the 3D model from my description alone, but I was quickly proven wrong. So I did it the old-fashioned way, defining it myself part by part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/v1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A CAD drawing of the first, complicated 3D model showing a fan housing, a 90-degree turn, and a rectangular outlet.&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Blue was the part to be used to tie the rope to. French flag is accidental&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my first design, I planned to mount the fan and duct directly onto the door with ropes so it would move with it (blue part would push against the door and the notch at the end is for rope). Before starting a long 3D print, I decided to build a quick and dirty prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using two pizza boxes and some tape, I mocked up the shape. I held my cardboard contraption against the door with the rope, just as I’d planned. Then, I let the rope go slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just sat there. On the floor. Perfectly stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a facepalm moment. I had to laugh at myself for over-engineering it. Why did I think it needed a complex mounting system? It could just be a simple, floor-standing unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/pizza_prototype_suspended.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of the prototype made from pizza boxes and tape, suspended near the floor by the door.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototype also &lt;em&gt;worked&lt;/em&gt;, lowering the CO2 by about 150 ppm with the fan at 40% speed (for lower noise). Now it was time to improve on the design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;first-3d-print&quot;&gt;First 3D Print&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first 3D-printed version came from a research rabbit hole. I’d read that industrial ventilation needs huge, smooth turns to prevent turbulence. The result was a beast—a three-part device with 4mm thick walls that looked like a defensive tower from a strategy game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/v2_printed.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A photo of the large, three-part 3D printed &amp;quot;tower&amp;quot; duct, alonside the pizza box prototype.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It worked a little better than the prototype, lowering CO2 by about 200 ppm by itself. But looking at it I realized it was overkill. For my setup, I didn’t need industrial-grade design, the air speed was almost imperceptibly low. I could make the duct much simpler and smaller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;further-improvements&quot;&gt;Further Improvements&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was to just add more fans side-by-side, but that would get expensive and might be premature. I decided to improve the design first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first breakthrough came one morning, as I was lying in bed; my brain must have been working on the problem in the background. &lt;em&gt;Why the 90-degree turn?&lt;/em&gt; The fan could work in any orientation. By placing the fan on its side, I could get rid of the turn completely. This would save a massive amount of plastic and print time, and also reduce air friction losses from the bend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went back to CadQuery and designed a much sleeker version. The defensive tower had evolved into a… simple funnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/v4-cad.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A CAD drawing of the new, simpler funnel-shaped duct.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After printing two new funnels, experimentation led to two more improvements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead of just pushing stale air &lt;em&gt;out&lt;/em&gt;, using one fan to actively pull fresh air &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; from the hallway dropped the CO2 by another 100 ppm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There was no draft in the room. Air exchange away from the door was slow, likely relying on simple diffusion. I realized I could accelerate this. I already had quiet standing fan so I placed it near the door, aimed inwards. That, surprisingly, cut another 200 ppm without adding more fans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-final-current-system&quot;&gt;The &lt;del&gt;Final&lt;/del&gt; Current System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, the area by my door is a mess of wires and fans, but it works. A single power adapter feeds a PWM controller, which then splits the signal to my three fans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe title=&quot;Peak CO2 based on setup&quot; aria-label=&quot;Bar Chart&quot; id=&quot;datawrapper-chart-DNhwZ&quot; src=&quot;https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/DNhwZ/1/&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; style=&quot;width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;&quot; height=&quot;233&quot; data-external=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;script type=&quot;text/javascript&quot;&gt;!function(){&quot;use strict&quot;;window.addEventListener(&quot;message&quot;,(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;]){var e=document.querySelectorAll(&quot;iframe&quot;);for(var t in a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data[&quot;datawrapper-height&quot;][t]+&quot;px&quot;;r.style.height=d}}}))}();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2025-06-22-DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings/v4-v3-prototype.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;My current setup, from left to right: the new funnel duct (v4), the &amp;quot;defensive tower&amp;quot; (v2), and the original pizza box prototype. The second funnel and the standing fan are not shown.&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPD&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44366535&quot;&gt;Hacker News discussion&lt;/a&gt; gave me a great new idea: flip the entire system on its head. Instead of creating negative pressure at the door, I could create &lt;em&gt;positive&lt;/em&gt; pressure from the source of fresh air. This means installing a fan directly in the trickle vent to actively pump fresh air &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt;. I’ll need to design a new duct to adapt the fan to the vent’s shape and add a coarse filter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I still don’t fully understand why the system works as it does. Is it really creating negative pressure and pulling fresh air through the trickle vent, like I first thought? Or is it just mixing the air near the door and propagating it? The next step is to find a way to measure the actual airflow.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The other improvement is more practical. Right now, my setup is a functional but messy collection of parts. I’d like to design and print a single, clean enclosure to hold all the fans. It would look better and be much easier to move out of the way when I need to.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;build-your-own&quot;&gt;Build Your Own&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3D Models &amp;amp; Code:&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andrey-lepekhin/diy-door-fan&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Primary Fan:&lt;/strong&gt; Noctua NF-F12 PWM — for its high static pressure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fan Controller:&lt;/strong&gt; Noctua NA-FC1 — for easy manual fan speed control&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power supply:&lt;/strong&gt; Noctua NV-PS1 — also packs 1-to-3 splitter cable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CO2 Monitor:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airgradient.com/documentation/diy-v4/&quot;&gt;AirGradient DIY v4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standing fan:&lt;/strong&gt; Xiaomi Mi Smart Standing Fan 2 — at 1% speed it’s almost as quiet as the smaller fans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-am-i-mickey-mouse-now&quot;&gt;So, Am I Mickey Mouse Now?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t wake up with a cartoonish smile every day. But my mornings &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; better. The grogginess is mostly gone, and I feel more rested. Of course, it could be the summer starting (circadian rhythm/melatonin change, etc), placebo or some combinations of factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, I loved the process. I learned about ventilation, got better at 3D modeling &lt;em&gt;for&lt;/em&gt; 3D printing, and felt the satisfaction of building something real that solved my own problem. That journey, with all its mistakes and small victories, was the real reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Since &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/06/02/Biohacking-and-me&quot;&gt;my biohacking days&lt;/a&gt;, I’ve been pretty strict about sleep hygiene. I consistently get my 8 hours, go to bed at the same time, and avoid things like late-night meals or alcohol. I was confident the issue wasn’t just poor sleep habits. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">It all started with a comment from my doctor. He told me that, ideally, I should wake up like Mickey Mouse: bright, energetic, and ready to leap out of bed.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Should AI Take the Wheel?</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/03/24/Should-AI-Take-the-Wheel" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Should AI Take the Wheel?" /><published>2025-03-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-03-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/03/24/Should-AI-Take-the-Wheel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/03/24/Should-AI-Take-the-Wheel">&lt;p&gt;When my wife asked, “&lt;em&gt;Which decisions should you &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; delegate to AI?&lt;/em&gt;”, I froze mid-thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--excerpt_separator--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At that moment, it hit me just how much I’d already outsourced—maybe even too much. She noticed (quicker than I did!) that I’d become increasingly dependent on AI, whose capabilities seem to grow by the week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It started innocently enough. Small questions like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;What meal can I make with these leftovers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;quickly escalated to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Should we move to another city?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before long, decisions I’d usually ponder through journaling, or with trusted friends, had slowly become quick prompts to ChatGPT, answered instantly. Convenience quietly replaced reflection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It begs the question: when do we cross the line from helpful to dangerously passive?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;better-decisions&quot;&gt;Better decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I chatted about this with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://x.com/Aay17ush&quot;&gt;friend&lt;/a&gt;. We talked about how little practice we really get with life’s biggest choices: leaving a job, ending a relationship, deciding to move abroad. These choices come up infrequently yet have massive stakes attached, no wonder we struggle with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this perspective, AI seems almost irresistible. Trained on humanity’s collective experiences, less affected by the emotional blind spots that hinder our judgment,&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; wouldn’t AI naturally tend to make wiser, more objective choices?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cheat-code-to-life&quot;&gt;Cheat code to life&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yet&lt;/em&gt;, even if AI produces objectively better outcomes, could depending on it take away something vital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It reminds me of using cheat codes in video games as a child (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;IDDQD&lt;/code&gt;, anyone?). At first, cheating felt amazing. Soon afterward, however, I noticed something unexpected—I wasn’t having any fun. The challenge vanished, the tension collapsed, and with them disappeared all the joy and meaning behind playing in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder: Could over-depending on AI feel the same way, robbing me of life’s struggles—the very struggles that I suspect build character, resilience, and empathy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve resorted to cheats in games when they became frustratingly hard or when low mood got the best of me, &lt;em&gt;even&lt;/em&gt; when I knew it would spoil the fun longer-term. If I can’t resist that temptation in gaming, how can I resist the allure of AI making my life easier?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But maybe&lt;/em&gt; the gaming analogy doesn’t perfectly map onto real life. It’s worth exploring the limitations of this idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;real-life-isnt-a-carefully-crafted-video-game&quot;&gt;Real life isn’t a carefully crafted video game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our daily challenges aren’t necessarily meaningful or valuable. Many struggles aren’t instructive—they’re random, painful occurrences delivering little personal growth or satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these circumstances, reducing unnecessary trauma and harm isn’t “cheating”; it’s just common sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;not-all-gain-requires-pain&quot;&gt;Not all gain requires pain&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And maybe I’ve overestimated the necessity of struggle and hardship for personal growth. Positive experiences like curiosity and creativity, can also shape who we become. Perhaps AI might help us learn and grow without unnecessarily painful detours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;but-some-gain-still-might&quot;&gt;…but some gain still might?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, there’s a risk: if we delegate &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; challenging decision, we might lose the valuable tension that drives personal growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s value in wrestling with uncertainty even when the AI reliably suggests &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; good path. That tension carries meaning—or at the very least feels very human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;local-maxima-trap&quot;&gt;Local maxima trap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Further complicating things&lt;/em&gt;, even if AI could perfectly optimize for our preferences, it might trap us in a ‘local maximum’—offering instant relief while stalling long-term growth. Picture an AI that keeps you in barely tolerable relationships or jobs, preventing the discomfort that often sparks transformative change.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In short, short-term comfort might lead to long-term stagnation, much like the marshmallow test suggests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;convenience-vs-agency&quot;&gt;Convenience vs. Agency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All these thoughts bring me back to larger questions of personal agency. As AI improves, will relying on it drain my sense of autonomy? Will life lose some deep, intangible spark if I delegate too many important decisions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My current view: we will have to try and see. What comforts me a bit is reflecting on my life thus far. Despite thinking of myself as the &lt;em&gt;instant gratification monkey&lt;/em&gt;, my life tells a different story—I actually go out of my comfort zone and do stuff despite the lure of The Algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I expect AI to become more powerful, more useful, and I also feel confident that I’ll notice if I start veering toward an unfulfilling, agency-lacking existence—and trust myself to course-correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear your thoughts, and I’m curious how future-me will reflect on another year of closer reliance on AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;To be clear, today’s AIs carry &lt;em&gt;all the biases&lt;/em&gt; inherited from training data; the hope is that they balance each other out. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Current AIs are good at surface-level optimization but may fail to suggest difficult-in-the-moment but ultimately enriching decisions. Future models could potentially integrate secondary- and tertiary-level consequences, vectorize your preferences and &lt;em&gt;your whole psyche&lt;/em&gt;, and ultimately be able to make decisions that are &lt;em&gt;just good for you&lt;/em&gt;. But that is post-singularity AI, firmly in Speculationland. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">When my wife asked, “Which decisions should you not delegate to AI?”, I froze mid-thought.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My favorite fiction books</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/07/09/My-favorite-fiction-books" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My favorite fiction books" /><published>2022-07-09T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2022-07-09T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/07/09/My-favorite-fiction-books</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/07/09/My-favorite-fiction-books">&lt;p&gt;I wanted to write something without too much virtue signaling. When I look at earlier posts, I see something like a trophy board to show everyone how smart and likable I am.&lt;!--excerpt_separator--&gt;
Although everything I wrote about back then was and is really interesting to me, it still seems dishonest somehow. I guess my current mood is different from the one I used to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I want to try something different. I’m going to write about the books I absolutely love. Not about philosophy or the role of technology in today’s world. Just 3 books that have made the last seven years much more pleasant for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This kind of writing is harder to do because it makes me more vulnerable, it’s not only about the books but about me and my history with them. It’s something dear to my heart: what if you don’t like it? What if you criticize me and my haphazard way of gushing about these books?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, for the joy of writing this, I’m still willing to take the risk :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading fantasy and science fiction for more than 25 years. I started with Wells, Stanislaw Lem, the Strugatsky brothers, Ray Bradbury, and Philip K. Dick.
After reading through the classics, I discovered the Hugo and Nebula Awards for SF and went through all the finalists. After that, I gradually moved on to lesser and lesser known books and authors.
After scraping the bottom of the barrel for some time, I lucked into web series, books written one chapter at a time and posted on forums or blogs. And how glad I am that I found them, because all the books on this list below are representatives of this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;harry-potter-and-the-methods-of-rationality&quot;&gt;Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Eliezer Yudkowsky [&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hpmor.com/&quot;&gt;link to the (free) book&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books/hpmor-book-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover showing a hand with fingers poised to snap&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sorry, this is the one book I won’t stop raving about. The following text is just my fanboy noises aimed to get you to read this book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sure that fanfics are nothing more than erotic fantasies of teenagers turned into text. In &lt;em&gt;special&lt;/em&gt; forums and with lots of grammatical errors. Or they are not very funny parody books that want to exploit the fame of the original to cash in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tacky title of this fanfic didn’t help it stand out from that crowd. It was the author’s name that helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eliezer was known to me as the champion of the rationality movement and author of many articles on lesswrong.com.
Just the fact that such a person wrote a fanfic began to change my image of what a fanfic is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also helped that the author suggests in the preface to stop reading the book after the fifth chapter if you weren’t hooked. That’s a good heuristic to use with other books as well — it allows you to start a long book without fear of committing to finish it. And this is a book of considerable length.
Fortunately this is one of those cases where the length of a book seems intimidating at first, but then becomes a joy when you realize that many more pages of this fascinating entertainment await you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enjoy this book, &lt;strong&gt;you don’t have to like or even have read the original&lt;/strong&gt; Harry Potter books.
It’s my top 1 recommendation even for people who don’t read much fiction at all (and they love it too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I once tried to write my own novel. I researched how to structure it, how to edit it. I used my project management skills to break it down into small chunks and wrote them out. I edited them in iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It sucked and the result was crap. I didn’t have the motivation to practice and get better.
But since then, when I re-read HPMOR, I notice all the things the author did that are just. so. good. How it hooks me in emotionally and intellectually. How it changes the cadence without ever being too slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sad at the end of the first read, knowing for a fact that such excitingly captivating books are very few and hard to find.
But there’s hope! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fanfiction.net/s/11174940/1/Significant-Digits&quot;&gt;Significant Digits&lt;/a&gt; by Alexander Davis is “the best HPMOR continuation fic” (quote from Elizer). The other books in this post are also similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elizer is mainly working on AI alignment. I don’t want our world to end as much as the next guy, but it’s a pity Eliezer isn’t writing SF books for a living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worm&quot;&gt;Worm&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By John C. McCrae [&lt;a href=&quot;https://parahumans.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;link to the (free) book&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books/worm-book-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover showing a metropolitan city skyline with an overcast sky&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A grimdark world where superheroes aren’t so good and villains aren’t so evil is a popular theme these days, just think of the recent popularity of The Boys TV series. But Worm was the first book of this genre for me, and boy, did it take me away for &lt;em&gt;a ride&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Endless cliffhangers and conflict escalation led to many nights where I couldn’t stop reading until sleep finally took me at 4am. Usually when a book is this interesting I finish it quickly, but not this one. This book is 4 Wars and Peaces long. So it was &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of sleepless nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I finally finished it, I wanted more. And the fanfic world didn’t disappoint. I’ve been reading Worm fanfics for years. I’m not exaggerating, here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/FanficRecs/Worm&quot;&gt;an (incomplete) list of them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;~&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over dozens of fanfics, the characters and setting have become familiar to me, all the key situations have been lived through from different angles with different consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I liked Worm because it fit my depressed mood at the time, but after years of fanfics, this world has become the ultimate cozy feel-good read, where I return to old friends and places and relieve fond memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(This transition to warm and fuzzy was influenced by some of ack1308’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fanfiction.net/u/5180580/ack1308&quot;&gt;wholesome Worm fanfics&lt;/a&gt;, where each and every conflict is resolved in the best possible way.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;worth-the-candle&quot;&gt;Worth The Candle&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Alexander Wales [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.royalroad.com/fiction/25137/worth-the-candle&quot;&gt;link to the (free) book&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books/worth-the-candle-book-cover.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Book cover showing a man fighting with a much bigger humanoid opponent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LitRPG to rule them all. Interesting mechanics, but not too much of it. So meta and trope-riding, -bending, -exploiting that it’s at least three levels deep.
The author is the king of nuanced worldbuilding. My god! He’s made a variety of worlds with details down history and politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other fiction&lt;/strong&gt;: a horde of ugly goblins invade with mindless fury, killing innocents and destroying millennia-old elven forests. They force the main character to wipe them out. He moves on to the next challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This book&lt;/strong&gt;: a horde of ugly goblins invades. But their ugliness doesn’t dehumanize them, they’re still people. People who have a long history with elves, with war crimes on both sides. The new political regime of Goblinland forced this goblin contingent to flee their lands or be persecuted as a minority. There are also women and children behind the soldiers. The main character understands all this and when the negotiations fail, it’s not an easy moral decision to kill the goblins. Some of the horde warriors are defeated, but that still leaves the surrendering goblins and their families to deal with. You’ll need logistics to organize it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Humanitarian crisis, supply chains, politics, ethics — this book has it all, and that rare depth pleasantly tickles my brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The author seems so much smarter than I’m that he can conjure up all these worlds and unite them in a story with just the right… everything for me. It’s like reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/&quot;&gt;Slate Star Codex&lt;/a&gt;: someone intelligent has thought through a lot of details and made them accessible to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, and this is a recurring feature of all the books on this list, this book is lusciously long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honorable mention&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;mother-of-learning&quot;&gt;Mother of Learning&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By Domagoj Kurmaic [&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.royalroad.com/fiction/21220/mother-of-learning&quot;&gt;link to the (free) book&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A progression fantasy in which the protagonist grows not only in skills, but also in wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first chapter felt a bit awkward in terms of dialogue, but then the story really picked up, the complex situation unravelling with lots of action, and that hooked me in till the satisfying end.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="book" /><summary type="html">I wanted to write something without too much virtue signaling. When I look at earlier posts, I see something like a trophy board to show everyone how smart and likable I am. So I want to try something different.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dark mode implementation for this blog</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/02/06/Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dark mode implementation for this blog" /><published>2022-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-02-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/02/06/Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/02/06/Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog">&lt;p&gt;I’ve implemented the dark theme for this blog. An endeavour for 2-3 hours that has visible results. A satisfying project, I invite everyone with a light-theme-only blog to try.
&lt;!--excerpt_separator--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2022-02-06-Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog/dark-mode-example-picture.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;An article screenshot, one half of which is in light mode and the other half is in dark mode&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CSS Tricks&lt;/em&gt;, of course, has this topic thoroughly covered in their &lt;a href=&quot;https://css-tricks.com/a-complete-guide-to-dark-mode-on-the-web/&quot;&gt;Complete Guide to Dark Mode on the Web&lt;/a&gt;. I’ll describe what I’ve done in this particular blog and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@media (prefers-color-scheme: dark) { ... }&lt;/code&gt; CSS media query which lets me use OS-level user preferences. I chose not to support manual toggling between modes because of two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implementation involves JavaScript swapping CSS classes and storing state in Local Storage–a harder effort than I wanted for this quick-win project&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a user has strong preferences about the dark mode, I imagine such a user already has a way of controlling the interface. Such as a browser plugin that changes the theme, e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://darkreader.org/&quot;&gt;Dark Reader&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As dark mode gains momentum, I think major browsers will display a toggle between modes (not only in Dev Tools) making the effort of creating this toggle myself moot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog uses a modified &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/johno/pixyll&quot;&gt;Pixyll theme&lt;/a&gt; that has &lt;strong&gt;32&lt;/strong&gt; SASS files that get compiled into one big CSS file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://www.lepekhin.com/assets/images/2022-02-06-Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog/sass-includes-listing.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Part of includes listing @importing separate SASS files for links, code, header, etc&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This otherwise reasonable divide-and-conquer approach bites me in the ass here, as I needed to insert the media-query block 17 times. For each style, I wanted to look different when dark. Here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/andrey-lepekhin/andrey-lepekhin.github.io/commit/b54227499b737f5042d151f60c39416e88c9ba4b&quot;&gt;the actual commit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could instead place all dark mode styles in one such file, but then I’ll lose the handy separation these files provide. Also, in the future, if I change a light mode style, the proximity of the corresponding dark mode style will remind me to change it as well. Something I might otherwise forget to do and test for.
If there is a better way, please tell me about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, that’s basically it: adding media-query styles and selecting particular colors that look good on dark background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, while we’re on a technical topic, I want to boast a little. This site got a 100/100 performance score at Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://pagespeed.web.dev&quot;&gt;PageSpeed Insights&lt;/a&gt; for desktop and 97 for mobile. I can mostly attribute it to Jekyll itself and a little bit to my tweaks using locally hosted fonts instead of Google Fonts’ CDN. I host this blog on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; for free, you can use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/barryclark/jekyll-now&quot;&gt;same GitHub Pages-friendly process&lt;/a&gt; I’m using.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="process" /><summary type="html">I’ve implemented the dark theme for this blog. An endeavour for 2-3 hours that has visible results. A satisfying project, I invite everyone with a light-theme-only blog to try.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">3 links: future, present and uncomfortable</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/24/3-links-future-present-and-uncomfortable" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="3 links: future, present and uncomfortable" /><published>2020-02-24T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-02-24T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/24/3-links-future-present-and-uncomfortable</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/24/3-links-future-present-and-uncomfortable">&lt;p&gt;A short post with 10 thought-provoking predictions for this decade (e.g. decentralized internet and the world run by Millennials)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://avc.com/2020/01/what-will-happen-in-the-2020s/&quot;&gt;What Will Happen In The 2020s&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Fred Wilson&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China leading the way with more ways to use QR codes than you can shake a stick at (e.g. meet and flirt online at bars): &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2019/10/30/the-power-of-qr-codes/&quot;&gt;Remember QR Codes? They’re More Powerful Than You Think&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Avery Segal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love awkward questions, they make one vulnerable and create a possibility for closeness and/or satisfaction of one’s needs. Here is a paper that helps stop avoiding sensitive questions.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3437468&quot;&gt;I Didn’t Want to Offend You: The Cost of Avoiding Sensitive Questions&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Einav Hart&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eric VanEpps&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Maurice E. Schweitzer&lt;/em&gt;
A quote from the abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Across three pilot studies and four experimental studies, we demonstrate that individuals avoid asking sensitive questions, because they fear making others uncomfortable and because of impression management concerns. We demonstrate that this aversion to asking sensitive questions is both costly and misguided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">A short post with 10 thought-provoking predictions for this decade (e.g. decentralized internet and the world run by Millennials) What Will Happen In The 2020s by Fred Wilson</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Some programming idioms explained</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Some-programming-idioms-explained" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Some programming idioms explained" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Some-programming-idioms-explained</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Some-programming-idioms-explained">&lt;p&gt;As a perpetually novice programmer, it was nice to see the reasons behind some popular idioms explained. &lt;!--excerpt_separator--&gt;Like why “Maintainability counts” or “Avoid package level state”.
Also this way of seeing developer work as preparation for inevitable change:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Change is the name of the game we’re in. What we do as programmers is manage change. When we do that well we call it design, or architecture. When we do it badly we call it technical debt, or legacy code.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;If you are writing a program that works perfectly, one time, for one fixed set of inputs then nobody cares if the code is good or bad because ultimately the output of the program is all the business cares about.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But this is never true. Software has bugs, requirements change, inputs change, and very few programs are written solely to be executed once, thus your program will change over time. Maybe it’s you who’ll be tasked with this, more likely it will be someone else, but someone has to change that code. Someone has to maintain that code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://dave.cheney.net/2020/02/23/the-zen-of-go&quot;&gt;The Zen of Go&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Dave Cheney&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">As a perpetually novice programmer, it was nice to see the reasons behind some popular idioms explained.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Simple status games</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Simple-status-games" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Simple status games" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Simple-status-games</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Simple-status-games">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thepointmag.com/examined-life/who-wants-to-play-the-status-game-agnes-callard/&quot;&gt;Who Wants to Play the Status Game?&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;em&gt;Agnes Callard&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to think that I see a hidden meaning, a secret game being played behind the curtains of everyday interactions. Naturally, I like articles about signalling and social games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A player of the Importance Game tries to ascend high enough to reach for something that will set her above her interlocutor, a player of the Leveling Game reaches down low enough to hit common ground. The former needs to signal enough power to establish a hierarchy; the latter enough powerlessness to establish equality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In an academic context, I’ve noticed that complaining about how busy one is hits a sweet spot of oppression—I cannot manage my life!—and importance—because I am so in demand! When you’re playing with a master, it can be hard to tell which game you’re in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ending of the article is too unclear for my taste, but then I’m no philosopher.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">Who Wants to Play the Status Game? by Agnes Callard</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pitfalls of our simplistic moral evaluation system</title><link href="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Pitfalls-of-our-simplistic-moral-evaluation-system" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pitfalls of our simplistic moral evaluation system" /><published>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2020-02-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Pitfalls-of-our-simplistic-moral-evaluation-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Pitfalls-of-our-simplistic-moral-evaluation-system">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/M2LWXsJxKS626QNEA/the-trouble-with-good&quot;&gt;The Trouble With “Good”&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Scott Alexander&lt;/em&gt; describes some problems that stem from our evolutionary-induced simplistic good-bad evaluation system (emotivism), that meshes moral beliefs with facts and personal preferences.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ll only paste one quote as the post itself has just the right composition to be clear enough while not being too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So this is one problem: the inputs to our mental karma system aren’t always closely related to the real merit of a person/thing/idea.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Another problem: our interpretation of whether to upvote or downvote something depends on how many upvotes or downvotes it already has. […]&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Another problem: we are tempted to assign everything about a concept the same score. Eliezer Yudkowsky currently has 2486 karma. How good is Eliezer at philosophy? Apparently somewhere around the level it would take to get 2486 karma. How much does he know about economics? Somewhere around level 2486 would be my guess. How well does he write? Probably well enough to get 2486 karma. Translated into mental terms, this looks like the Halo Effect. Yes, we can pick apart our analyses in greater detail; having read Eliezer’s posts, I know he’s better at some things than others. But that 2486 number is going to cause anchoring-and-adjustment issues even so.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;But the big problem, the world-breaking problem, is that sticking everything good and bad about something into one big bin and making decisions based on whether it’s a net positive or a net negative is an unsubtle, leaky heuristic completely unsuitable for complicated problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">In The Trouble With “Good” Scott Alexander describes some problems that stem from our evolutionary-induced simplistic good-bad evaluation system (emotivism), that meshes moral beliefs with facts and personal preferences. I’ll only paste one quote as the post itself has just the right composition to be clear enough while not being too long.</summary></entry></feed>