<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-04-22T08:25:03+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/</id><title type="html">The Blog of Andrey Lepekhin</title><subtitle>personal page</subtitle><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><entry><title type="html">Web comics category</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Web comics category" /><published>2099-01-01T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2099-01-01T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category">&lt;p&gt;Beware, comics posted here tend to be profane and some are even NSFW.&lt;br /&gt;
Have fun! and ignore the ‘continue reading’ link (there’s nothing inside).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">Beware, comics posted here tend to be profane and some are even NSFW. Have fun! and ignore the ‘continue reading’ link (there’s nothing inside).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happiness Is a Chore</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/21/Happiness-is-chore" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happiness Is a Chore" /><published>2018-04-21T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/21/Happiness-is-chore</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/21/Happiness-is-chore">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPD&lt;/strong&gt; This post rises some important questions, so I promote it from link-post to the index page for visibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The pursuit of happiness defines many parts of my life. Or should I say “happiness”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;SquirrelInHell&lt;/em&gt; writes about unbelievable problem that &lt;a href=&quot;https://squirrelinhell.blogspot.se/2017/12/happiness-is-chore.html&quot;&gt;Happiness Is a Chore&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;See, the human activity you describe as “pursuing happiness” […] seems to be in the same category as other common activities such as “acquiring education”, “helping people”, “talking to friends” (or should I say “talking” to “friends”) and so on. Which is to say, people do them in a way which is outwardly convincing enough to allow everyone to keep up the social pretenses. This is way different from what you’d see people do if they actually cared. The simple matter of fact is that the human brain is a kludge, and people are puppets dancing on the strings of a mad puppetmaster. Almost anything they claim to be doing isn’t for real. This is true even when they themselves know about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is strongly related to &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/09/Why-dont-we-try-really-doing-things&quot;&gt;The Thing and the Symbolic Representation of The Thing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[…] I enjoy and see great value in happiness when it happens, but when it doesn’t I only work on it grudgingly. It’s like with exercise, which is great but I’m rarely enthusiastic about starting it. The problem is not that I don’t value happiness enough. The problem is rather that there is no gut-level motivational gradient to get actual happiness. There are gradients for all sorts of things which are crappy, fake substitutes. […] But you still end up optimizing for them, because that’s what your brain does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;↑ This indeed, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/3Hkpttb6WsJwr5WdF/happiness-is-a-chore#BP2j9rDHr9SqMjDh9&quot;&gt;one LW commenter points out&lt;/a&gt;, looks like akrasia. And will probably benefit from methods that are good against akrasia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Related, SquirrelInHell’s site &lt;a href=&quot;http://bewelltuned.com/&quot;&gt;Be Well Tuned&lt;/a&gt; (“a very unusual guide to improving your brain and your life”). I’ve added it to my to-do list &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/tag/goal&quot;&gt;#goals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After (re)reading through everything linked above, I see that, at this moment, I’m &lt;em&gt;focused&lt;/em&gt; on riding my hedonic treadmill, solving various optimization problems, and I’m &lt;strong&gt;not mindful&lt;/strong&gt; about it; also not happy. This is a tendency I have. I will think about my terminal values and what to do about it with my psychotherapist.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="squirrelinhell" /><category term="goal" /><summary type="html">UPD This post rises some important questions, so I promote it from link-post to the index page for visibility. The pursuit of happiness defines many parts of my life. Or should I say “happiness”?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Planning fallacy</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/14/Planning-fallacy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Planning fallacy" /><published>2018-04-14T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/14/Planning-fallacy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/14/Planning-fallacy">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eliezer Yudkowsky&lt;/em&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/CPm5LTwHrvBJCa9h5/planning-fallacy&quot;&gt;Planning Fallacy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The planning fallacy is that people think they can plan, ha ha.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While planning, and in need of &lt;em&gt;realistic&lt;/em&gt; scenario, people instead think of &lt;em&gt;best-case scenario&lt;/em&gt;. (See the article for related studies.)&lt;br /&gt;
Now on to how to fix it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;So there is a fairly reliable way to fix the planning fallacy, if you’re doing something broadly similar to a reference class of previous projects. Just ask how long similar projects have taken in the past, without considering any of the special properties of this project.  Better yet, ask an experienced outsider how long similar projects have taken.&lt;br /&gt;
You’ll get back an answer that sounds hideously long, and clearly reflects no understanding of the special reasons why this particular task will take less time. This answer is true.  Deal with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="yudkowsky" /><summary type="html">Eliezer Yudkowsky about Planning Fallacy The planning fallacy is that people think they can plan, ha ha.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On-demand everything</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On-demand everything" /><published>2018-04-07T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lauren Smiley&lt;/em&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/matter/the-shut-in-economy-ec3ec1294816&quot;&gt;The Shut-In Economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
“In the new world of on-demand everything, you’re either pampered, isolated royalty — or you’re a 21st century servant.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Click-bait false dichotomy aside, this is an interesting area to think about. Is the future of work looks like a bunch of APIs for people?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can image it being quite dystopian: install an app, answer some questions about your abilities, qualifications, schedule, etc. and &lt;em&gt;poof&lt;/em&gt; your time is auto-magically assigned to be spent in the most efficient way (most cost-efficient way for the API-hubs companies, that is).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extreme optimization also may look like little additions to your daily life: The App nudges you to buy extra ice-cream on your way home; when you are on a red light, another &lt;del&gt;drone&lt;/del&gt; App user comes up to you and takes the ice-cream. She’s going home herself but is making a small detour to deliver that ice-cream to the one that ordered it. That order was placed automatically too, after analyzing customer’s biometric and social graph data (ML model says: though breakup) and coming to a conclusion that to maximize LTV, this purchase was needed. It also may lead to a need for a fitness programme purchase later, but again, that’s just LTV maximizing, nothing personal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, back to our totally different world and the article at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The luxuries usually afforded to one-percenters now stretch to the urban upper-middle class, or so the technology industry cheers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pnas.org/content/114/32/8523.full&quot;&gt;a study&lt;/a&gt; saying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Around the world, increases in wealth have produced an unintended consequence: a rising sense of time scarcity. We provide evidence that using money to buy time can provide a buffer against this time famine, thereby promoting happiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also the gender angle:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That’s the other side of this, the gender one. The errands being served up by the on-demand economy — cooking, cleaning, laundry, groceries, runs to the post office — all were all once, and in many places still are, the jobs of stay-at-home mothers. Even now, when women outnumber men in the formal workplace, they continue to bear the brunt of that invisible domestic work, often for many, many hours a week. So women — those who can afford it, at least — have the most to win from passing that load on to somebody else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually pre-order food to work, and sometimes hire a cleaning service — it saves a lot of time indeed, and, as I start to have less free time, I increasingly value it. I’m thinking of outsourcing making my breakfast and dinner too.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><summary type="html">Lauren Smiley about The Shut-In Economy “In the new world of on-demand everything, you’re either pampered, isolated royalty — or you’re a 21st century servant.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How successful people work less — and get more done</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/How-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How successful people work less — and get more done" /><published>2018-04-07T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-04-07T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/How-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/How-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Travis Bradberry&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/386166/how-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done/&quot;&gt;How successful people work less—and get more done&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Quite a diverse list of things, actually:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They disconnect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything&quot;&gt;minimize chores&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They reflect&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They exercise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They pursue a passion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They spend quality time with family&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They schedule micro-adventures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They wake up at the same time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They designate mornings as “me time”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;They prepare for the upcoming week&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;del&gt;But most importantly, they attac&lt;/del&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See the article for more details. This list is by no means scientific, I included it here as a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/tag/goal/&quot;&gt;goal-reminder&lt;/a&gt;: I already do more than half of it, probably should look into what’s left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The study found that productivity per hour declines sharply when the workweek exceeds 50 hours, and productivity drops off so much after 55 hours that there’s no point in working any more. That’s right, people who work as much as 70 hours (or more) per week actually get the same amount done as people who work 55 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that they studied people productivity in &lt;em&gt;manufacturing&lt;/em&gt;, e.g. “Forty Women Milling a Screw Thread on Fuze Bodies”, I’m not sure how well it translates to creative work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first I grabbed this article and sent it to people who (I think) overwork. To which they countered that output of 55 hours is still bigger than that of 40 hours of work. Of course you have to pay the price, but still, if you’re willing and can do so sustainably, you really can get more done by working more than 8 hours a day (or without weekends).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="goal" /><summary type="html">Travis Bradberry on How successful people work less—and get more done Quite a diverse list of things, actually:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tony Robbins interview with Tim Ferriss - my takeaways</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/31/Tony-Robbins-interview-with-Tim-Ferriss-my-takeaways" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tony Robbins interview with Tim Ferriss - my takeaways" /><published>2018-03-31T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-03-31T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/31/Tony-Robbins-interview-with-Tim-Ferriss-my-takeaways</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/31/Tony-Robbins-interview-with-Tim-Ferriss-my-takeaways">&lt;p&gt;I’ve first heard Tony Robbins’ interviews sometime in 2016. I was fascinated: a great story-teller and he speaks about things that interest me — mood-states that affect behavior, and how to change your energy levels. Here are my takeaways from one of his &lt;a href=&quot;https://encrypted.google.com/search?q=Tony+Robbins+site%3Atim.blog&quot;&gt;interviews with Tim Ferriss&lt;/a&gt;. Each paragraph is a paraphrased quote from Tony followed by my comment in &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You have to give to prosper. Even if you think you don’t have enough.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That is something I struggle with as it’s not obvious to me &lt;strong&gt;why&lt;/strong&gt; I should divert resources from myself. I’m going to speak with effective altruists (EA) and try and get convinced.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Number one quality to foster is staying hungry, this will bring others along. How to do it? Be among people who are successful. You are who you spend time with. To be happy you need to grow.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is also something that is hard for me - by default I don’t value friendship that much. At least I understand the logic here and I’m making progress: meeting new people and starting (non-romantic) relationships with them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Failure is a part of life. It doesn’t need to stop you. It’s a stepping stone to success, speed bump. I know I’m going to fail, but it’s not failure if you learn something. We don’t value what we don’t fight for. Like cheating in video games. There’s no such thing as effortless approach.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I did have a belief along the lines of “life &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; be easy”. And that was (and still is sometimes) a source of discontent for me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Money doesn’t change you, it magnifies what you already are.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That is also why I think I should start donating now, and looks like that is what EA guys preach too (donate at least 1% to create a habit)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The most important decision in your life is deciding whether you’re truly committed to being happy no matter what. You will experience extreme stress, no matter what. Life’s too short to suffer. Decide to be in a beautiful state. &lt;strong&gt;This brain is not designed to make you happy, it’s designed to make you survive&lt;/strong&gt;. You have to work to be happy.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See also Tim Urban about &lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/06/taming-mammoth-let-peoples-opinions-run-life.html&quot;&gt;Social Survival Mammoth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Highest experiences in life have this in common: there is some growth within ourselves (face fear, overcome something, etc) and some contribution beyond ourselves.
Worst experiences are about only you. When you are suffering it’s because you’re obsessing about yourself. Something happened and you have less of something, or you lost something (love, money, significance, attention). Loss, less, never are the sources of suffering. All suffering is obsession with self. Snap out of your suffering. Stop expecting and start appreciating things outside of yourself: people, nature. You learn and grow from that. If you love, if you give, if you’re grateful - suffering disappears instantly.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It’s a good a place to paste my favorite quote from a Haruki Murakami book cover: “Pain is inevitable. Suffering is optional.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in 2016 I’ve decided to attend one of Tony’s seminars to get some of that energy from the man himself. I attended UPW London 2017 and it was like a giant rave with applied psychology and lots of hugs. I loved it.&lt;br /&gt;
After I go through my notes, I’ll post my takeaways from there as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="goal" /><category term="tony-robbins" /><summary type="html">I’ve first heard Tony Robbins’ interviews sometime in 2016. I was fascinated: a great story-teller and he speaks about things that interest me — mood-states that affect behavior, and how to change your energy levels. Here are my takeaways from one of his interviews with Tim Ferriss. Each paragraph is a paraphrased quote from Tony followed by my comment in italics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Religion, growth framework and enlightenment</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Religion-growth-framework-and-enlightenment" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Religion, growth framework and enlightenment" /><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Religion-growth-framework-and-enlightenment</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Religion-growth-framework-and-enlightenment">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tim Urban&lt;/em&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/10/religion-for-the-nonreligious.html&quot;&gt;Religion for the Nonreligious&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Like many of his great posts, this one is long. I’ve read it in 2015 when I was struggling to find my way around religion and it stroke a chord. &lt;em&gt;For me&lt;/em&gt;, it’s about two things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-states-of-mind&quot;&gt;1. States of mind&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) Engulfed in primitive, primal thoughts&lt;br /&gt;
(2) See things as they are, enlightenment&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-creating-a-better-belief-system&quot;&gt;2. Creating a better belief system&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…smelted with a &lt;em&gt;growth framework&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
Coincidentally, growth framework is something that I lacked in 2015. I now have a system in place, it’s still new and I’m not as religious about it as Tim. I will make a post about it after 1 year test-drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Short quote&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Yes, I’m an atheist, but atheism isn’t a growth model any more than “I don’t like rollerblading” is a workout strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="todo" /><summary type="html">Tim Urban about Religion for the Nonreligious Like many of his great posts, this one is long. I’ve read it in 2015 when I was struggling to find my way around religion and it stroke a chord. For me, it’s about two things:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Giving up too hastily on hard goals</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Giving-up-too-hastily-on-hard-goals" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Giving up too hastily on hard goals" /><published>2018-03-25T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-03-25T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Giving-up-too-hastily-on-hard-goals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Giving-up-too-hastily-on-hard-goals">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eliezer Yudkowsky&lt;/em&gt;’s  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/fhEPnveFhb9tmd7Pe/use-the-try-harder-luke&quot;&gt;Use the Try Harder, Luke&lt;/a&gt;
— is a short funny story about how we’re conditioned for giving up fast, after (also hastily) labeling something as impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This continues with a longer piece &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/fpecAJLG9czABgCe9/on-doing-the-impossible&quot;&gt;On Doing the Impossible&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To do things that are very difficult or “impossible”,&lt;br /&gt;
First you have to not run away.  That takes seconds.&lt;br /&gt;
Then you have to work.  That takes hours.&lt;br /&gt;
Then you have to stick at it.  That takes years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="yudkowsky" /><summary type="html">Eliezer Yudkowsky’s Use the Try Harder, Luke — is a short funny story about how we’re conditioned for giving up fast, after (also hastily) labeling something as impossible.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Taking Children Seriously - philosophy of parenting</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/24/Taking-children-seriously-philosophy-of-parenting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Taking Children Seriously - philosophy of parenting" /><published>2018-03-24T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-03-24T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/24/Taking-children-seriously-philosophy-of-parenting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/24/Taking-children-seriously-philosophy-of-parenting">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elliot Temple&lt;/em&gt; about &lt;a href=&quot;http://fallibleideas.com/taking-children-seriously&quot;&gt;Taking Children Seriously&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Taking Children Seriously (TCS) is a rational, non-coercive philosophy of parenting and learning which says:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;* The main goal of parenting is to help children learn.  
* Punishing doesn’t help with learning.  
* Reason helps everyone win.  
* Ignorance isn’t stupidity.  
* Children aren’t fragile.  
* Obedience and rules are bad.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks like a great rational framework for parenting. Many ‘enable everything’ or ‘obedience is the only way’ ways of parenting just don’t sit well with me, this one does. 
It also underscores my existing belief that &lt;em&gt;parenting is hard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the sake of history, my current argument &lt;strong&gt;against having children&lt;/strong&gt; goes like this: &lt;br /&gt;
raising children requires a lot of time and this time commitment is at least for &lt;strong&gt;18.75 years&lt;/strong&gt;.
Anecdotal &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;it's worth it&lt;/code&gt; from the parents I know can really be some sort of Stockholm syndrome. I mean, if you have a child already and you don’t like it, you have the choice of suffering (bad for you and the child) or learning how to love it and make the best of the situation. Leaving a child looks like a heavy conscience penalty so it’s out of the consideration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please tell me if you have a counter to this line of thinking. It does look shaky and I definitely will need to do a full analysis of this question later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. Here are some &lt;a href=&quot;http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/16/bundles-of-joy/&quot;&gt;stats on life satisfaction depending on number of children from SSC&lt;/a&gt; (spoiler: more children - more satisfaction).&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="parenting" /><summary type="html">Elliot Temple about Taking Children Seriously</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why it’s easy to start a subpar relationship</title><link href="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/17/Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why it's easy to start a subpar relationship" /><published>2018-03-17T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-03-17T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/17/Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/17/Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship">&lt;p&gt;And what to do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what’s happening when I’m not in a relationship for some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph 1, described in text below&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acceptable partner attractiveness (APA) is everything I seek for in a partner: physical beauty, personal qualities, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When I am in a relationship, APA is at max level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As a relationship ends, my APA lingers at max for a bit and then starts to lower.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After I start a new relationship, APA goes back to max levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;problems&quot;&gt;Problems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-becomes-harder-to-date-more-attractive-partners&quot;&gt;It becomes harder to date more attractive partners&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/images/scumbag_brain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Scumbag brain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primitive mind auto-applies dates’ &lt;em&gt;courting easiness&lt;/em&gt; labels based on &lt;em&gt;attractiveness&lt;/em&gt;. The less attractive the date, the easier it seems to court her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am programmed to do least possible amount work to achieve my goals so, if acting by default, I will court dates with lower perceived attractiveness because it seems like less work, and still gets acceptable result. &lt;strong&gt;Why try hard when easy’s good enough?&lt;/strong&gt; My amygdala doesn’t care that the result is only acceptable right in that moment and will become unacceptable soon after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;its-easier-to-begin-an-unacceptable-relationship&quot;&gt;It’s easier to begin an unacceptable relationship&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s just me, but when you’re fresh out of a relationship, you don’t seem too eager to jump start a new one. But as the loneliness goes on, desire for &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; relationship grows.
&lt;strong&gt;So not only your requirements are lowered, you actually &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; being in a relationship more, exactly at the time when they are low&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph 2, yearning for a relationship grows with time&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;yearning-for-relationship-correlates-with-easiness-of-starting-a-subpar-relationship-&quot;&gt;Yearning for relationship correlates with easiness of starting a subpar relationship :(&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the acceptable standard lowers, the pool of available partners grows and it’s easier to start a new relationship.
There would not be a problem if acceptable SO attractiveness didn’t rise to the max after that, but it does and the consequences are dire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being in a relationship that doesn’t satisfy you sucks.
The internal conflict rises: should I stay or should I go? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BN1WwnEDWAM&quot;&gt;♫&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s not an &lt;a href=&quot;/2018/03/01/Why-choices-are-bad&quot;&gt;easy choice&lt;/a&gt;, you have emotional attachment and a whole host of cognitive biases working against you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Wanting to stay in a relationship is reinforced by many biases (status quo bias, ambiguity effect, choice supportive bias, loss aversion, mere-exposure effect, ostrich effect). For someone to break through all those biases and end things, they must be extremely unhappy.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;footer&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lesswrong.com/lw/m78/strategies_and_tools_for_getting_through_a_break/&quot;&gt;Strategies and tools for getting through a break up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/footer&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more this draws on the more stakes are in opportunity cost and the more it becomes harder to break things apart. Some stay in this state of conflict throughout their whole lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worth mentioning: I am not an &lt;em&gt;extreme&lt;/em&gt; idealist, I understand there can be compromises. Here I am speaking of cases when you can’t compromise after standards go up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-do-the-standards-fall&quot;&gt;Why do the standards fall&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Graph 3, progression of acceptable partner attractiveness criteria for high (just after relationship) to low (just before starting a relationship) to high again&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that it’s a response to one of the basic needs not being met.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ll try a metaphor. Imagine you do not have a place to sleep. In the morning you do not need to sleep so your idea of a place to sleep is a 5-star hotel. In the afternoon you become a little sleepier and make vague attempts on finding &lt;em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; hotel, &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; hotel. In the evening you’re sleepy and really need a place to rest, and will agree on a capsule hotel or a hostel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or maybe it’s just evolution nudging: “Come on, stop thinking, just fuck whatever”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-do-the-standards-rise-again&quot;&gt;Why do the standards rise again&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like a natural thing to happen after a bare minimum of a need is met.
In a place-to-sleep example above: after a night in a capsule hotel you do feel refreshed, but you also understand that you &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; silence to sleep really well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-to-do&quot;&gt;What to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Forewarned is forearmed. Just keeping this whole thing in mind helps me in some cases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I’ve created and maintain my &lt;em&gt;partner criteria list&lt;/em&gt; and filter out my new dates under a threat of suffering (unsatisfactory relationship).&lt;br /&gt;
This doesn’t help with increased perceived difficultness of dating more attractive partners; I’m still searching a solution for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s solvable by sex without relationships?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Friends with benefits - doesn’t work for me, as it usually grows into a relationship.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One-night-stands - I didn’t have that many encounters so I cannot generalize. Probably should look into it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paying for sex (here’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/biohack-your-intelligence-now-or-become-obsolete-97cdd15e395f&quot;&gt;Serge Faguet’s take on it&lt;/a&gt;) - same as above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What did I miss?&lt;/strong&gt; How do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; solve this problem? Please &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lepekhin.com/about#contact-me&quot;&gt;share&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ps-dear-ladies&quot;&gt;P.S. Dear ladies&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are my partner and you’re wondering what if I secretly think of you as a subpar choice, I have good news.
This post is a public commitment: I will only start relationships with those who meet my criteria for a partner. It still doesn’t make our relationship bulletproof and there are ways it can go awry, but at least I (and you) have one less thing to worry about.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Andrey Lepekhin</name></author><category term="goal" /><category term="process" /><category term="relationships" /><summary type="html">And what to do about it.</summary></entry></feed>