<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>The Blog of Andrey Lepekhin</title>
    <link>https://www.lepekhin.com</link>
    <description>
      Thoughts on life improvement
    </description>
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comics category</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Beware, comics posted here tend to be profane and some are even NSFW.<br />
Have fun! and ignore the ‘continue reading’ link (there’s nothing inside).</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2099/01/01/Web-comics-category</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2099 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>DIY Door Fan to Fix My Groggy Mornings</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>It all started with a comment from my doctor. He told me that, ideally, I should wake up like Mickey Mouse: bright, energetic, and ready to leap out of bed.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-pseudo-Mickey.jpg" alt="Animated mouse waking up, looking chipper. Generated by ChatGPT." width="50%" />
  <figcaption>Legally distinct, chipper morning mouse.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I thought about my own mornings. The reality was a slow, groggy 30-minute crawl out of sleep. Mickey Mouse? I was more like a grumpy bear waking up from a long hibernation.</p>

<p>Then one day, the ventilation failed in my office. After a few hours in the stuffy air, I had the exact same groggy feeling and a splitting headache. The pieces clicked into place. My office felt just like my bedroom in the morning. The enemy was CO2.</p>

<p>My bedroom was the perfect trap. As a light sleeper in the city, I seal it for silence. The window is closed to block out seagulls, and the door is shut to mute the rest of the apartment. Ventilation-wise my room has only a “trickle vent” – a small slit above the window to suck in fresh air based on pressure difference. But it didn’t feel like it was enough.</p>

<p>And so, a new obsession was born. I have a habit of looking for a “silver bullet”, a single fix that I believe will solve <em>everything</em>. If I could just lower the CO2 in my bedroom, I’d be more productive, make better decisions, and be happier. These waves of inspiration are my favorite part of any project. The bullet never solves all the problems, but the process is usually worth it.</p>

<p>It was time to build a solution.</p>

<h3 id="measuring-the-problem">Measuring the Problem</h3>

<p>Before I could solve the problem, I had to measure it. I remembered <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28457135">a Hacker News post</a> about a DIY CO2 monitor and ordered the parts.</p>

<p>My soldering skills were rusty, so a helpful stranger at the local maker space coached me through pin soldering without frying the sensors.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-diy_v4_assembled.jpg" alt="Assembled DIY Air quality monitor by AirGradient" />
  <figcaption><a href="https://www.airgradient.com/documentation/diy-v4/">AirGradient DIY monitor</a>, licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">CC BY-SA 4.0</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I put the new sensor on my nightstand. The next morning, the results were bad. While fresh air sits at 400 ppm and stuffiness symptoms begin around 1,000 ppm, my room was peaking at <strong>1,700 ppm</strong>.  <br />
While it isn’t <em>dangerous</em>, it still might’ve been the reason for my morning grogginess.</p>

<iframe title="Overnight CO2" aria-label="Interactive line chart" id="datawrapper-chart-SpOXU" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/SpOXU/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="396" data-external="1"></iframe>
<script type="text/javascript">!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}}))}();
</script>

<h3 id="the-main-idea">The Main Idea</h3>

<p>My rental agreement meant I couldn’t drill holes in walls. The only way for air to get in or out was the 18mm gap under my door. This led to my main idea: <strong>if I could actively push stale air <em>out</em> from under the door, the negative pressure in the room would pull fresh air <em>in</em> through the trickle vent.</strong></p>

<p>The heart of this system would be a fan. It needed to be powerful enough but also quiet. My mind went straight to Noctua, a brand PC builders use for silent fans. I chose the NF-F12 PWM model, which has high static pressure (good for pushing air through tight spaces) and low noise.</p>

<p>Now for the main design challenge: how to funnel the air from a round 120mm fan into a long, thin gap.</p>

<h3 id="the-pizza-box-prototype">The Pizza Box Prototype</h3>

<p>I started designing a duct in <a href="https://github.com/CadQuery/cadquery">CadQuery</a>, a Python library for making 3D models. I hoped current LLMs could create the 3D model from my description alone, but I was quickly proven wrong. So I did it the old-fashioned way, defining it myself part by part.</p>

<figure>
<img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-v1.jpg" alt="A CAD drawing of the first, complicated 3D model showing a fan housing, a 90-degree turn, and a rectangular outlet." />
  <figcaption>Blue was the part to be used to tie the rope to. French flag is accidental</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>In my first design, I planned to mount the fan and duct directly onto the door with ropes so it would move with it (blue part would push against the door and the notch at the end is for rope). Before starting a long 3D print, I decided to build a quick and dirty prototype.</p>

<p>Using two pizza boxes and some tape, I mocked up the shape. I held my cardboard contraption against the door with the rope, just as I’d planned. Then, I let the rope go slack.</p>

<p>It just sat there. On the floor. Perfectly stable.</p>

<p>It was a facepalm moment. I had to laugh at myself for over-engineering it. Why did I think it needed a complex mounting system? It could just be a simple, floor-standing unit.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-pizza_prototype_suspended.jpg" alt="A photo of the prototype made from pizza boxes and tape, suspended near the floor by the door." /></p>

<p>The prototype also <em>worked</em>, lowering the CO2 by about 150 ppm with the fan at 40% speed (for lower noise). Now it was time to improve on the design.</p>

<h3 id="first-3d-print">First 3D Print</h3>

<p>My first 3D-printed version came from a research rabbit hole. I’d read that industrial ventilation needs huge, smooth turns to prevent turbulence. The result was a beast—a three-part device with 4mm thick walls that looked like a defensive tower from a strategy game.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-v2_printed.jpg" alt="A photo of the large, three-part 3D printed &quot;tower&quot; duct, alonside the pizza box prototype." /></p>

<p>It worked a little better than the prototype, lowering CO2 by about 200 ppm by itself. But looking at it I realized it was overkill. For my setup, I didn’t need industrial-grade design, the air speed was almost imperceptibly low. I could make the duct much simpler and smaller.</p>

<h3 id="further-improvements">Further Improvements</h3>

<p>My first thought was to just add more fans side-by-side, but that would get expensive and might be premature. I decided to improve the design first.</p>

<p>The first breakthrough came one morning, as I was lying in bed; my brain must have been working on the problem in the background. <em>Why the 90-degree turn?</em> The fan could work in any orientation. By placing the fan on its side, I could get rid of the turn completely. This would save a massive amount of plastic and print time, and also reduce air friction losses from the bend.</p>

<p>I went back to CadQuery and designed a much sleeker version. The defensive tower had evolved into a… simple funnel.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-v4-cad.jpg" alt="A CAD drawing of the new, simpler funnel-shaped duct." /></p>

<p>After printing two new funnels, experimentation led to two more improvements:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Instead of just pushing stale air <em>out</em>, using one fan to actively pull fresh air <em>in</em> from the hallway dropped the CO2 by another 100 ppm.</li>
  <li>There was no draft in the room. Air exchange away from the door was slow, likely relying on simple diffusion. I realized I could accelerate this. I already had quiet standing fan so I placed it near the door, aimed inwards. That, surprisingly, cut another 200 ppm without adding more fans.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-final-current-system">The <del>Final</del> Current System</h3>

<p>Today, the area by my door is a mess of wires and fans, but it works. A single power adapter feeds a PWM controller, which then splits the signal to my three fans.</p>

<iframe title="Peak CO2 based on setup" aria-label="Bar Chart" id="datawrapper-chart-DNhwZ" src="https://datawrapper.dwcdn.net/DNhwZ/1/" scrolling="no" frameborder="0" style="width: 0; min-width: 100% !important; border: none;" height="233" data-external="1"></iframe>
<script type="text/javascript">!function(){"use strict";window.addEventListener("message",(function(a){if(void 0!==a.data["datawrapper-height"]){var e=document.querySelectorAll("iframe");for(var t in a.data["datawrapper-height"])for(var r,i=0;r=e[i];i++)if(r.contentWindow===a.source){var d=a.data["datawrapper-height"][t]+"px";r.style.height=d}}}))}();
</script>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2025-06-23-v4-v3-prototype.jpg" alt="My current setup, from left to right: the new funnel duct (v4), the &quot;defensive tower&quot; (v2), and the original pizza box prototype. The second funnel and the standing fan are not shown." /></p>

<h4 id="whats-next">What’s Next?</h4>
<ul>
  <li>
    <p>I still don’t fully understand why the system works as it does. Is it really creating negative pressure and pulling fresh air through the trickle vent, like I first thought? Or is it just mixing the air near the door and propagating it? The next step is to find a way to measure the actual airflow.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The other improvement is more practical. Right now, my setup is a functional but messy collection of parts. I’d like to design and print a single, clean enclosure to hold all the fans. It would look better and be much easier to move out of the way when I need to.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="build-your-own">Build Your Own</h3>
<ul>
  <li><strong>3D Models &amp; Code:</strong> on <a href="https://github.com/andrey-lepekhin/diy-door-fan">GitHub</a></li>
  <li><strong>Primary Fan:</strong> Noctua NF-F12 PWM — for its high static pressure</li>
  <li><strong>Fan Controller:</strong> Noctua NA-FC1 — for easy manual fan speed control</li>
  <li><strong>Power supply:</strong> Noctua NV-PS1 — also packs 1-to-3 splitter cable</li>
  <li><strong>CO2 Monitor:</strong> <a href="https://www.airgradient.com/documentation/diy-v4/">AirGradient DIY v4</a></li>
  <li><strong>Standing fan:</strong> Xiaomi Mi Smart Standing Fan 2 — at 1% speed it’s almost as quiet as the smaller fans</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="so-am-i-mickey-mouse-now">So, Am I Mickey Mouse Now?</h3>

<p>I don’t wake up with a cartoonish smile every day. But my mornings <em>are</em> better. The grogginess is mostly gone, and I feel more rested. Of course, it could be the summer starting (circadian rhythm/melatonin change, etc), placebo or some combinations of factors.</p>

<p>Most importantly, I loved the process. I learned about ventilation, got better at 3D modeling <em>for</em> 3D printing, and felt the satisfaction of building something real that solved my own problem. That journey, with all its mistakes and small victories, was the real reward.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2025/06/22/DIY-Door-Fan-to-Fix-My-Groggy-Mornings</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>H</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/05/01/h</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <h1 id="my-quest-for-silence-an-engineers-journey-into-acoustics-to-build-soundproof-sleep-capsule">My Quest for Silence: An Engineer’s Journey into Acoustics to build Soundproof Sleep Capsule</h1>

<p>It started with sleep problems. I’m very sensitive to sounds during sleep, and throughout my life, I’ve faced various environment-based or neighbor-based noises waking me up. I’ve tried everything: custom-made earplugs, white noise machines, heavy curtains &amp; rugs, meditation, psychotherapy, supplements, perscription drugs – you name it. Everything with various success and not without downsides. The best solution was always <em>be</em> somewhere silent. But since I rent and want to live in a city, that’s hard. An apartment can be silent when you evaluate it and noisy at night.</p>

<p>Anyway, that was a preface to set the scene, so my jump to designing a soundproof sleep capsule doesn’t seem <em>as</em> crazy.</p>

<h2 id="the-cost-of-noise-maybe-make-this-section-collapseble-i-feel-it-might-distract-from-the-main-theme">The Cost of Noise [maybe make this section collapseble, I feel it might distract from the main theme]</h2>

<p>It’s not just about being woken up; it’s the anxiety that builds about the downstream consequences. If I don’t get enough sleep, my next day is shot, my decisions suffer, and it can spiral from there.</p>

<p>I tend to imagine the worst possible outcomes. One anecdote sticks out: In a fashionable part of town I’d just moved into, I heard techno music coming from upstairs on a Friday night.  I become pretty worked up about things that hinder my sleep, and I definitely got worked up that night.</p>

<p>After trying earplugs, and audiobooks, the bass still kicked through everything, especially my mood. Bracing for the worst – picturing some unhinged, muscular punk who didn’t care about neighbors – I went upstairs. Emotionally, I was ready for a physical fight.</p>

<p>The door opened to reveal a lovely young lady. She was completely understanding. We immediately worked out a solution: she moved her small party to a different room further from my apartment. I got her contact info, and she insisted I call if there was ever a problem again. It resolved nicely, a good reminder that my fears are often unfounded and exaggerated, but it highlights the stress noise sensitivity can cause. Building a soundproof capsule is a drastic measure, costly and even potentially dangerous, – all to achieve something that is casually taken for granted.</p>

<h2 id="tackling-the-problem-the-hard-way-engineering-silence">Tackling the Problem the Hard Way: Engineering Silence</h2>

<p>After moving to Finland and facing familiar noise issues, I thought, maybe I should solve this once and for all, the hard way: by mechanically stopping the sound.</p>

<p>So, I embarked on this project. My first thought was that people already solved this for sound recording studios. I dove into books on the topic, found the  bible of building soundproof studios [add a reference], and followed it.</p>

<p>Low-frequency noise (AKA bass), the hardest to stop and my main issue during sleep, was the target. High-frequency noise is usually handled by closing windows.</p>

<p>From an engineering acoustics perspective, stopping low-frequency waves requires <strong>mass</strong> and <strong>decoupling</strong>. Decoupling means the internal wall isn’t rigidly connected to the external one, preventing vibration transmission. I was thinking a ‘room within a room’ – essentially a small soundproof studio inside my existing room. That is, of course, not the entirety of that book, the field has an endless supply of details.</p>

<p>[Image: Early draft design prototype sketch]</p>

<p>After I understood a rough shape of requirements, I started working with a contractor from Upwork to understand how designing physical objects works – something I’d never done before at this scale. Through him, I realized this was a complicated engineering project. The necessary mass for the desired sound attenuation meant the whole thing would weigh over half a ton. This introduced many engineering challenges, for example: a 100kg door needs special construction to help move it, avoid injury or tipping the structure. Entire engineering fields are dedicated to this. The deeper I dug, the more I realized how much I didn’t know.</p>

<p>Working with the contractor was an absolute blast, though. I lucked out, he was very supportive, and possessed a wealth of practical knowledge about building real-world products. He brought practicality to my naive approach, emphasizing cost considerations from the start. I’d assumed materials like plywood, drywall, or mineral wool wouldn’t be that expensive, but costs add up quickly. So thinking about materials during the design phase pays off. He was the one who suggested we build a prototype first – a standard concept in software, but here, it was my turn to be that stakeholder  who wants everything perfect on the first try, I had to be persuaded.</p>

<h2 id="the-prototype-unexpected-help-and-humbling-realities">The Prototype, Unexpected Help, and Humbling Realities</h2>

<p>What about ventilation? We don’t want it to become a soundproof coffin afterall. But ventilation needs gaps, and gaps let noise in. Designing ventilation for soundproof studios is <em>another</em> engineering challenge: letting air in while trapping noise, circulating air effectively, implementing failsafes, alerts, addressing condensation, cleaning… If I were sleeping in it, grime would accumulate. What is this I hear about a hermetic seal?.. My project folder grew exponentially with these myriad engineering challenges.</p>

<p>I isolated and tackled problems one by one, starting with basics. I decided to build a prototype cube with half-meter sides, two decoupled walls, and filling between them, to test the principle: mass + decoupled walls + somewhat hermetic seal = sound attenuation.</p>

<p>I did not have the tools needed to build it, so I asked in a local chat group. A complete stranger volunteered to help! First, with lots of advice on where to buy materials, and then he suggested I could use his backyard for construction. He ended up driving with me to the shop and teaching me a few tricks with a saw. My immense gratitude goes out to him.</p>

<p>[Image: Working on the prototype in his backyard]</p>

<p>This was another humbling moment. I thought making a cube out of plywood would be easy. But even cutting the six sides presents non-obvious complexities. Knots in the wood can interfere, and fraction-of-a-millimeter errors in cuts add up really fast, potentially hindering the whole assembly. I found a new respect for tradespeople. So much seemingly simple stuff I took for granted – a wooden ladder, a road, even a metal hose clamp – is far from simple to build right.</p>

<p>[Image: Photo of the finished test cube prototype]</p>

<p>With the cube built, I bought a calibrated microphone and tested sound pressure level (SPL) attenuation at different frequencies. It goes in two phases 1) put the mic 2m from a good flat-response speaker, play brown noise and record. 2) put the mic into the prototype box and play the same noise. Compare:</p>

<p>[Graph: SPL attenuation results from the cube test]</p>

<p>Doing this, I discovered that attenuation varied wildly across frequencies due to the cube’s size and materials. For some frequencies, it was orders of magnitude different. It was very rewarding to build something physical. However, testing the cube was also a moment of disappointment. I compared STL (sound transmission loss) of my cube VS my room door and was disappointed to see that lower frequencies where not filtered at all. At first, I thought my construction was flawed, or my testing setup. Later, theory explained one valley on the graph above (related to cube dimensions and its acoustic modes), but I never figured out the other.</p>

<h2 id="a-detour-into-metamaterials-and-programmatic-cad">A Detour into Metamaterials and Programmatic CAD</h2>

<p>Demotivated, I also realized that building something so heavy and potentially dangerous was beyond my current skillset. So, I looked for other solutions. That’s when I found <strong>metamaterials</strong> – engineered materials with acoustic properties derived from their structure or composition. [insert simple example]</p>

<p>I started reading scientific papers on acoustics. For around 15 years, papers have celebrated metamaterials as the next big thing. By the way, acoustics is a whole separate field. I honestly didn’t know that initially; I assumed it was mostly solved engineering problem. It’s not :)</p>

<p>Anyway, papers promised sound attenuation using materials without the weight or volume of, say, a 3m cement wall.</p>

<p>I read about various metamaterials and found some promising structures. I thought maybe I will not need such heavy walls if some meatamaterial will be very effective. [Add link to the paper] This led to a delightful foray into programmatically-defined CAD. Unlike the manual chore of designing the cube, here I wrote code to generate a 3D mesh for printing. Change the code, bam! New model. It felt like magic. I designed and 3D-printed a prototype array of Helmholtz resonators.</p>

<p>[add image of DIY a bass trap]
BTW, the typical foam or holey things hobbyists use often lack solid scientific backing – acoustic forums are full of holy wars about different sound traps. Again, I expected this to be a solved issue and best practices to be obvious; they weren’t.</p>

<p>[Image: Photo of 3D printed Helmholtz resonator prototypes]</p>

<h2 id="hope-calculations-and-resignation">Hope, Calculations, and Resignation</h2>

<p>Then I found a paper, published in 2023, that captured my imagination. It used plastic plumbing tubes with cleverly cut holes to create paired Helmholtz resonators (they are more effective together then alone), attenuating sound (including low frequencies) across a broad range. Most metamaterials target narrow bands (like a specific airplane engine noise), but my goal was broad attenuation. This paper promised exactly that <em>and</em> claimed it didn’t require a hermetic seal! Wow! No need for complex ventilation setup! [<link to="" paper="" />]</p>

<p>I emailed the authors with clarifying questions (using LLMs along the way to aid my understanding of the paper). I was enamored: plastic tubes seemed light, cheap, and targeted the needed frequency range. This felt like an emotional high point – lots of hope and excitement.</p>

<p>After some months of emails, I was ready to build a prototype. I went online to buy the materials. That’s when I calculated the tubing needed for the smallest possible single-person sleep area: a surprising <strong>250 meters</strong>. This turned out to be neither cheap nor light, weighing over half a ton. I was right back to the original problem: the construction was too unwieldy. Resignation. At that point, I was already a bit checked out from the project.</p>

<h2 id="an-unexpected-resolution">An Unexpected Resolution</h2>

<p>Over this period, my sleep patterns shifted. I no longer have the same problems as last year. I’m not sure exactly why. Since moving to Finland, my life has become more balanced, leading to general stress reduction. I’ve also gotten to know my neighbors; they know my condition and are very understanding.</p>

<p>Recently, I disassembled the cube, reclaiming the apparently expensive plywood for future projects (a nod to my earlier naivete about costs). Overall, I spent under 1,000 euros and a solid man-month of effort. It was absolutely a good investment. I enjoyed the deep dives, the learning, the process of trying to build something real. I’m already using the experience in my next hobby project. It was a fascinating journey that made my current lived experice so much richer, for now I see and appreciate complexity and work needed to design and produce everyday things, previously hidden from me.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2025/05/01/h</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Should AI Take the Wheel?</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2025/03/24/Should-AI-Take-the-Wheel</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>When my wife asked, “<em>Which decisions should you <strong>not</strong> delegate to AI?</em>”, I froze mid-thought.</p>

<!--excerpt_separator-->

<p>At that moment, it hit me just how much I’d already outsourced—maybe even too much. She noticed (quicker than I did!) that I’d become increasingly dependent on AI, whose capabilities seem to grow by the week.</p>

<p>It started innocently enough. Small questions like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What meal can I make with these leftovers?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>quickly escalated to:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Should we move to another city?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Before long, decisions I’d usually ponder through journaling, or with trusted friends, had slowly become quick prompts to ChatGPT, answered instantly. Convenience quietly replaced reflection.</p>

<p>It begs the question: when do we cross the line from helpful to dangerously passive?</p>

<h2 id="better-decisions">Better decisions</h2>

<p>Recently, I chatted about this with a <a href="https://x.com/Aay17ush">friend</a>. We talked about how little practice we really get with life’s biggest choices: leaving a job, ending a relationship, deciding to move abroad. These choices come up infrequently yet have massive stakes attached, no wonder we struggle with them.</p>

<p>From this perspective, AI seems almost irresistible. Trained on humanity’s collective experiences, less affected by the emotional blind spots that hinder our judgment,<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> wouldn’t AI naturally tend to make wiser, more objective choices?</p>

<h2 id="cheat-code-to-life">Cheat code to life</h2>

<p><em>Yet</em>, even if AI produces objectively better outcomes, could depending on it take away something vital?</p>

<p>It reminds me of using cheat codes in video games as a child (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">IDDQD</code>, anyone?). At first, cheating felt amazing. Soon afterward, however, I noticed something unexpected—I wasn’t having any fun. The challenge vanished, the tension collapsed, and with them disappeared all the joy and meaning behind playing in the first place.</p>

<p>I wonder: Could over-depending on AI feel the same way, robbing me of life’s struggles—the very struggles that I suspect build character, resilience, and empathy?</p>

<p>I’ve resorted to cheats in games when they became frustratingly hard or when low mood got the best of me, <em>even</em> when I knew it would spoil the fun longer-term. If I can’t resist that temptation in gaming, how can I resist the allure of AI making my life easier?</p>

<hr />

<p><em>But maybe</em> the gaming analogy doesn’t perfectly map onto real life. It’s worth exploring the limitations of this idea.</p>

<h2 id="real-life-isnt-a-carefully-crafted-video-game">Real life isn’t a carefully crafted video game</h2>

<p>Our daily challenges aren’t necessarily meaningful or valuable. Many struggles aren’t instructive—they’re random, painful occurrences delivering little personal growth or satisfaction.</p>

<p>In these circumstances, reducing unnecessary trauma and harm isn’t “cheating”; it’s just common sense.</p>

<h3 id="not-all-gain-requires-pain">Not all gain requires pain</h3>

<p>And maybe I’ve overestimated the necessity of struggle and hardship for personal growth. Positive experiences like curiosity and creativity, can also shape who we become. Perhaps AI might help us learn and grow without unnecessarily painful detours.</p>

<h3 id="but-some-gain-still-might">…but some gain still might?</h3>

<p>Still, there’s a risk: if we delegate <em>every</em> challenging decision, we might lose the valuable tension that drives personal growth.</p>

<p>There’s value in wrestling with uncertainty even when the AI reliably suggests <em>a</em> good path. That tension carries meaning—or at the very least feels very human.</p>

<h2 id="local-maxima-trap">Local maxima trap</h2>

<p><em>Further complicating things</em>, even if AI could perfectly optimize for our preferences, it might trap us in a ‘local maximum’—offering instant relief while stalling long-term growth. Picture an AI that keeps you in barely tolerable relationships or jobs, preventing the discomfort that often sparks transformative change.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> In short, short-term comfort might lead to long-term stagnation, much like the marshmallow test suggests.</p>

<h2 id="convenience-vs-agency">Convenience vs. Agency</h2>

<p>All these thoughts bring me back to larger questions of personal agency. As AI improves, will relying on it drain my sense of autonomy? Will life lose some deep, intangible spark if I delegate too many important decisions?</p>

<p>My current view: we will have to try and see. What comforts me a bit is reflecting on my life thus far. Despite thinking of myself as the <em>instant gratification monkey</em>, my life tells a different story—I actually go out of my comfort zone and do stuff despite the lure of The Algorithm.</p>

<p>So I expect AI to become more powerful, more useful, and I also feel confident that I’ll notice if I start veering toward an unfulfilling, agency-lacking existence—and trust myself to course-correct.</p>

<p>I’d love to hear your thoughts, and I’m curious how future-me will reflect on another year of closer reliance on AI.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>To be clear, today’s AIs carry <em>all the biases</em> inherited from training data; the hope is that they balance each other out. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Current AIs are good at surface-level optimization but may fail to suggest difficult-in-the-moment but ultimately enriching decisions. Future models could potentially integrate secondary- and tertiary-level consequences, vectorize your preferences and <em>your whole psyche</em>, and ultimately be able to make decisions that are <em>just good for you</em>. But that is post-singularity AI, firmly in Speculationland. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2025/03/24/Should-AI-Take-the-Wheel</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>My favorite fiction books</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/07/09/My-favorite-fiction-books</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I wanted to write something without too much virtue signaling. When I look at earlier posts, I see something like a trophy board to show everyone how smart and likable I am.<!--excerpt_separator-->
Although everything I wrote about back then was and is really interesting to me, it still seems dishonest somehow. I guess my current mood is different from the one I used to have.</p>

<p>So I want to try something different. I’m going to write about the books I absolutely love. Not about philosophy or the role of technology in today’s world. Just 3 books that have made the last seven years much more pleasant for me.</p>

<p>This kind of writing is harder to do because it makes me more vulnerable, it’s not only about the books but about me and my history with them. It’s something dear to my heart: what if you don’t like it? What if you criticize me and my haphazard way of gushing about these books?</p>

<p>Well, for the joy of writing this, I’m still willing to take the risk :-)</p>

<hr />

<p>I’ve been reading fantasy and science fiction for more than 25 years. I started with Wells, Stanislaw Lem, the Strugatsky brothers, Ray Bradbury, and Philip K. Dick.
After reading through the classics, I discovered the Hugo and Nebula Awards for SF and went through all the finalists. After that, I gradually moved on to lesser and lesser known books and authors.
After scraping the bottom of the barrel for some time, I lucked into web series, books written one chapter at a time and posted on forums or blogs. And how glad I am that I found them, because all the books on this list below are representatives of this category.</p>

<h2 id="harry-potter-and-the-methods-of-rationality">Harry Potter and the Methods of Rationality</h2>
<p>By Eliezer Yudkowsky [<a href="http://www.hpmor.com/">link to the (free) book</a>]</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books-hpmor-book-cover.jpg" alt="Book cover showing a hand with fingers poised to snap" /></p>

<p>I’m sorry, this is the one book I won’t stop raving about. The following text is just my fanboy noises aimed to get you to read this book.</p>

<p>I was sure that fanfics are nothing more than erotic fantasies of teenagers turned into text. In <em>special</em> forums and with lots of grammatical errors. Or they are not very funny parody books that want to exploit the fame of the original to cash in.</p>

<p>The tacky title of this fanfic didn’t help it stand out from that crowd. It was the author’s name that helped.</p>

<p>Eliezer was known to me as the champion of the rationality movement and author of many articles on lesswrong.com.
Just the fact that such a person wrote a fanfic began to change my image of what a fanfic is.</p>

<p>It also helped that the author suggests in the preface to stop reading the book after the fifth chapter if you weren’t hooked. That’s a good heuristic to use with other books as well — it allows you to start a long book without fear of committing to finish it. And this is a book of considerable length.
Fortunately this is one of those cases where the length of a book seems intimidating at first, but then becomes a joy when you realize that many more pages of this fascinating entertainment await you.</p>

<p>To enjoy this book, <strong>you don’t have to like or even have read the original</strong> Harry Potter books.
It’s my top 1 recommendation even for people who don’t read much fiction at all (and they love it too).</p>

<p>~</p>

<p>I once tried to write my own novel. I researched how to structure it, how to edit it. I used my project management skills to break it down into small chunks and wrote them out. I edited them in iterations.</p>

<p>It sucked and the result was crap. I didn’t have the motivation to practice and get better.
But since then, when I re-read HPMOR, I notice all the things the author did that are just. so. good. How it hooks me in emotionally and intellectually. How it changes the cadence without ever being too slow.</p>

<p>~</p>

<p>I was sad at the end of the first read, knowing for a fact that such excitingly captivating books are very few and hard to find.
But there’s hope! <a href="https://www.fanfiction.net/s/11174940/1/Significant-Digits">Significant Digits</a> by Alexander Davis is “the best HPMOR continuation fic” (quote from Elizer). The other books in this post are also similar.</p>

<p>Elizer is mainly working on AI alignment. I don’t want our world to end as much as the next guy, but it’s a pity Eliezer isn’t writing SF books for a living.</p>

<h2 id="worm">Worm</h2>
<p>By John C. McCrae [<a href="https://parahumans.wordpress.com/">link to the (free) book</a>]</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books-worm-book-cover.jpg" alt="Book cover showing a metropolitan city skyline with an overcast sky" /></p>

<p>A grimdark world where superheroes aren’t so good and villains aren’t so evil is a popular theme these days, just think of the recent popularity of The Boys TV series. But Worm was the first book of this genre for me, and boy, did it take me away for <em>a ride</em>.</p>

<p>Endless cliffhangers and conflict escalation led to many nights where I couldn’t stop reading until sleep finally took me at 4am. Usually when a book is this interesting I finish it quickly, but not this one. This book is 4 Wars and Peaces long. So it was <em>a lot</em> of sleepless nights.</p>

<p>After I finally finished it, I wanted more. And the fanfic world didn’t disappoint. I’ve been reading Worm fanfics for years. I’m not exaggerating, here’s <a href="https://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/FanficRecs/Worm">an (incomplete) list of them</a>.</p>

<p>~</p>

<p>Over dozens of fanfics, the characters and setting have become familiar to me, all the key situations have been lived through from different angles with different consequences.</p>

<p>At first I liked Worm because it fit my depressed mood at the time, but after years of fanfics, this world has become the ultimate cozy feel-good read, where I return to old friends and places and relieve fond memories.</p>

<p>(This transition to warm and fuzzy was influenced by some of ack1308’s <a href="https://www.fanfiction.net/u/5180580/ack1308">wholesome Worm fanfics</a>, where each and every conflict is resolved in the best possible way.)</p>

<h2 id="worth-the-candle">Worth The Candle</h2>
<p>By Alexander Wales [<a href="https://www.royalroad.com/fiction/25137/worth-the-candle">link to the (free) book</a>]</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2022-07-09-My-favorite-fiction-books-worth-the-candle-book-cover.jpg" alt="Book cover showing a man fighting with a much bigger humanoid opponent" /></p>

<p>The LitRPG to rule them all. Interesting mechanics, but not too much of it. So meta and trope-riding, -bending, -exploiting that it’s at least three levels deep.
The author is the king of nuanced worldbuilding. My god! He’s made a variety of worlds with details down history and politics.</p>

<p><strong>Other fiction</strong>: a horde of ugly goblins invade with mindless fury, killing innocents and destroying millennia-old elven forests. They force the main character to wipe them out. He moves on to the next challenge.</p>

<p><strong>This book</strong>: a horde of ugly goblins invades. But their ugliness doesn’t dehumanize them, they’re still people. People who have a long history with elves, with war crimes on both sides. The new political regime of Goblinland forced this goblin contingent to flee their lands or be persecuted as a minority. There are also women and children behind the soldiers. The main character understands all this and when the negotiations fail, it’s not an easy moral decision to kill the goblins. Some of the horde warriors are defeated, but that still leaves the surrendering goblins and their families to deal with. You’ll need logistics to organize it all.</p>

<p>Humanitarian crisis, supply chains, politics, ethics — this book has it all, and that rare depth pleasantly tickles my brain.</p>

<p>The author seems so much smarter than I’m that he can conjure up all these worlds and unite them in a story with just the right… everything for me. It’s like reading <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/">Slate Star Codex</a>: someone intelligent has thought through a lot of details and made them accessible to me.</p>

<p>Also, and this is a recurring feature of all the books on this list, this book is lusciously long.</p>

<hr />
<p>Honorable mention</p>
<h3 id="mother-of-learning">Mother of Learning</h3>
<p>By Domagoj Kurmaic [<a href="https://www.royalroad.com/fiction/21220/mother-of-learning">link to the (free) book</a>]</p>

<p>A progression fantasy in which the protagonist grows not only in skills, but also in wisdom.</p>

<p>The first chapter felt a bit awkward in terms of dialogue, but then the story really picked up, the complex situation unravelling with lots of action, and that hooked me in till the satisfying end.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2022/07/09/My-favorite-fiction-books</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Dark mode implementation for this blog</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2022/02/06/Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I’ve implemented the dark theme for this blog. An endeavour for 2-3 hours that has visible results. A satisfying project, I invite everyone with a light-theme-only blog to try.
<!--excerpt_separator--></p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2022-02-06-Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog--dark-mode-example-picture.jpg" alt="An article screenshot, one half of which is in light mode and the other half is in dark mode" /></p>

<p><em>CSS Tricks</em>, of course, has this topic thoroughly covered in their <a href="https://css-tricks.com/a-complete-guide-to-dark-mode-on-the-web/">Complete Guide to Dark Mode on the Web</a>. I’ll describe what I’ve done in this particular blog and why.</p>

<p>I’m using <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">@media (prefers-color-scheme: dark) { ... }</code> CSS media query which lets me use OS-level user preferences. I chose not to support manual toggling between modes because of two reasons:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Implementation involves JavaScript swapping CSS classes and storing state in Local Storage–a harder effort than I wanted for this quick-win project</li>
  <li>If a user has strong preferences about the dark mode, I imagine such a user already has a way of controlling the interface. Such as a browser plugin that changes the theme, e.g. <a href="https://darkreader.org/">Dark Reader</a>.</li>
</ol>

<p>As dark mode gains momentum, I think major browsers will display a toggle between modes (not only in Dev Tools) making the effort of creating this toggle myself moot.</p>

<h2 id="implementation">Implementation</h2>

<p>This blog uses a modified <a href="https://github.com/johno/pixyll">Pixyll theme</a> that has <strong>32</strong> SASS files that get compiled into one big CSS file.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2022-02-06-Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog--sass-includes-listing.jpg" alt="Part of includes listing @importing separate SASS files for links, code, header, etc" width="350" /></p>

<p>This otherwise reasonable divide-and-conquer approach bites me in the ass here, as I needed to insert the media-query block 17 times. For each style, I wanted to look different when dark. Here’s <a href="https://github.com/andrey-lepekhin/andrey-lepekhin.github.io/commit/b54227499b737f5042d151f60c39416e88c9ba4b">the actual commit</a>.</p>

<p>I could instead place all dark mode styles in one such file, but then I’ll lose the handy separation these files provide. Also, in the future, if I change a light mode style, the proximity of the corresponding dark mode style will remind me to change it as well. Something I might otherwise forget to do and test for.
If there is a better way, please tell me about it.</p>

<p>So, that’s basically it: adding media-query styles and selecting particular colors that look good on dark background.</p>

<hr />

<p>Oh, while we’re on a technical topic, I want to boast a little. This site got a 100/100 performance score at Google’s <a href="https://pagespeed.web.dev">PageSpeed Insights</a> for desktop and 97 for mobile. I can mostly attribute it to Jekyll itself and a little bit to my tweaks using locally hosted fonts instead of Google Fonts’ CDN. I host this blog on <a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub Pages</a> for free, you can use the <a href="https://github.com/barryclark/jekyll-now">same GitHub Pages-friendly process</a> I’m using.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2022/02/06/Dark-mode-implementation-for-this-blog</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>3 links: future, present and uncomfortable</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/24/3-links-future-present-and-uncomfortable</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>A short post with 10 thought-provoking predictions for this decade (e.g. decentralized internet and the world run by Millennials)
<a href="https://avc.com/2020/01/what-will-happen-in-the-2020s/">What Will Happen In The 2020s</a> by <em>Fred Wilson</em></p>

<hr />

<p>China leading the way with more ways to use QR codes than you can shake a stick at (e.g. meet and flirt online at bars): <a href="https://a16z.com/2019/10/30/the-power-of-qr-codes/">Remember QR Codes? They’re More Powerful Than You Think</a> by <em>Avery Segal</em>.</p>

<hr />

<p>I love awkward questions, they make one vulnerable and create a possibility for closeness and/or satisfaction of one’s needs. Here is a paper that helps stop avoiding sensitive questions.
<a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3437468">I Didn’t Want to Offend You: The Cost of Avoiding Sensitive Questions</a> by <em>Einav Hart</em>, <em>Eric VanEpps</em>, and <em>Maurice E. Schweitzer</em>
A quote from the abstract:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Across three pilot studies and four experimental studies, we demonstrate that individuals avoid asking sensitive questions, because they fear making others uncomfortable and because of impression management concerns. We demonstrate that this aversion to asking sensitive questions is both costly and misguided.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2020/02/24/3-links-future-present-and-uncomfortable</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Some programming idioms explained</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Some-programming-idioms-explained</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>As a perpetually novice programmer, it was nice to see the reasons behind some popular idioms explained. <!--excerpt_separator-->Like why “Maintainability counts” or “Avoid package level state”.
Also this way of seeing developer work as preparation for inevitable change:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Change is the name of the game we’re in. What we do as programmers is manage change. When we do that well we call it design, or architecture. When we do it badly we call it technical debt, or legacy code.</p>

  <p>If you are writing a program that works perfectly, one time, for one fixed set of inputs then nobody cares if the code is good or bad because ultimately the output of the program is all the business cares about.</p>

  <p>But this is never true. Software has bugs, requirements change, inputs change, and very few programs are written solely to be executed once, thus your program will change over time. Maybe it’s you who’ll be tasked with this, more likely it will be someone else, but someone has to change that code. Someone has to maintain that code.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://dave.cheney.net/2020/02/23/the-zen-of-go">The Zen of Go</a> by <em>Dave Cheney</em></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2020/02/23/Some-programming-idioms-explained</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Simple status games</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Simple-status-games</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://thepointmag.com/examined-life/who-wants-to-play-the-status-game-agnes-callard/">Who Wants to Play the Status Game?</a> by <em>Agnes Callard</em></p>

<p>I like to think that I see a hidden meaning, a secret game being played behind the curtains of everyday interactions. Naturally, I like articles about signalling and social games.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A player of the Importance Game tries to ascend high enough to reach for something that will set her above her interlocutor, a player of the Leveling Game reaches down low enough to hit common ground. The former needs to signal enough power to establish a hierarchy; the latter enough powerlessness to establish equality.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In an academic context, I’ve noticed that complaining about how busy one is hits a sweet spot of oppression—I cannot manage my life!—and importance—because I am so in demand! When you’re playing with a master, it can be hard to tell which game you’re in.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The ending of the article is too unclear for my taste, but then I’m no philosopher.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2020/02/23/Simple-status-games</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Pitfalls of our simplistic moral evaluation system</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2020/02/23/Pitfalls-of-our-simplistic-moral-evaluation-system</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>In <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/M2LWXsJxKS626QNEA/the-trouble-with-good">The Trouble With “Good”</a> <em>Scott Alexander</em> describes some problems that stem from our evolutionary-induced simplistic good-bad evaluation system (emotivism), that meshes moral beliefs with facts and personal preferences.<br />
I’ll only paste one quote as the post itself has just the right composition to be clear enough while not being too long.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So this is one problem: the inputs to our mental karma system aren’t always closely related to the real merit of a person/thing/idea.</p>

  <p>Another problem: our interpretation of whether to upvote or downvote something depends on how many upvotes or downvotes it already has. […]</p>

  <p>Another problem: we are tempted to assign everything about a concept the same score. Eliezer Yudkowsky currently has 2486 karma. How good is Eliezer at philosophy? Apparently somewhere around the level it would take to get 2486 karma. How much does he know about economics? Somewhere around level 2486 would be my guess. How well does he write? Probably well enough to get 2486 karma. Translated into mental terms, this looks like the Halo Effect. Yes, we can pick apart our analyses in greater detail; having read Eliezer’s posts, I know he’s better at some things than others. But that 2486 number is going to cause anchoring-and-adjustment issues even so.</p>

  <p>But the big problem, the world-breaking problem, is that sticking everything good and bad about something into one big bin and making decisions based on whether it’s a net positive or a net negative is an unsubtle, leaky heuristic completely unsuitable for complicated problems.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2020/02/23/Pitfalls-of-our-simplistic-moral-evaluation-system</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Rent downtown to reduce your commute time — conquering a frugal mindset</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2019/11/26/Rent-downtown-to-reduce-your-commute-time-conquering-a-frugal-mindset</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Daily living and commuting conditions have an immense impact on your wellbeing. This post is for people who live in a metropolitan area, have enough income to rent a place for themselves (with flatmates if needed), don’t have commitments that prohibit them from moving and, most importantly, are <strong>not satisfied with their commute time</strong>.</p>

<p>I want to describe why I came to a decision to rent a pricey apartment downtown. This is part of a <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/tag/renting/">series</a> where I share my tools and thinking processes towards renting: from changing your mindset to apartment research to communication with your landlord.</p>

<h2 id="rationale">Rationale</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Every extra minute of commute time reduces job satisfaction, reduces leisure time satisfaction, increases strain and reduces mental health.<br />
[…]<br />
An additional 10 minutes (each way) of commuting time is associated with the equivalent effect on job satisfaction as a 19% reduction in gross personal income.</p>

  <p><a href="https://travelbehaviour.files.wordpress.com/2017/10/caw-summaryreport-onlineedition.pdf">Study</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I used to think of my 1h 10m (each way) commute as a needed tribute to adult values, something most of my college friends did (sometimes with much longer travel times), something inescapable. But studies similar to the one cited above and my own happiness being affected due to the mediocre use of these precious hours brought me to a realization: I want to live closer to the office.</p>

<h2 id="being-thrifty-can-be-an-issue">Being thrifty can be an issue</h2>

<p>There was one problem though — it was prohibitively expensive. Technically, I could afford it, but habituated with cheap living while spending less than half of my income, I just could not justify such an expense. The thought of the yearly cost of rent in the city filled my frugal self with outrage. <em>That’s an unfair price!</em> — I thought.</p>

<p>Could I be wrong? What if those hours spent commuting really are <em>more</em> valuable than even such a sizeable chunk of money?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a <a href="https://hbr.org/2017/05/reclaim-your-commute">2017 article published in <em>Harvard Business Review</em></a>, researchers discussed the results of a study they conducted where they asked subjects to choose between two jobs:<br />
●	Job #1 had a 50-minute round-trip commute and paid $67,000 a year.<br />
●	Job #2 had a 20-minute round-trip commute and paid $64,000 a year.<br />
84% of the participants in the study selected job #1, as researchers wrote, “expressing a willingness to forfeit one hour each workday to their commute—250 hours per year—in exchange for just $3,000. That’s $12 an hour of commuting time—less than half their hourly rate at work!”<br />
They concluded that people were unable to “fully appreciate the psychological, emotional, and physical costs of longer travel times.”</p>

  <p><a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90381845/how-to-make-your-long-commute-less-stressful">How to make your long commute less stressful</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>So, how to overcome this bias and</p>

<h2 id="measure-an-adequate-cost-of-time-spent-commuting">Measure an adequate cost of time spent commuting</h2>

<p>My first approach was to answer a hypothetical like: “<em>After 9 hours at work, Mr. Burns wants me to do some menial work for another hour. How much does he have to pay for me to be satisfied with this hour?</em>”<br />
That provided an amount of 12 000 ₽<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> as a result. I had to revise the question immediately as the real situation was not so one-sided:<br />
I enjoy reading on the tube, and I don’t mind a brisk walk of up to 20 minutes. So, the question had to change.</p>

<p>Turns out I was already asking myself a useful question before every Uber drive: “Am I willing to pay this amount for speed and comfort instead of using public transport?” <br />
With that, I realized a better question to ask before commuting is: “<strong>How much am I willing to pay right now to be home/at work in 20 minutes?</strong>” I answered this question every day for two weeks and got a variety of results:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2019-11-26-table-how-much-to-fly-to-work.png" alt="The table with varying answers for each morning and evening of 10 weekdays, with median calculated as 1350 rub." />
Some days I dreaded the tube, and some days it was more… acceptable.</p>

<p>The median price I was willing to pay per 50 commute-free minutes was nine times lower than the sum that my initial question provided. That’s 1350*60/50 = 1620 ₽ per hour of commute time saved. That applies to work days only, so to compare apples with apples, I’ll smear that number throughout an average month = 1620*22/30 = 1188 ₽. Let’s see what it will get me:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2019-11-26-Moscow_rent_cost_map.png" alt="Heat map of rent prices of Moscow. Higher prices in city center" />
The price of renting is higher the closer you are to downtown, which is filled with offices and historic places.</p>

<p>I’ve made a table to calculate the daily cost of time saved on commuting and the daily cost of rent in the corresponding neighborhoods<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2019-11-26-table-daily-rent-vs-cost-of-saved-time.png" alt="The table which shows said calculations. Daily cost of saved free time minus cost of rent in the area of 20 minutes commute is positive" /></p>

<p>The positive numbers in the last column mean that the price I’m willing to pay for a lesser commute is higher than the rent cost in the area that will provide said commute. What do you know, my frugal self <em>can</em> afford to live closer to the office! :tada:<br />
…And that’s not even counting the opportunity costs of a long commute!</p>

<p>With that, making a decision is easy, I’m going to rent downtown!<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> The next post is about how to approach selecting a neighborhood within an acceptable distance from your office.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That’s around $200. Hereafter, prices will be in Rubles since I’m in Moscow, but it shouldn’t matter. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>There are two important assumptions made for simplification here: 1) These two weeks are not outliers 2) Each minute of commute costs exactly the same. That’s somehow irrelevant as the equilibrium between daily rent and the cost of saved time was achieved exactly at the 20-minute mark - the time I asked about in the previous question. Happy coincidence. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Something that has also helped my paradigm shift and start this whole process was an honest acceptance of the fact that yes, rent is expensive, it may not seem fair, but it’s a seller’s market and my outrage will not change this one bit. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2019/11/26/Rent-downtown-to-reduce-your-commute-time-conquering-a-frugal-mindset</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Intricacies of day-night and season cycles</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2019/11/10/Intricacies-of-day-night-and-season-cycles</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Much more than you wanted to know about day-night and season cycles.<br />
Check out this beautifully implemented interactive page <a href="https://ciechanow.ski/earth-and-sun/">Earth and Sun</a> by <em>Bartosz Ciechanowski</em>.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2019/11/10/Intricacies-of-day-night-and-season-cycles</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 10 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Sometimes it&apos;s really hard to measure the effects of online ads</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2019/11/09/Sometimes-its-really-hard-to-measure-the-effects-of-online-ads</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Or as <em>Jesse Frederik</em> and <em>Maurits Martijn</em> named it <a href="https://thecorrespondent.com/100/the-new-dot-com-bubble-is-here-its-called-online-advertising/13228924500-22d5fd24">The new dot com bubble is here: it’s called online advertising </a>.</p>

<p>It goes in length describing the case where eBay stopped paying $20mln annually for buying brand-name search ads from Google and did not see any visitors decrease. Then finishes with 13 studies of Facebook ad campaigns, in 10 of which the vast majority of sales increases were attributed to selection effect (e.g. customers were already looking for Nike shoes but went to nike.com through a Google ad).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Advertising rationally, the way it’s described in economic textbooks, is unattainable. Then how do advertisers know what they ought to pay for ads?<br />
“Yeah, basically they don’t know,” Lewis said in one of those throw-away clauses that kept running through my head for days after.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The article stops there, but I’ll have to argue that most of the examples apply to big brand companies. While a startup with a proven niche and known unit economics can and should still benefit from ads. Just not the brand-name ones, but the ones that help a user to discover their service (e.g. ‘cooked meals delivery’).</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2019/11/09/Sometimes-its-really-hard-to-measure-the-effects-of-online-ads</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>OpenAI language model is about to change how we parse meaningless text</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2019/02/26/OpenAI-language-model-is-about-to-change-how-we-parse-meaningless-text</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://srconstantin.wordpress.com/2019/02/25/humans-who-are-not-concentrating-are-not-general-intelligences/">Humans Who Are Not Concentrating Are Not General Intelligences</a> in which <em>srconstantin</em> describes one of many possible consequences of OpenAI’s <a href="https://blog.openai.com/better-language-models/">new language model</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The mental motion of “I didn’t really parse that paragraph, but sure, whatever, I’ll take the author’s word for it” is, in my introspective experience, absolutely identical to “I didn’t really parse that paragraph because it was bot-generated and didn’t make any sense so I couldn’t possibly have parsed it”, except that in the first case, I assume that the error lies with me rather than the text.  This is not a safe assumption in a post-GPT2 world. Instead of “default to humility” (assume that when you don’t understand a passage, the passage is true and you’re just missing something) the ideal mental action in a world full of bots is “default to null” (if you don’t understand a passage, assume you’re in the same epistemic state as if you’d never read it at all.)</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>While we’re on this topic, I’ll add two possible applications for GPT-2 successors that I see emerging in the next couple of years: 1) ‘Get-a-date Tinder chatbot’ and 2) ‘Witty chat messages suggestions’ in major chat apps.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2019/02/26/OpenAI-language-model-is-about-to-change-how-we-parse-meaningless-text</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Slack rant</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/07/30/Slack-rant</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Replying to Slack messages <em>feels</em> productive, but it is a very, <strong>very</strong> addictive way to procrastinate. It’s hard to say no to it. Others are replying fast. Instant messaging creates <em>expectation</em> of a fast answer. It’s not your grandpa’s email after all. It is gratifying, it is a quick fix, it’s easy. Get your dopamine hit <strong>now</strong>.</p>

<p>Oh, it feels good having answered all unread messages. No anxiety. Bliss. Yet the faster you reply, the faster you get another message.</p>

<p>There’s no real multitasking for humans. You have to decide whether you want to have a state of flow or allow constant interruptions<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>

<p>Not plunging into this infinite pseudo-productive sea of quick-fixes is something that is still hard for me. I don’t have new message notifications of course, but I know that red unread messages counter exists and it beckons.<br />
<img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-07-30-Slack-notification.png" alt="" style="width: 50px;" /></p>

<h3 id="counter-measures">Counter-measures</h3>
<ul>
  <li>I lobby for not-expecting-an-immediate-answer culture when I can</li>
  <li>Slack is hidden in the tray or turned off by default</li>
  <li>I <em>try</em> to answer messages in bulk at scheduled unproductive times of the day.</li>
  <li>I <em>try</em> not to mark messages as unread. This is still hard. Otherwise, I read a message, decide I don’t want to answer now, mark it unread… and one hour later the cycle repeats, eating away my time and attention.</li>
  <li>I start working at home, with no distractions, no phone, no Slack, no email.</li>
  <li>There is one thing that really helps me with slackrastination (that is a word now), or any procrastination for that matter: instead of automatically changing what you do, you make the process as conscious as possible. For me the good example are weeks when I track my time. Each time I change what I do, I write the new activity down and start corresponding activity timer<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. When I am in a state of flow and start writing “Slack” to change timers, I usually catch myself and go back to doing the important stuff.</li>
  <li>My wallpaper at work <img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-07-30-turnoffSlack.png" alt="White canvas with words: &quot;Close Slack &amp; Gmail. Do what's important. Heart emoji&quot;" style="border: black 0.1em;border-style: dashed;" /></li>
</ul>
<p>&lt;/rant&gt;</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Don’t get me started on open space offices, I have one rant per post policy. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>I use <a href="https://toggl.com/">Toggl</a> for that. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/07/30/Slack-rant</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Huge productivity gains</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/07/29/Huge-productivity-gains</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>This is how I got <strong>the biggest increase in productivity</strong> in the last 5 years.</p>

<p>The idea is from this article: <a href="http://blog.complice.co/post/121559734412/how-to-start-on-the-most-important-thing-every-day">How to start on the most important thing every day</a> by Malcolm Ocean (thanks, man!).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I want to emphasize that this is the most valuable habit I have, by a large margin (and I’ve got some good ones!). Therefore if you’re reading this, I think that it’s at least worth <em>trying</em> to create a similar system in your own life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I second Malcolm here, go read the article, I’ll wait.</p>

<p>It is the new norm now, but you wouldn’t <em>believe</em> how big this change was for me at the time. The difference was night and day, I wouldn’t stop telling my friends about it! Ok, if you’re sold, read on for details.</p>

<h2 id="my-impelentation">My impelentation</h2>

<p><strong>Evening</strong>, 2 hours before the sleep time</p>
<ul>
  <li>Write down the plan for the next morning, including one most important goal, and optional hints like “start the going out routine by 8:00, leave home by 8:30”</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Morning</strong>, immediately after waking up<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<ul>
  <li>At least one pomodoro doing the most important task</li>
</ul>

<p>Before breaking for any less productive activities like eating, Reddit or email checking:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Dance to at least one track<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, immediately followed by</li>
  <li>Meditate for at least 10 minutes</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-didnt-work">What didn’t work</h2>

<h3 id="planning-right-before-bed">Planning right before bed</h3>
<p>I started to plan the next morning before going to bed, but as I was very sleepy, plans that came out were poor. Now I plan 2 hours before bed time, when I’m more lucid.</p>

<h3 id="doing-things-that-look-like-procrastinating">Doing things that <em>look</em> like procrastinating</h3>
<p>e.g. one time I was looking for a flat to rent and that was my main task for some weeks. Problem is, browsing listings, looking at a lot of pictures, is similar to my relaxation habit of browsing Reddit. After I finished looking through new listings, I noticed that it is super easy to slip into Reddit. I started scheduling my flat search later in the day.</p>

<h3 id="planning-my-day-as-the-first-task">Planning my day as the first task</h3>
<p>After initial success, I drifted toward “plan my whole day and <em>then</em> start that important task”. Didn’t work so well. While planning a day, I usually encountered a small task: “Aha, easy 3-minute win! GTD prepared me for this! I just have to start this Slack conversation to update this status”. Then inevitably I’m replaying to other messages, it’s 15 minutes later and the productive mood is gone. <del>Ok, it’s Slack rant time!</del> I’ve moved it to a <a href="/2018/07/30/Slack-rant">separate post</a>.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Some mornings I am groggier than on others, that’s where having a clear todo list from the evening before shines – I don’t need to deliberate about what to do, no decision necessary. In case you forgot - <a href="/2018/03/01/Why-choices-are-bad">choices are bad</a>. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Why? According to two years of correlating my activities and mood, dancing consistently makes me happy. Sometimes it’s 3 minutes, sometimes it will be 20. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/07/29/Huge-productivity-gains</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>The intricate dance of eye contact</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/07/22/The-intricate-dance-of-eye-contact</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I’m amazed that I’ve only learned about this in my thirties. I’ve started seeing a new subcurrent of information that is communicated wordlessly (like body language). Now, it is so much more interesting to pay attention to and participate in this dance. What are they signaling? Did the interlocutor notice your move?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.artofmanliness.com/articles/look-em-in-the-eye-part-ii-how-to-make-eye-contact-the-right-way-in-life-business-and-love/">How to Make Eye Contact the Right Way in Life, Business, and Love</a> by Brett &amp; Kate McKay.</p>

<p>For some time, I’ve been mindful about my own eye contact during various forms of communication. But I never did the next step — treat and interpret the variety of possible eye contacts as the signals they are. We’re hardwired to interpret eye contact as a signal to answer questions like are you interested or not, are you submissive or dominant, are you trustworthy?</p>

<p>For example, in some contexts, I just took notice that “it’s uncomfortable to hold that gaze” and concluded “I’ll look at the table instead”. After reading this article, I started making the next step of assessing the situation: “…which could be interpreted as me signaling lower status”. After that I can choose whether that is something I want to happen right now.</p>

<p>Having predetermined etiquette for expressing interest in the opposite sex is also very handy. In the past, after meeting a woman’s gaze several times I usually started thinking “Does it mean anything, or is it a coincidence? Should I go say hi now or wait a couple of minutes to be sure?”. The article conveniently answers these questions and more.</p>

<p>The article is small and neatly divided with subheadings so you can take only what you need:</p>

<ul>
  <li>General guidelines on how to do it. When to look, where to look, how long, how to avert your gaze and what does it signal</li>
  <li>Sales and pitching (job interviews included)</li>
  <li>When you need to intimidate/dominate or diffuse a conflict</li>
  <li>Meeting the eyes of a stranger in the street</li>
  <li>Making eye contact with the opposite sex</li>
  <li>When giving a speech</li>
</ul>

<p>After I started paying attention and <em>choosing</em> my eye contact behavior rather than <em>reacting</em>, I’ve became more confident in almost all of those situations. And confidence feels great.</p>

<p>What else might I be missing? I’m sure there are more nuances to communication than I know of, after all <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/11/07/concept-shaped-holes-can-be-impossible-to-notice/">Concept-Shaped Holes Can Be Impossible To Notice</a>. <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/about#contact-me">Drop me a line</a> if you have something in mind.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/07/22/The-intricate-dance-of-eye-contact</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>How I began to befriend my feelings instead of trying to control them</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/07/07/Do-you-update-your-model-with-your-actual-experiences</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I do a lot to control my internal state</p>
<ul>
  <li>8-hour sleep and daily routine ✔</li>
  <li>Meditation and various cognitive habits ✔</li>
  <li>Healthy food ✔</li>
  <li>Sport ✔</li>
  <li>No stimulants ✔</li>
  <li>Rigorous work-life balance ✔</li>
  <li>Therapy, friends, commitment devices, etc. ✔</li>
</ul>

<p>Doing all this does indeed provide me with a higher baseline happiness<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Still, I’ve managed to fool myself into treating all <a href="/2018/07/01/Living-in-the-now">living-in-the-moment advise</a> as ‘a list of goals that undoubtedly <strong>will</strong> bring happiness when completed’.  I was too dependent on <em>ideas</em> of what happiness <em>should be</em> and was ignoring what I really felt in the process.</p>

<p>There are times when, even after meticulous completion of todo-list items, I feel down for some reason. Maybe I wanted to accomplish more, maybe someone was a dick to me, maybe I was a dick to someone, maybe it’s just a mysterious hormone fluctuation.<br />
Sometimes, all it takes to bring my mood up are compassion and <em>a permission</em> to feel bad.</p>

<p>There are also times when I did a lot of prep work, read articles by bestselling authors and listened to podcasts, made a model of myself and a plan how to improve my life; discussed and validated this plan with other people. But when I start executing, it feels like a grind, leaves me unmotivated with not much to show for my effort.</p>

<p>At that point, I usually concluded that my plan is flawed and I need to improve it. Or I’m not following the plan well enough because I’m a lazy asshole and I need to figure out how to motivate me first.</p>

<p>Recent therapy helped me to get out of my bubble a little and understand that 
<strong>I didn’t give enough credit to the direct experience</strong> and my actual (vs. best guess) feelings. It’s like I was learning to ride a bicycle only by reading some physics textbooks.</p>

<p>If you’re like me, the overanalysing type, it can take a while to understand. This doesn’t mean that planning and analysis are unnecessary, I will still do them. But I will err on the side of (validation through) action.</p>

<p>I can formulate the main thought as <strong>update your model with your actual experience; plan for raw experience inputs and corrections early and throughout the plan</strong>.
<br /><br /><br /><br /></p>

<p>I’m applying this newly learned principle for my hobbies/vocations search: I’m searching for things to do besides my day job, and start with no idea of what I could be doing.</p>

<p><strong>Before</strong>: elaborate planning, with weighted criteria list based on my best approximation of what I like; using said list as a scoring method for a vast list of hobbies<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.<br />
<strong>After</strong>: same plan scaffolding but the criteria list and their weights come from a direct experience of doing stuff. I.e. I try doing stuff that I sorta feel like doing, sometimes even (gah!) without a scoring behind that feeling.</p>

<p>If you’re familiar with software methodologies, I see this idea as applying the lean concept. It’s like iterating on an <a href="/2018/02/25/Vigilant-MVP-case-of-this-blog">MVP</a> instead of waiting for the waterfall to end.</p>

<p>This is all still very new, but it feels uncomfortable and right – the best kind of feeling, meaning I’m broadening my comfort zone. Anyway, I’ll see where this particular rabbit hole goes and will change the course if I don’t like it.</p>

<hr />

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I’ve logged my mood and activity during random parts of the day for more than a year now. This allows me to see correlations between my activities and mood. Maybe someday I will make a more thorough proof that there is indeed causation, but right now I’m comfortable being sure that, e.g. dancing and lifting weights reliably make me happy, and playing computer games makes me sad. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_hobbies">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_hobbies</a>, <a href="http://www.notsoboringlife.com/list-of-hobbies/">http://www.notsoboringlife.com/list-of-hobbies/</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/07/07/Do-you-update-your-model-with-your-actual-experiences</guid>
                <description>
                    
                    I do a lot to control my internal state, but I was too dependent on &lt;i&gt;ideas&lt;/i&gt; of what happiness &lt;i&gt;should be&lt;/i&gt; and was ignoring what I really felt in the process.
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Living in the now</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/07/01/Living-in-the-now</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Focus on the process, not just the goals; live in the day-to-day and enjoy it — I did not internalize these concepts until recently.</p>

<p>Some other common ideas (e.g. “silence is golden”) were well understood by me during adolescence, but the “live in the now, it’s all you’ve got” mantra was as elusive as it is ubiquitous<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.<br />
Here are the quotes from two great articles that clarify this topic for me.</p>

<p><a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/how-schopenhauers-thought-can-illuminate-a-midlife-crisis">How Schopenhauer’s thought can illuminate a midlife crisis</a> by Kieran Setiya:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Hence one common figure of the midlife crisis: the striving high-achiever, obsessed with getting things done, who is haunted by the hollowness of everyday life. When you are obsessed with projects, ceaselessly replacing old with new, satisfaction is always in the future. Or the past. It is mortgaged, then archived, but never possessed. In pursuing goals, you aim at outcomes that preclude the possibility of that pursuit, extinguishing the sparks of meaning in your life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>[…]</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If the crisis diagnosed by Schopenhauer turns on excessive investment in projects, then the solution is to invest more fully in the process, giving meaning to your life through activities that have no terminal point: since they cannot be completed, your engagement with them is not exhaustive. It will not subvert itself. Nor does it invite the sense of frustration that Schopenhauer scorns in unsatisfied desire – the sense of being at a distance from one’s goal, so that fulfilment is always in the future or the past.</p>

  <p>We should not give up on our worthwhile goals. Their achievement matters. But we should meditate, too, on the value of the process. It is no accident that the young and the old are generally more satisfied with life than those in middle age. Young adults have not embarked on life-defining projects; the aged have such accomplishments behind them. That makes it more natural for them to live in the present: to find value in atelic activities that are not exhausted by engagement or deferred to the future, but realised here and now. It is hard to resist the tyranny of projects in midlife, to find a balance between the telic and atelic. But if we hope to overcome the midlife crisis, to escape the gloom of emptiness and self-defeat, that is what we have to do.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2013/11/life-is-picture-but-you-live-in-pixel.html">Life is a Picture, But You Live in a Pixel</a> by Tim Urban:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Jack’s difficulties also relate to The Pixel Theory, a phrase coined by Tim Urban during his famous “alone in his apartment in front of the mirror” TED Talk.</p>

  <p>Jack sees his life as a rich picture depicting an epic story and assumes that the key to his happiness lies in the broad components of the image.</p>

  <p>But this is a mistake, because Jack doesn’t live in the picture’s broad strokes, he lives at all times in a single pixel of the image—a single Today.</p>

  <p>So while thousands of Jack’s Todays will, to an outsider from far away, begin to look like a complete picture, Jack spends each moment of his actual reality in one unremarkable Today pixel or another. Jack’s error is brushing off his mundane Wednesday and focusing entirely on the big picture, when in fact the mundane Wednesday is the experience of his actual life.<br />
And his assumption that his future Todays would be as vibrant and rich as the broad picture of his life is misunderstanding the unremarkable nature of a pixel, no matter what one’s life looks like in broad strokes. This assumption leads Jack to feel like his uneventful Today must be an unsatisfactory temporary relationship, when in reality it’s an inevitable and permanent marriage that he must accept and embrace in order to be happy.</p>

  <p>As far as what will actually make Jack happier as he lives in his mundane Wednesday, there are a number of scientifically proven things, including spending time with people you like, sleeping well and exercising, doing things you’re good at, and doing kind things for others.</p>

  <p>But perhaps the first thing Jack needs to do is learn to feel more gratitude, another scientifically proven route to happiness and the area in which he falls the most woefully short. Jack spends so much of his time looking up at the great things that will come his way and planning his future happiness and not nearly enough time looking down and thinking about how badly he used to want so many of the things he currently has.</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>My guess it’s because it goes against basic evolutionary goals of staying alive long enough to reproduce: you just don’t enjoy the sunset while the woods are dark and full of terrors. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/07/01/Living-in-the-now</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Rationalist group houses</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/06/23/Rationalist-group-houses</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I’ve long dreamt of an outside construct that will make me my best self without my lazy part having a say. And a lot of my routines are just that - a construct to make me behave in a way that benefits me in the long term. I’ve even sometimes dreamt of teaming up and living with like-minded people: helping and pushing each other further.</p>

<p>Well, The Zvi has written <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/06/24/on-dragon-army/">a huge piece discussing <em>the Dragon Army</em></a>, and now I know that rationalist group houses exist and have been discussed <em>in length</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p><strong>What is Dragon Army [Barracks]?</strong>  It’s a high-commitment, high-standards, high-investment group house model with centralized leadership and an up-or-out participation norm, designed to a) improve its members and b) actually accomplish medium-to-large scale tasks requiring long-term coordination.  Tongue-in-cheek referred to as the “fascist/authoritarian take on rationalist housing,” which has no doubt contributed to my being vulnerable to strawmanning but was nevertheless the correct joke to be making, lest people misunderstand what they were signing up for.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Quote from <a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/p23/dragon_army_theory_charter_30min_read/">the original post about Dragon Army</a> by <em>Duncan Sabien</em>.<br />
If you plan on doing something like that near Moscow, please call me up, I am better than average with discipline and no novice to levelling up in groups.</p>

<hr />

<p>I particularly liked Zvi’s thought that self-improvement shouldn’t be a goal in itself, but should have some other, primary goal to which self-improvement is an auxiliary:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The problem is that in my experience, your <em>real</em> terminal goal can be self-improvement all you like, but unless you choose a different primary goal and work towards <em>that</em>, you won’t self-improve all that much. The way you get better is because you need to get better <em>to do a thing</em>. Otherwise it’s all, well, let’s let Duncan’s hero Tyler Durden explain:<br />
[video]</p>

  <p>This is importantly true (although in a literal sense it is obviously false), and seems like the most obvious point of failure. Another is choosing Tyler’s solution to this problem. Don’t do that either.</p>

  <p>So yes, do all six of these things and have all three of these goals, but don’t think that down near the bottom of your list is doing a few concrete things every now and then. Everyone needs to have the thing, and have the thing be central and important to them, whatever the thing may be, and that person should then judge their success or failure on that basis, and the group also needs a big thing. Yes, we will also evaluate whether we hit the self-improvement marks, but on their own they simply do not cut it. Credit to my wife Laura Baur for making this point very clear and explicit to me, so that I realized its importance. Which is very high.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/06/23/Rationalist-group-houses</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>List of self-improvement-related links</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/06/08/List-of-self-improvement-related-links</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>As with <a href="/2018/03/05/List-of-entrepreneur-related-links">entrepreneurship-related articles list</a>, I just want to offload this bunch of articles sitting in my Pocket.<br />
When (if) I come reading through them, I will add descriptions and short versions.<br />
<strong>Beware</strong> this is a work in progress, some articles may be more than just a little dubious. Though you can still use this list to judge what were my 28-year-old self’s problems and aspirations.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2014/06/taming-mammoth-let-peoples-opinions-run-life.html">Taming the Mammoth: Why You Should Stop Caring What Other People Think</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://brennandunn.com/optimizing-your-life/">http://brennandunn.com/optimizing-your-life/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://time.com/2933971/how-to-motivate-yourself-3-steps-backed-by-science/?utm_source=pocket&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_campaign=pockethits">How to Motivate Yourself: 3 Steps Backed By Science</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/9wr/my_algorithm_for_beating_procrastination/">My Algorithm for Beating Procrastination</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.makeuseof.com/tag/ultimate-cheat-sheet-becoming-great-public-speaker/">The Ultimate Cheat Sheet To Becoming A Great Public Speaker</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/28/upshot/looking-at-productivity-as-a-state-of-mind.html?abt=0002&amp;abg=0">Looking at Productivity as a State of Mind - NYTimes.com</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.ecommercefuel.com/my-corporate-escape-story/">My Corporate Escape Story | From Overworked to World Travel</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://lifehacker.com/how-to-make-the-most-of-a-mentor-and-get-ahead-in-your-1646087771">How to Make the Most of a Mentor and Get Ahead in Your Career</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/ij/update_yourself_incrementally/">Update Yourself Incrementally - Less Wrong</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/xnPFYBuaGhpq869mY/ureshiku-naritai">Ureshiku Naritai</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://thenextweb.com/lifehacks/2014/11/23/physics-productivity-newtons-laws-getting-stuff-done">The physics of productivity: Newton’s laws for getting stuff done</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2011/01/eight-weeks-to-a-better-brain/">Eight weeks to a better brain | Harvard Gazette</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.makeuseof.com/tag/ultimate-cheat-sheet-becoming-great-public-speaker/">The Ultimate Cheat Sheet To Becoming A Great Public Speaker</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://habrahabr.ru/post/246639/">Три способа не выполнить цели на 2015 год / Хабрахабр</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.marcandangel.com/2014/12/21/27-simple-things-to-start-doing-for-your-happiness/">27 Simple Things to Start Doing for Your Happiness</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2014/05/life-weeks.html">Your Life in Weeks | Wait But Why</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lifehacker.com/how-to-overcome-your-own-laziness-1676371259?utm_campaign=socialflow_lifehacker_facebook&amp;utm_source=lifehacker_facebook&amp;utm_medium=socialflow">How to Overcome Your Own Laziness</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lemire.me/blog/archives/2014/12/30/how-to-learn-efficiently/">How to learn efficiently</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/5kz/the_5second_level/">The 5-Second Level</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/r/discussion/lw/juc/optimal_exercise/">Optimal Exercise - Less Wrong Discussion</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://99u.adobe.com/articles/7230/hacking-habits-how-to-make-new-behaviors-last-for-good">Hacking Habits: How To Make New Behaviors Last For Good</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://productizeandscale.com/decision-paralysis/">Break Out of Decision Paralysis</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bbc.com/future/story/20150324-the-hidden-tricks-of-persuasion">BBC - Future - The hidden tricks of powerful persuasion</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.raptitude.com/2011/10/7-high-leverage-life-skills-they-should-teach-in-grade-school/">7 High-leverage life skills they should teach in grade school</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.garlikov.com/Soc_Meth.html">The Socratic Method</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://kellymcgonigal.com/willpowerinstinct/">The Willpower Instinct</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://megaplan.ru/blog/management/high-five/">ППП: Пять правил переговорщика</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.actionablebooks.com/en-ca/summaries/think-grow-rich/">Think &amp; Grow Rich – Actionable Books</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.actionablebooks.com/en-ca/summaries/who-moved-my-cheese/">Who Moved My Cheese – Actionable Books</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/246118">The Ultimate Guide to Learning Anything Faster </a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.adaringadventure.com/bestof/20-awesome-self-development-questions/">20 Awesome Self Development Questions - A Daring Adventure</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.structuredprocrastination.com/">Structured Procrastination: Do Less &amp; Deceive Yourself</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/bayes-s-theorem-what-s-the-big-deal/">Bayes's Theorem: What's the Big Deal? - Scientific American Blog Network</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lifehacker.com/how-to-negotiate-your-salary-1566202988">How to Negotiate Your Salary</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2016/03/24/how-to-get-out-of-bed/">The Depressive’s Guide to Getting Out of Bed</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hbr.org/2016/05/learn-to-love-networking">Learn to Love Networking</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://shyal.com/blog/a-simple-mind-hack-that-helps-beat-procrastination">a simple mind hack that helps beat procrastination | shyal.com</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://sivers.org/book/PersonalDevelopmentForSmartPeople">Personal Development for Smart People - by Steve Pavlina | Derek Sivers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.blinkist.com/en/reader/the-hard-thing-about-hard-things-en/">https://www.blinkist.com/en/reader/the-hard-thing-about-hard-things-en/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/diagnosis-diet/201609/preventing-alzheimer-s-disease-is-easier-you-think">Preventing Alzheimer’s Disease May Be Easier Than You Think</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://fourhourworkweek.com/2016/10/20/my-life-extension-pilgrimage-to-easter-island/">My Life Extension Pilgrimage to Easter Island | The Blog of Author Tim Ferr</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/tim-ferriss-on-exercise-to-overcome-fears-2015-4">Tim Ferriss on exercise to overcome fears - Business Insider</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.ycombinator.com/how-do-you-measure-leadership/">How Do You Measure Leadership?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://tim.blog/gear/#orgasm1">On orgasm - The 4-Hour Body Tools | The Blog of Author Tim Ferriss</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.05060">Functional Decision Theory: A New Theory of Instrumental Rationality</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.goodreads.com/book/show/324750.High_Output_Management">High Output Management</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/fc3/checklist_of_rationality_habits/">Checklist of Rationality Habits</a><br /><br />
2019-11-10 update:<br /><br /></li>
  <li><a href="https://antongorlin.com/blog/photography-composition-definitive-guide/">Photography Composition: The Definitive Guide - Beautiful Pictures</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.7pace.com/blog/become-a-better-programmer-skills-development">How to Become a Better Software Developer: A Handbook on Personal Performan</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/strohl89/posts/10154358190599598"><strong>Brienne Yudkowsky’s 5-minute focused grit process</strong></a></li>
  <li><a href="https://alexvermeer.com/what-in-my-life-is-opaque/">What in my life is opaque?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://alexvermeer.com/so-good-they-cant-ignore-you-by-cal-newport-review-and-summary/">So Good They Can’t Ignore You by Cal Newport – Review &amp; Summary</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=18733535">Ask HN: How to shadow a CEO? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://fs.blog/mental-models/">Mental Models: The Best Way to Make Intelligent Decisions (109 Models Explained)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.samaltman.com/how-to-be-successful">How To Be Successful - Sam Altman</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://secretpmhandbook.com/persuasion-tips-for-product-managers/">Persuasion Tips For Product Managers - The Secret Product Manager Handbook</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.quora.com/What-distinguishes-the-Top-1-of-product-managers-from-the-Top-10/answer/Ian-McAllister">Ian McAllister's answer to What distinguishes the Top 1% of product managers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/@duncanr/deadlines-are-killing-us-and-almost-everything-else-i-know-about-leadership-7032a5fb12ac">Deadlines Are Killing Us, And Almost Everything Else I Know About Leadershi</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/humaning-is-hard/%D0%BF%D1%80%D1%8F%D0%BC%D0%B0%D1%8F-%D0%BE%D0%B1%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%82%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%8F-%D1%81%D0%B2%D1%8F%D0%B7%D1%8C-%D0%BA%D0%B0%D0%BA-%D1%8D%D1%84%D1%84%D0%B5%D0%BA%D1%82%D0%B8%D0%B2%D0%BD%D0%B5%D0%B5-%D1%81%D1%81%D0%BE%D1%80%D0%B8%D1%82%D1%8C%D1%81%D1%8F-%D1%81-%D0%BA%D0%BE%D0%BB%D0%BB%D0%B5%D0%B3%D0%B0%D0%BC%D0%B8-30b3bb93a58a">Прямая обратная связь: как эффективнее ссориться с коллегами</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://doist.com/blog/complete-guide-to-deep-work/">The Complete Guide to Deep Work (including a step-by-step checklist)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.drmaciver.com/2019/05/how-to-do-hard-things/">How to do hard things | David R. MacIver</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://cognitiontoday.com/2019/05/you-procrastinate-because-of-emotions-not-laziness-regulate-them-to-stop-procrastinating/">You Procrastinate Because Of Emotions, Not Laziness. Regulate Them To Stop </a></li>
  <li><a href="https://effectiviology.com/self-distancing-rational-decisions/">Self-Distancing: What It Is and How You Can Use It to Make Better Decisions</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.pragmaticengineer.com/on-writing-well/">Undervalued Software Engineering Skills: Writing Well</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://nav.al/how-to-get-rich">How to Get Rich: Every Episode – Naval</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.stephsmith.io/how-to-be-great/">How to Be Great? Just be Good, Repeatably</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.reboot.io/service/peer-groups/">Find your Leadership Peer Group with Reboot Circles</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/sixstringalice/posts/10219251823384559">The Living Room event for building communities - Alisa Kuznetsova</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://fs.blog/2014/02/decision-journal/">How a Decision Journal Changed the Way I make Decisions (Template Included)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://science.sciencemag.org/content/365/6455/834.full">Stand out as a speaker | Science</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://codejamming.org/2019/how-to-return-to-flow">How to return to the flow faster | Code Jamming</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20920635">Ask HN: What things do you wish you discovered earlier? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.elidedbranches.com/2017/09/how-do-managers-get-stuck.html">Elided Branches: How do managers* get stuck?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://onezero.medium.com/being-indistractable-will-be-the-skill-of-the-future-a07780cf36f4">Being ‘Indistractable’ Will Be the Skill of the Future</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://apenwarr.ca/log/20190926">What do executives do, anyway? - apenwarr</a></li>
</ol>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/06/08/List-of-self-improvement-related-links</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Biohacking and me</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/06/02/Biohacking-and-me</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Serge Faguet is an entrepreneur that has written three long controversial articles on Hackernoon and revamped the term ‘biohacking’ for me.</p>

<p>The articles were designed to get attention, so please look past misused memes and click-baity headings.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://hackernoon.com/im-32-and-spent-200k-on-biohacking-became-calmer-thinner-extroverted-healthier-happier-2a2e846ae113">I’m 32 and spent $200k on biohacking. Became calmer, thinner, extroverted, healthier &amp; happier</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hackernoon.com/biohack-your-intelligence-now-or-become-obsolete-97cdd15e395f">How to biohack your intelligence — with everything from sex to modafinil to MDMA</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hackernoon.com/how-i-set-and-execute-50-year-goals-why-i-see-cutting-in-lines-as-morally-right-f4d0ce28574f">How I set and execute 50-year goals + why I see cutting in lines as morally right</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Serge was also a CEO of a company I used to work for. While still a CEO, he did several seminars where he described his reasoning and methods behind (then called) life-optimization. I am one of the people that that was sold on the less hardcore part.</p>

<h3 id="what-does-it-mean-for-me-in-practical-terms">What does it mean for me in practical terms?</h3>

<ol>
  <li>A quarterly blood panel of around 50 blood markers</li>
  <li>Implementation of strategies to change the markers that are not in the green (e.g. try supplements, change training routines, etc)</li>
  <li>Eat less sugar. Switching from a lifetime consumption of the family-recipe homemade jam was hard at first, but now I actually enjoy how food tastes without any added sweetness</li>
  <li>Intermittent fasting protocol where I eat during 6-8 hours of a day, leaving the rest to fasting</li>
  <li>Sleeping at the same times daily: going to bed before 22:00 and waking up at 06:30.</li>
  <li>Daily meditation</li>
  <li>Free weights exercise. I used to do HIIT, but paused as my main goal is gaining muscle at the moment</li>
</ol>

<h4 id="what-i-havent-done-yet-but-plan-to">What I haven’t done yet but plan to</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Ketogenic diet for reported cognitive enhancements</li>
  <li>Prolonged fasting as a cancer prevention</li>
  <li>SSRIs and <em>legal</em> drugs</li>
  <li>More sleep experiments (<em>total</em> darkness, coolness, and optimal CO2) with help from devices like oura ring</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-results">The results</h3>
<p><strong>Updated after two years</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>I’m more physically active and enjoy a better focus on the days that I’ve slept well, exercised and ate healthy. According to my self-testing.</li>
  <li>I benefit from my life being more structured, i.e. when I <a href="/2018/03/01/Why-choices-are-bad">don’t have to decide</a> when to get out of bed, or what to eat today.</li>
  <li>Blood panel has yet to lead to any actionable insights. Well, at least now I have a snapshot of how things were when I was 30 for reference in the future.</li>
  <li>If nothing else, I view it all as a healthy hobby that is also a handy conversation piece.</li>
</ul>

<p>After two years I’ve <a href="/2018/07/07/Do-you-update-your-model-with-your-actual-experiences">learned to be less rigid</a> about these habits and indulge in a late night with friends now and then, knowing that the fatigue price I will be paying the next day is worth it.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/06/02/Biohacking-and-me</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>85 Things I learned being a CEO</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/05/20/85-things-i-learned-being-a-ceo</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>A Hackernoon <a href="https://hackernoon.com/85-things-i-learned-being-a-ceo-4c25fc1c7b99">post</a> where <em>Sachin Gupta</em> details lessons from his CEO career in the areas of job’s key responsibilities, decision making, culture, leadership, self-management, people management, meetings, hiring, and fundraising.</p>

<p>Currently, the most relevant for me are these parts about meetings</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Explicitly ask people if you are needed to be part of a meeting. Wherever you are needed, ask them for an agenda and also ask what is expected from you in the meeting. Else say no.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are only 2 types of meetings that you should attend — a) where you have to take a decision b) where you get updates/information. The productivity of the first depends solely on you and the latter on how you have trained your team. Step out from any meeting where you are not going to take any decision and you are not getting information you already don’t have.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/05/20/85-things-i-learned-being-a-ceo</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 20 May 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Six Steps to a Daily Writing Habit</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/05/12/Six-steps-to-a-daily-writing-habit</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>How to use Beeminder for a daily habit of X.<br />
<a href="http://socratic-form-microscopy.com/2017/06/18/six-steps-to-a-daily-writing-habit/">A great post</a> by <em>Zachary Jacobi</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I recommend looking at Beeminder not as a tool to effectively guilt yourself into writing, but as a reminder of what writing is worth to you. You value consistently writing at $X. You know that every time you skip writing for a day or a week, there is a Y% chance that you might lose the habit. Multiply those two together and you get your ideal maximum Beeminder pledge.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Right now <a href="https://www.beeminder.com/bizzz/pocket">I use Beeminder</a> to read up all of my pocketed articles.<br />
Sometime in the past couple of years I’ve created a bad akrasia-like habit of pocketing articles that are too hard to read at that moment. “Imma read this funny small LJ post now and let future-Andrey handle that huge SSC post later”. I also used to add some neat posts that are useless to me (e.g. HN post about how to use ardruino and tensorflow to detect misoginy in Sillicon Valley). Thus I amassed hundreds of articles and tons of guilt.<br />
Now, each time I add an article, a point is substracted; a point is added each time I finish one (automation through <a href="https://ifttt.com/pocket">IFTTT snippets</a>). In the last three months, I’ve ploughed through 150 articles, some 400 yet to go.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/05/12/Six-steps-to-a-daily-writing-habit</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Life satisfaction depending on number of children</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/05/05/Life-satisfaction-depending-on-number-of-children</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>My current position is <em>against</em> having children due to huge time commitment necessary to raise them. I do not factor in children’s happiness or their possible utility to the world into my decision. But then again, I am not an effective altruist (yet?) and do not have a pronounced moral stance as Scott does.</p>

<p>Here’s a <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/16/bundles-of-joy/">post</a> by <em>Scott Alexander</em> where he analyses his survey results in the context of life satisfaction of people having children. After reading this, I’m a tad more inclined to think about it.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/05/05/Life-satisfaction-depending-on-number-of-children</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 05 May 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Maybe The Real Superintelligent AI Is Extremely Smart Computers</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/05/01/Maybe-the-real-superintelligent-ai-is-extremely-smart-computers</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I love Ted Chiang novels, especially ‘Understand’, but man-oh-man, that was a hilarious bashing to read. Scott Alexander <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/15/maybe-the-real-superintelligent-ai-is-extremely-smart-computers/">is on the roll</a> with his kabbalah metaphors.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/05/01/Maybe-the-real-superintelligent-ai-is-extremely-smart-computers</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Why Am I So Lazy?</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/30/Why-am-i-so-lazy</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Heather Havrilesky</em> with her raw, passionate and poignant article about (re)defining your self. <a href="https://www.thecut.com/2018/01/ask-polly-why-am-i-so-lazy.html">Why Am I So Lazy?</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You know how they say “Scratch a cynic, find a romantic”? Well, scratch an underachiever and find a hard worker afraid of disappointing herself. Both the cynic and the underachiever are afraid of sticking their necks out and becoming who they deeply, passionately want to become, for fear of looking stupid or failing. […] I’ll bet you’re not even an introvert at heart. You’re someone who wants to live out loud, share herself with the world, and stop overthinking and delaying and avoiding the pesky little tasks that make up a life.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sometimes I wonder if I’m that romantic in hiding. While, indeed, I can be <em>skeptical</em> about all this passion-speech, in the end Heather recommends much of the same approach that I currently support: experimentation.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Get a therapist. Experiment with schedules. Try on different behaviors for size. Get very organized (without piles of things on the floor). Try making new friends. Try vigorous exercise. Try leaving the house more. Try not leaving. Try writing your feelings down. Check in with your body when you do things that stress you out. Notice your feelings. Express your feelings. Be honest, be honest, be honest. Take notes.</p>
</blockquote>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/04/30/Why-am-i-so-lazy</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 30 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Happiness Is a Chore</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/21/Happiness-is-chore</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em><strong>UPD</strong> This post rises some important questions, so I promote it to the index page for visibility.</em><br />
The pursuit of happiness defines many parts of my life. Or should I say “happiness”?</p>

<p><em>SquirrelInHell</em> writes about an unbelievable problem that <a href="https://squirrelinhell.blogspot.se/2017/12/happiness-is-chore.html">Happiness Is a Chore</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>See, the human activity you describe as “pursuing happiness” […] seems to be in the same category as other common activities such as “acquiring education”, “helping people”, “talking to friends” (or should I say “talking” to “friends”) and so on. Which is to say, people do them in a way which is outwardly convincing enough to allow everyone to keep up the social pretenses. This is way different from what you’d see people do if they actually cared. The simple matter of fact is that the human brain is a kludge, and people are puppets dancing on the strings of a mad puppetmaster. Almost anything they claim to be doing isn’t for real. This is true even when they themselves know about this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is strongly related to <a href="/2018/03/09/Why-dont-we-try-really-doing-things">The Thing and the Symbolic Representation of The Thing</a>. (Next quote is still from <em>SquirrelInHell</em>)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[…] I enjoy and see great value in happiness when it happens, but when it doesn’t I only work on it grudgingly. It’s like with exercise, which is great but I’m rarely enthusiastic about starting it. The problem is not that I don’t value happiness enough. The problem is rather that there is no gut-level motivational gradient to get actual happiness. There are gradients for all sorts of things which are crappy, fake substitutes. […] But you still end up optimizing for them, because that’s what your brain does.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>↑ This indeed, as <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/3Hkpttb6WsJwr5WdF/happiness-is-a-chore#BP2j9rDHr9SqMjDh9">one LW commenter points out</a>, looks like akrasia. And will probably benefit from methods that are good against akrasia.</p>

<p>Related, SquirrelInHell’s site <a href="http://bewelltuned.com/">Be Well Tuned</a> (“a very unusual guide to improving your brain and your life”). I’ve added it to my to-do list <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/tag/goal">#goals</a></p>

<hr />

<p><strong>UPD</strong><br />
After rereading through everything linked above, I see that, at this moment, I’m <em>focused</em> on riding my hedonic treadmill, solving various optimization problems, and I’m <strong>not mindful</strong> about it; also not happy. This is a tendency I have. After talking about it with my psychotherapist, I will experiment with making more unsctrutured time and enjoying it; also spending less time on hardcore goal-oriented activities.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/04/21/Happiness-is-chore</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 21 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Planning fallacy</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/14/Planning-fallacy</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Eliezer Yudkowsky</em> about <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/CPm5LTwHrvBJCa9h5/planning-fallacy">Planning Fallacy</a></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>The planning fallacy is that people think they can plan, ha ha.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>While planning, and in need of <em>realistic</em> scenario, people instead think of <em>best-case scenario</em>. (See the article for related studies.)<br />
Now on to how to fix it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So there is a fairly reliable way to fix the planning fallacy, if you’re doing something broadly similar to a reference class of previous projects. Just ask how long similar projects have taken in the past, without considering any of the special properties of this project.  Better yet, ask an experienced outsider how long similar projects have taken.<br />
You’ll get back an answer that sounds hideously long, and clearly reflects no understanding of the special reasons why this particular task will take less time. This answer is true.  Deal with it.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/04/14/Planning-fallacy</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>On-demand everything</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Lauren Smiley</em> about <a href="https://medium.com/matter/the-shut-in-economy-ec3ec1294816">The Shut-In Economy</a><br />
“In the new world of on-demand everything, you’re either pampered, isolated royalty — or you’re a 21st century servant.”</p>

<p>Click-bait false dichotomy aside, this is an interesting area to think about. Is the future of work looks like a bunch of APIs for people?</p>

<p>I can image it being quite dystopian: install an app, answer some questions about your abilities, qualifications, schedule, etc. and <em>poof</em> your time is auto-magically assigned to be spent in the most efficient way (most cost-efficient way for the API-hubs companies, that is).</p>

<p>Extreme optimization also may look like little additions to your daily life: The App nudges you to buy extra ice-cream on your way home; when you are on a red light, another <del>drone</del> App user comes up to you and takes the ice-cream. She’s going home herself but is making a small detour to deliver that ice-cream to the one that ordered it. That order was placed automatically too, after analyzing customer’s biometric and social graph data (ML model says: though breakup) and coming to a conclusion that to maximize LTV, this purchase was needed. It also may lead to a need for a fitness programme purchase later, but again, that’s just LTV maximizing, nothing personal.</p>

<p>Ok, back to our totally different world and the article at hand.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The luxuries usually afforded to one-percenters now stretch to the urban upper-middle class, or so the technology industry cheers.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/114/32/8523.full">a study</a> saying</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Around the world, increases in wealth have produced an unintended consequence: a rising sense of time scarcity. We provide evidence that using money to buy time can provide a buffer against this time famine, thereby promoting happiness.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There’s also the gender angle:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>That’s the other side of this, the gender one. The errands being served up by the on-demand economy — cooking, cleaning, laundry, groceries, runs to the post office — all were all once, and in many places still are, the jobs of stay-at-home mothers. Even now, when women outnumber men in the formal workplace, they continue to bear the brunt of that invisible domestic work, often for many, many hours a week. So women — those who can afford it, at least — have the most to win from passing that load on to somebody else.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I usually pre-order food to work, and sometimes hire a cleaning service — it saves a lot of time indeed, and, as I start to have less free time, I increasingly value it. I’m thinking of outsourcing making my breakfast and dinner too.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>How successful people work less — and get more done</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/04/07/How-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Travis Bradberry</em> on <a href="https://qz.com/386166/how-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done/">How successful people work less—and get more done</a><br />
Quite a diverse list of things, actually:</p>

<ol>
  <li>They disconnect</li>
  <li>They <a href="/2018/04/07/On-demand-everything">minimize chores</a></li>
  <li>They reflect</li>
  <li>They exercise</li>
  <li>They pursue a passion</li>
  <li>They spend quality time with family</li>
  <li>They schedule micro-adventures</li>
  <li>They wake up at the same time</li>
  <li>They designate mornings as “me time”</li>
  <li>They prepare for the upcoming week</li>
  <li><del>But most importantly, they attac</del></li>
</ol>

<p>See the article for more details. This list is by no means scientific, I included it here as a <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/tag/goal/">goal-reminder</a>: I already do more than half of it, probably should look into what’s left.</p>

<hr />

<blockquote>
  <p>The study found that productivity per hour declines sharply when the workweek exceeds 50 hours, and productivity drops off so much after 55 hours that there’s no point in working any more. That’s right, people who work as much as 70 hours (or more) per week actually get the same amount done as people who work 55 hours.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Note that they studied people productivity in <em>manufacturing</em>, e.g. “Forty Women Milling a Screw Thread on Fuze Bodies”, I’m not sure how well it translates to creative work.</p>

<p>At first I grabbed this article and sent it to people who (I think) overwork. To which they countered that output of 55 hours is still bigger than that of 40 hours of work. Of course you have to pay the price, but still, if you’re willing and can do so sustainably, you really can get more done by working more than 8 hours a day (or without weekends).</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/04/07/How-successful-people-work-less-and-get-more-done</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Tony Robbins interview with Tim Ferriss - my takeaways</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/31/Tony-Robbins-interview-with-Tim-Ferriss-my-takeaways</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I’ve first heard Tony Robbins’ interviews sometime in 2016. I was fascinated: a great story-teller and he speaks about things that interest me — mood-states that affect behavior, and how to change your energy levels. Here are my takeaways from one of his <a href="https://encrypted.google.com/search?q=Tony+Robbins+site%3Atim.blog">interviews with Tim Ferriss</a>. Each paragraph is a <strong>paraphrased</strong> quote from Tony followed by my comment in <em>italics</em>.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>You have to give to prosper. Even if you think you don’t have enough.</p>

    <p><em>That is something I struggle with as it’s not obvious to me <strong>why</strong> I should divert resources from myself. I’m going to speak with effective altruists (EA) and try and get convinced.</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Number one quality to foster is staying hungry, this will bring others along. How to do it? Be among people who are successful. You are who you spend time with. To be happy you need to grow.</p>

    <p><em>This is also something that is hard for me - by default I don’t value friendship that much. At least I understand the logic here and I’m making progress: meeting new people and starting (non-romantic) relationships with them.</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Failure is a part of life. It doesn’t need to stop you. It’s a stepping stone to success, speed bump. I know I’m going to fail, but it’s not failure if you learn something. We don’t value what we don’t fight for. Like cheating in video games. There’s no such thing as effortless approach.</p>

    <p><em>I did have a belief along the lines of “life <strong>should</strong> be easy”. And that was (and still is sometimes) a source of discontent for me.</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Money doesn’t change you, it magnifies what you already are.</p>

    <p><em>That is also why I think I should start donating now, and looks like that is what EA guys preach too (donate at least 1% to create a habit)</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The most important decision in your life is deciding whether you’re truly committed to being happy no matter what. You will experience extreme stress, no matter what. Life’s too short to suffer. Decide to be in a beautiful state. <strong>This brain is not designed to make you happy, it’s designed to make you survive</strong>. You have to work to be happy.</p>

    <p><em>See also Tim Urban’s <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/06/taming-mammoth-let-peoples-opinions-run-life.html">Social Survival Mammoth</a></em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Highest experiences in life have this in common: there is some growth within ourselves (face a fear, overcome something, etc) and some contribution beyond ourselves.
Worst experiences are about only you. When you are suffering it’s because you’re obsessing about yourself. Something happened and you have less of something, or you lost something (love, money, significance, attention). Loss, less, never are the sources of suffering. All suffering is obsession with self. Snap out of your suffering. Stop expecting and start appreciating things outside of yourself: people, nature. You learn and grow from that. If you love, if you give, if you’re grateful - suffering disappears instantly.</p>

    <p><em>It’s a good a place to paste my favorite quote from a Haruki Murakami book cover: “Pain is inevitable. Suffering is optional.”</em></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Later in 2016 I’ve decided to attend one of Tony’s seminars to get some of that energy from the man himself. I attended UPW London 2017 and it was like a giant dancing rave with applied psychology and lots of hugs. I loved it.<br />
After I go through my notes, I’ll post my takeaways from there as well.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/31/Tony-Robbins-interview-with-Tim-Ferriss-my-takeaways</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 31 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0300</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Religion, growth framework and enlightenment</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Religion-growth-framework-and-enlightenment</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Tim Urban</em> about <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/10/religion-for-the-nonreligious.html">Religion for the Nonreligious</a><br />
Like many of his great posts, this one is long. I’ve read it in 2015 when I was struggling to find my way around religion and it stroke a chord. <em>For me</em>, it’s about two things:</p>

<h4 id="1-states-of-mind">1. States of mind</h4>
<p>(1) Engulfed in primitive, primal thoughts<br />
(2) See things as they are, enlightenment</p>

<h4 id="2-creating-a-better-belief-system">2. Creating a better belief system</h4>
<p>…smelted with a <em>growth framework</em>.<br />
Coincidentally, growth framework is something that I lacked in 2015. I now have a system in place, it’s still new and I’m not as religious about it as Tim. I will make a post about it after 1 year test-drive.</p>

<p>Short quote</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Yes, I’m an atheist, but atheism isn’t a growth model any more than “I don’t like rollerblading” is a workout strategy.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/25/Religion-growth-framework-and-enlightenment</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Giving up too hastily on hard goals</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/25/Giving-up-too-hastily-on-hard-goals</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Eliezer Yudkowsky</em>’s  <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/fhEPnveFhb9tmd7Pe/use-the-try-harder-luke">Use the Try Harder, Luke</a>
— is a short funny story about how we’re conditioned for giving up fast, after (also hastily) labeling something as impossible.</p>

<p>This continues with a longer piece <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/fpecAJLG9czABgCe9/on-doing-the-impossible">On Doing the Impossible</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To do things that are very difficult or “impossible”,<br />
First you have to not run away.  That takes seconds.<br />
Then you have to work.  That takes hours.<br />
Then you have to stick at it.  That takes years.</p>
</blockquote>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/25/Giving-up-too-hastily-on-hard-goals</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 25 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Taking Children Seriously - philosophy of parenting</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/24/Taking-children-seriously-philosophy-of-parenting</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Elliot Temple</em> about <a href="http://fallibleideas.com/taking-children-seriously">Taking Children Seriously</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Taking Children Seriously (TCS) is a rational, non-coercive philosophy of parenting and learning which says:</p>
</blockquote>

<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>* The main goal of parenting is to help children learn.  
* Punishing doesn’t help with learning.  
* Reason helps everyone win.  
* Ignorance isn’t stupidity.  
* Children aren’t fragile.  
* Obedience and rules are bad.
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>Looks like a great rational framework for parenting. Many ‘enable everything’ or ‘obedience is the only way’ ways of parenting just don’t sit well with me, this one does. 
It also underscores my existing belief that <em>parenting is hard</em>.</p>

<p>For the sake of history, my current argument <strong>against having children</strong> goes like this: <br />
raising children requires a lot of time and this time commitment is at least for <strong>18.75 years</strong>.
Anecdotal <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">it's worth it</code> from the parents I know can really be some sort of Stockholm syndrome. I mean, if you have a child already and you don’t like it, you have the choice of suffering (bad for you and the child) or learning how to love it and make the best of the situation. Leaving a child looks like a heavy conscience penalty so it’s out of the consideration.</p>

<p>Please tell me if you have a counter to this line of thinking. It does look shaky and I definitely will need to do a full analysis of this question later.</p>

<p>P.S. Here are some <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2018/01/16/bundles-of-joy/">stats on life satisfaction depending on number of children from SSC</a> (spoiler: more children - more satisfaction).</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/24/Taking-children-seriously-philosophy-of-parenting</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 24 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Why it&apos;s easy to start a subpar relationship</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/17/Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>And what to do about it.</p>

<p>Here’s what’s happening when I’m not in a relationship for some time.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-1.png" alt="Graph 1, described in text below" /></p>

<p>Acceptable partner attractiveness (APA) is everything I seek for in a partner: physical beauty, personal qualities, etc.</p>

<ul>
  <li>When I am in a relationship, APA is at max level.</li>
  <li>As a relationship ends, my APA lingers at max for a bit and then starts to lower.</li>
  <li>After I start a new relationship, APA goes back to max levels.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="problems">Problems</h2>

<h3 id="it-becomes-harder-to-date-more-attractive-partners">It becomes harder to date more attractive partners</h3>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/scumbag_brain.png" alt="Scumbag brain" /></p>

<p>My primitive mind auto-applies dates’ <em>courting easiness</em> labels based on <em>attractiveness</em>. The less attractive the date, the easier it seems to court her.</p>

<p>I am programmed to do least possible amount work to achieve my goals so, if acting by default, I will court dates with lower perceived attractiveness because it seems like less work, and still gets acceptable result. <strong>Why try hard when easy’s good enough?</strong> My amygdala doesn’t care that the result is only acceptable right in that moment and will become unacceptable soon after that.</p>

<h3 id="its-easier-to-begin-an-unacceptable-relationship">It’s easier to begin an unacceptable relationship</h3>

<p>Maybe it’s just me, but when you’re fresh out of a relationship, you don’t seem too eager to jump start a new one. But as the loneliness goes on, desire for <em>a</em> relationship grows.
<strong>So not only your requirements are lowered, you actually <em>want</em> being in a relationship more, exactly at the time when they are low</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-2.png" alt="Graph 2, yearning for a relationship grows with time" /></p>

<h4 id="yearning-for-relationship-correlates-with-easiness-of-starting-a-subpar-relationship-">Yearning for relationship correlates with easiness of starting a subpar relationship :(</h4>

<p>As the acceptable standard lowers, the pool of available partners grows and it’s easier to start a new relationship.
There would not be a problem if acceptable SO attractiveness didn’t rise to the max after that, but it does and the consequences are dire.</p>

<p>Being in a relationship that doesn’t satisfy you sucks.
The internal conflict rises: should I stay or should I go? <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BN1WwnEDWAM">♫</a><br />
It’s not an easy choice, you have emotional attachment and a whole host of cognitive biases working against you:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    Wanting to stay in a relationship is reinforced by many biases (status quo bias, ambiguity effect, choice supportive bias, loss aversion, mere-exposure effect, ostrich effect). For someone to break through all those biases and end things, they must be extremely unhappy.
  </p>
  <footer><cite><a href="http://lesswrong.com/lw/m78/strategies_and_tools_for_getting_through_a_break/">Strategies and tools for getting through a break up</a></cite></footer>
</blockquote>

<p>The more this draws on the more stakes are in opportunity cost and the more it becomes harder to break things apart. Some stay in this state of conflict throughout their whole lives.</p>

<p>Worth mentioning: I am not an <em>extreme</em> idealist, I understand there can be compromises. Here I am speaking of cases when you can’t compromise after standards go up again.</p>

<h2 id="why-do-the-standards-fall">Why do the standards fall</h2>
<p><img src="https://www.lepekhin.com/images/2018-03-17-Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship-graph-3.png" alt="Graph 3, progression of acceptable partner attractiveness criteria for high (just after relationship) to low (just before starting a relationship) to high again" /></p>

<p>I think that it’s a response to one of the basic needs not being met.<br />
I’ll try a metaphor. Imagine you do not have a place to sleep. In the morning you do not need to sleep so your idea of a place to sleep is a 5-star hotel. In the afternoon you become a little sleepier and make vague attempts on finding <em>a</em> hotel, <em>any</em> hotel. In the evening you’re sleepy and really need a place to rest, and will agree on a capsule hotel or a hostel.</p>

<p>Or maybe it’s just evolution nudging: “Come on, stop thinking, procreate!”.</p>

<h3 id="why-do-the-standards-rise-again">Why do the standards rise again</h3>
<p>It looks like a natural thing to happen after a bare minimum of a need is met.
In a place-to-sleep example above: after a night in a capsule hotel you do feel somewhat refreshed, but you also understand that you <em>need</em> silence to sleep really well.</p>

<h2 id="what-to-do">What to do</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Forewarned is forearmed. Just keeping this whole thing in mind helps me in some cases.</li>
  <li>I’ve created and maintain my <em>partner criteria list</em> and filter out my new dates under a threat of suffering (unsatisfactory relationship).<br />
This doesn’t help with increased perceived difficultness of dating more attractive partners; I’m still searching a solution for that.</li>
</ol>

<p>Maybe it’s solvable by casual sex without serious relationships? Maybe if you fulfill your basic needs elsewhere, your standards do not lower?</p>

<ul>
  <li>Friends with benefits - doesn’t work for me, as it usually grows into a relationship.</li>
  <li>One-night-stands - I didn’t have that many encounters so I cannot generalize. Should look into it.</li>
  <li>Paying for sex (here’s <a href="https://hackernoon.com/biohack-your-intelligence-now-or-become-obsolete-97cdd15e395f">Serge Faguet’s take on it</a>) - same as above.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>What did I miss?</strong> How do <em>you</em> solve this problem? Please <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/about#contact-me">share</a>.</p>

<h3 id="ps">P.S.</h3>

<p>If you are my partner and you’re wondering what if I secretly think of you as a subpar choice, I have good news.
This post is a public commitment: I will only start relationships with those who meet my criteria for a partner. It still doesn’t make our relationship bulletproof and there are ways it can go awry, but at least I (and you) have one less thing to worry about.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/17/Why-its-easy-to-start-a-subpar-relationship</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>16 things I know are true but haven’t quite learned yet</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/10/16-things-i-know-are-true-but-havent-quite-learned-yet</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>David Cain</em> <a href="http://www.raptitude.com/2013/12/16-things-i-know-are-true-but-havent-quite-learned-yet/">about things that he knows are good for him but he still only does them seldomly</a>.</p>

<p>Number 8 will <em>blow your mind</em>! Just kidding. But seriously, I’ll quote the ones that apply to me the most:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>2) I never regret working out. […]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>10) The quickest and most reliable path to personal improvement is to do the things on my list that I resist most. […]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>11) All you need to do to finish things is keep starting them until they’re done. […]</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>14) The most consistently joyful activities for me are visiting with other people and reading books.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>After spending most of my life preferring various solitary entertainments to <em>socializing</em>, I’ve recently came to similar understanding about meeting other people. It seems to energize me and fill me with joy (self-reported mood data supports it). The trick is to find like-minded people. Maybe I’ll write a post about it sometime - it was a very big change in my life.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/10/16-things-i-know-are-true-but-havent-quite-learned-yet</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/10/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/479/"><img src="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/3-e1520299525393.jpg" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/479/">http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/479/</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/10/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>My process and goals for writing in this blog</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/10/My-process-and-goals-for-writing-in-this-blog</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I describe my processes for writing here and the goals behind those processes. Previously: <a href="/2018/02/24/Hello-world">first post in the blog and why I did it.</a></p>

<p>I’ll just dive into different types of posts and describe the process and goals for each type.</p>

<h2 id="type-link-posts">Type: Link-posts</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/category/links/">Links to articles, posts</a>, <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/category/comics/">webcomics</a> etc
— are not included in the general blog roll in the root of this blog</p>

<h3 id="purpose">Purpose</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Satisfy the sharing need: when I find something thought-provoking I get a craving to share it</li>
  <li>Learn something better by explaining it</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="process">Process</h3>
<ol>
  <li>Get a link into my Pocket mainly from: Hacker News and other IT-infused sources, friends, colleagues or RSS.</li>
  <li>Read it. If I find some parts that 1) are interesting new information, and 2) probably will improve my life if applied — I share those parts with myself via email.</li>
  <li>Once in a blue moon I read through such emails and weed out things that are no longer interesting. Maybe it seemed useful and now does not, or maybe I was trying to be trendy and now I see though my past-self. Time buffer.</li>
  <li>If I still feel like that info is useful, I then create a <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/category/links/">link-post</a> with a small description and key quotes so that future-me (and you, dear reader) can get to the point faster.</li>
  <li><strong>TODO</strong> Schedule re-reading of old posts or make an anki-like thing to remember and use practical parts.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="type-general-blog-posts">Type: General blog posts</h2>
<p>— the default type of posts that you see in the root if this blog. 
General blog posts are almost the same as link-posts above but I feel a lot more strongly about sharing these: their perceived importance is high. Also they tend to contain more text written by yours truly.</p>

<h3 id="purpose-1">Purpose</h3>
<p>Getting more writing experience for</p>
<ul>
  <li>the skill of getting my point across <em>quicker</em></li>
  <li>creating a thought-archive which I can analyze, and improve upon my thought processes. I think that the ability to write down thoughts is the first major artificial brain augmentation; it would be a shame not to use it.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="process-1">Process</h3>
<p>Same as for link-posts, but more time-consuming. Also, sometimes I have original ideas whereas link-posts are usually just my interpretation of someone else’s ideas.</p>

<hr />

<p>I will update this post if I change the process or the goals.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/10/My-process-and-goals-for-writing-in-this-blog</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 10 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Why don&apos;t we try really doing things</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/09/Why-dont-we-try-really-doing-things</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/12/02/more-dakka/">‘More Dakka’</a> by Zvi starts as a review on Eliezer Yudkowsky’s book Inadequate Eqilibria, and then turns to apply ideas of <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2015/06/30/the-thing-and-the-symbolic-representation-of-the-thing/">The Thing and the Symbolic Representation of The Thing</a> by Zvi, and Scott Alexander’s <a href="http://slatestarcodex.com/2017/11/07/concept-shaped-holes-can-be-impossible-to-notice/">Concept-Shaped Holes Can Be Impossible To Notice</a> to expand on whys and hows of the problem that I can only vaguely name as “Why don’t we try <em>really</em> doing things”. I do recommend reading all three posts, it was a feel-good delta knowledge for me. Here I will focus on ‘More Dakka’ which expands on why we do not try seemingly obvious solutions, or attempt and never finish.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>People express gratitude. We are told it improves subjective well-being in studies. Our subjective well-being improves a little. We could express more gratitude, with no real downsides. Almost all of us don’t.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>If something is a good idea, you need a reason to not try doing more of it. No, seriously. You need a reason.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>do more of what is already working and see if it works more</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Doing <em>the Thing</em> instead of <em>the Symbolic Representation of The Thing</em> is harder because:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li>You need to realize the thing might exist at all.</li>
    <li>You need to realize the symbolic representation of the thing isn’t the thing.</li>
    <li>You need to ignore the idea that you’ve done your job.</li>
    <li>You need to actually care about solving the problem.</li>
    <li>You need to think about the problem a little.</li>
    <li>You need to ignore the idea that no one could blame you for not trying.<br />
[…]</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>And then he explains each one in more detail. It looks like a bunch of small inconveniences that together form a learned helplessness buffer that prevents any actual work getting done.</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Something possibly being slightly socially awkward, or causing a likely nominal failure, acts as a veto. Rationalizations for this are created as needed.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some such worries are real. […] But they’re mostly trying to halt thinking about the object level, to keep you from being the nail that sticks up and gets hammered down. When someone else raises them, mostly <strong>they’re the hammer</strong>. The fears are mirages we’ve been trained and built to see.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>↑ This is one of my <a href="https://www.lepekhin.com/tag/goal">goals</a>: Getting to the object level, asking ‘why?’ and ‘what can be done to overcome this obstacle?’ until <em>the Thing</em> is <em>really</em> done.</p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/09/Why-dont-we-try-really-doing-things</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Why Education Startups Do Not Succeed</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/08/Why-education-startups-do-not-succeed</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Avichal Garg</em> on <a href="https://avichal.com/2011/10/07/why-education-startups-do-not-succeed/">Why Education Startups Do Not Succeed</a> — an interesting article from the guy who co-founded one in <em>2001</em>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You think of education as fundamentally a quality problem. The average person thinks of education as fundamentally a cost problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Educational companies that focus on delivering higher quality solutions to consumers will not scale to the mainstream. Educational companies built around driving down costs to the end consumer will scale.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>His other posts also seem interesting if a bit rare (8 total).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If the Chinese person doesn’t get an education there’s a good chance they will not get a job. They will die poor, unable to adequately feed their children, and unable to take care of their parents […]</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hmm, I wonder if that has something to do with <a href="/2018/03/01/Western-elite-from-Chinese-perspective">admission rates of <em>thousands</em> to one</a> in China universities.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/08/Why-education-startups-do-not-succeed</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 08 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Against Facebook: Comparison to Alternatives and Call to Action</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/06/Against-facebook-comparison-to-alternatives-and-call-to-action</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Basically, Facebook is bad - their goal is maximize the time you use the site (↑ad revenue). That means not allowing for efficient means of getting value out of the site’s main feature: a lot of people. Not allowing you control what and how you see (sort, search, The Zvi also wrote about it <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/04/22/against-facebook/">here</a>)</p>

<p>So here The Zvi describes the alternatives to Facebook:
<a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/04/22/against-facebook-comparison-to-alternatives-and-call-to-action/">https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/04/22/against-facebook-comparison-to-alternatives-and-call-to-action/</a></p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/06/Against-facebook-comparison-to-alternatives-and-call-to-action</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>List of entrepreneur-related links</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/05/List-of-entrepreneur-related-links</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>From time to time I Pocket articles that seem like they would help me when I’ll start working toward my own business.<br />
As I see it now, that time wouldn’t come in <del>2018</del> 2019, so I’ll make a handy stash of these articles here.</p>

<p>That’ll help to <a href="/2018/05/12/Six-steps-to-a-daily-writing-habit">empty out my Pocket</a> and somewhat placate my FOMO (it seems to think that all the cool people are entrepreneurs) without it costing too much:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>— You see, Mr. I-wanna-be-a-successfull-entrepreneur-guy, I’m making progress, my article list is mighty long!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When I come reading, I’ll mark them off the list and maybe even leave comments about their utility.<br />
Also, when I come, I will have to think of something that will prevent paralysis by analysis.</p>

<ol>
  <li><a href="http://30sleeps.com/blog/2007/09/27/set-your-hourly-rate/">http://30sleeps.com/blog/2007/09/27/set-your-hourly-rate/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://m.wikihow.com/Set-Consulting-Fees">http://m.wikihow.com/Set-Consulting-Fees</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://habrahabr.ru/post/225367/">http://habrahabr.ru/post/225367/</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://dilbert.com/blog/entry/the_pivot/">http://dilbert.com/blog/entry/the_pivot/</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="http://planscope.io/blog/giving-up-a-million-dollar-consultancy/">http://planscope.io/blog/giving-up-a-million-dollar-consultancy/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.chiefmarketer.com/5-strategies-for-better-b2b-ecommerce/">5 Strategies for Better B2B Ecommerce - Chiefmarketer</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.searchenginepeople.com/blog/25-conversion-rate-boosters.html">25 Amazing Ways to Boost eCommerce Conversion Rates | Search Engine People</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.iwdagency.com/blog/b2b-vs-b2c-ecommerce-what-are-the-key-differences/">B2B vs. B2C eCommerce: What Are the Key Differences?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=833bf5395122c8de57f99f863&amp;id=5b74c36918&amp;e=b84f647455">Бесплатный труд</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/2014/startup-escape-plan-free-up-time-energy-money-to-invest">Startup Escape Plan: How to free up time, energy &amp; money to build your future</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://letsworkshop.com/freelance-as-a-service/">http://letsworkshop.com/freelance-as-a-service/</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://casjam.com/use-outlines-and-ship/?__vid=659a56d04656013251e722000b2a88d7">http://casjam.com/use-outlines-and-ship/</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="http://casjam.com/loving-the-work/">Loving The Work</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jeremyaboyd.micro.blog/2016/09/01/tricks-to-monetize.html">Tricks to Monetize your Side Projects – Jeremy Boyd</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.ladder.io/business-idea/">How to Test Drive Your Business Idea Before Quitting Your Job</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://medium.com/@gerstenzang/21-management-things-i-learned-at-imgur-7abb72bdf8bf">21 management things I learned at Imgur — Medium</a></strong></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://onstartups.com/tabid/3339/bid/104056/A-Tech-Founder-s-Guide-To-Picking-A-Non-Tech-Founder.aspx">A Tech Founder’s Guide To Picking A Non-Tech Founder</a></strong>
<br /><br /><br />↑ I skimmed over those some time in the past and something caught my eye. Unfortunately past-me didn’t leave a more substantial note. Bold ones are the ones I starred.<br /><br /><br /></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/2013/why-you-should-do-a-tiny-product-first">Why You Should Do A Tiny Product First | Unicornfree with Amy Hoy: Creating</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-2-screw-your-ideas-before-they-screw-you?inf_contact_key=bc30e00e57a3d7779308b3a8bcebfe42b031fde4971ca4b829281942bee17e17">Screw your ideas before they screw you (part 2) | Unicornfree with Amy Hoy:</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-4-the-two-elements-of-a-crazy-effective-pitch?inf_contact_key=c1a420e1d56ef2923ae3924976d23406a390286e36a9f8e589a5fafb3f18a487">The two elements of a crazy effective pitch (Part 4) | Unicornfree with Amy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-5-customer-interviews?inf_contact_key=d8e0599528f2493b754c818c45f15f0124a52a57985b924c4126ca887b5b88e3">Customer Interviews… #1.$(@! (Part 5) | Unicornfree with Amy Hoy: Creating A</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-6-what-if-im-a-nobody-whos-going-to-buy-from-me?inf_contact_key=e992fceddae304803d937a69b6328b235db8b3d245a50016a7d13537ca1dfa8b">What if I’m a “nobody”? Who’s going to buy from me? (Part 6) | Unicornfree</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-7-the-dreaded-silent-launch?inf_contact_key=f50bcca923788d903cdd526da3e70d45e03c0f48da807facc145c205374192c5">Bootstrapping Series #7 – the dreaded silent launch | Unicornfree with Amy</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://unicornfree.com/bootstrapping-series-8-special-bonus-guide-inside-make-a-million-bucks-or-watch-buffy?inf_contact_key=f96477bf37271f7ee1b47682ff686319974830dbfc26528ea22eefcdab18f909">Special bonus guide – make a million bucks, or watch Buffy? (Part 8) | Unic</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://doubleyourfreelancing.com/new-industry-no-problem/">New Industry You’ve Never Worked In Before? No Problem! - Double Your Freel</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://leanstack.com/why-lean-canvas/">https://leanstack.com/why-lean-canvas/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/blog/">Blog | Kalzumeus Software</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=12720636">Ask HN: $1k side projecters, what was the best thing you did to market it?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.canny.io/saas-startup-ramen-profitability/">How we Bootstrapped our SaaS Startup to Ramen Profitability – Canny Blog</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://chrisbolman.com/strategy-develop-effective-framework/">Strategy: How to Develop, Structure and Shape a Winning System</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://richg42.blogspot.ru/2017/09/things-learned-while-running-your-own.html">Rich Geldreich’s Tech And Programmer Culture Blog: Things learned while run</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/@Louis_Grenier/2cc8c6c79c">How Seth Godin Would Launch a Business With a $1,000 Budget – Louis Grenier</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.capitalandgrowth.org/niko-bonatsos/">The 2 Underrated Startup Success Factors | Capital &amp; Growth Blog</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/07/01/invisible-unicorns-35-big-companies-that-started-with-little-or-no-money/">Invisible unicorns: 35 big companies that started with little or no money |</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://thebetterstory.co/everything-i-wish-id-known-before-i-started-demoing-saas-f83c1c4fad99">Everything I Wish I’d Known Before I Started Demoing SaaS</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2013/04/24/marketing-for-people-who-would-rather-be-building-stuff/">Marketing Software, For People Who Would Rather Be Building It | Kalzumeus</a></li>
  <li><del>http://discuss.joelonsoftware.com/default.asp?W1341</del></li>
  <li><del>EP10: Rob Walling – outsource on oDesk, find your idea, market your product http://productpeople.tv/2013/01/23/ep10-rob-walling-part2/</del></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7367243">Ask HN: Successful one-person online businesses? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/validating_product_ideas">How To Validate Product Ideas Before (And After) Building Them</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/episodes/episode-184">http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/episodes/episode-184</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://moz.com/blog/most-entertaining-guide-to-landing-page-optimization">http://moz.com/blog/most-entertaining-guide-to-landing-page-optimization</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://moz.com/beginners-guide-to-seo">http://moz.com/beginners-guide-to-seo</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://ninjasandrobots.com/how-to-get-business-ideas-remove-steps/">http://ninjasandrobots.com/how-to-get-business-ideas-remove-steps/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://ianlandsman.com/how-we-built-besnappy-for-317000/">http://ianlandsman.com/how-we-built-besnappy-for-317000/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.getgrowth.com/blog/jesse-mecham-ynabs-story-growth/">http://www.getgrowth.com/blog/jesse-mecham-ynabs-story-growth/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://pacehq.com/blog/why-im-starting-pace/">http://pacehq.com/blog/why-im-starting-pace/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8004272">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8004272</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140728184853/http://summitevergreen.com/aha-moments-2014-baconbiz/">“Aha Moments” from the 2014 BaconBiz Conference You Can Implement Today | S</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://m.habrahabr.ru/company/witget/blog/230247/">http://m.habrahabr.ru/company/witget/blog/230247/</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://goodui.org/">http://goodui.org/</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://unicornfree.com/2014/dont-fave-this-post-how-to-really-launch-in-2014">http://unicornfree.com/2014/dont-fave-this-post-how-to-really-launch-in-201</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="https://sg168.infusionsoft.com/app/hostedEmail/134357/c53a27c753a71cdf">“I launched to only one paid subscriber.”</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://businessofsoftware.org/2011/08/peldi-at-business-of-software-2010-do-worry-be-happy-keeping-sane-as-a-software-ceo-video-transcript/">Peldi at Business of Software 2010: Do Worry, Be Happy! Keeping sane as a s</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="http://businessofsoftware.org/2013/02/kathy-sierra-building-the-minimum-badass-user-business-of-software-a-masterclass-in-thinking-about-software-product-development/">Kathy Sierra: Building the minimum Badass User, Business of Software. A mas</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="https://casjam.com/productize/">Productize</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="http://patmaddox.com/2014/11/02/how-i-went-from-a-5-line-11-word-outline-to-shipping-an-ebook-in-12-hours/">How I went from a 5-line, 11-word outline to shipping an ebook in 12 hours</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://justinjackson.ca/growth/">How user growth really works | by @mijustin</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/services_vs_products">What Consulting Companies Can Learn From Product Companies</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://andyadams.org/you-can-charge-more/">Freelancing: How to talk yourself into charging more | Andy Adams</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://webcache.googleusercontent.com/search?q=cache:DOe6SfYAXqMJ:https://news.ycombinator.com/item%3Fid%3D8704303+&amp;cd=1&amp;hl=en&amp;ct=clnk&amp;gl=ru">Freelancing: How to talk yourself into charging more | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8908279">Ask HN: How do you find freelance/contract gigs? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://geektimes.ru/post/245916/">Дайджест интересных материалов о создании контента, маркетинге и Growth Hac</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=9289500">Ask HN: How to move beyond “freelancer”? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://unicornfree.com/2014/from-zero-to-3k-mrr-in-10-days-the-story-of-rubysteps?inf_contact_key=879cf66c334ad0970b841724a73b2113f7e4d1156c002f99dafebf64646901c8">From Zero to $3k MRR in 10 days — the story of launching RubySteps | Unicor</a></li>
  <li><strong><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/01/23/salary-negotiation/">Salary Negotiation: Make More Money, Be More Valued | Kalzumeus Software</a></strong></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/businesses/ministry-of-testing">Ministry of Testing - Indie Hackers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/businesses/submithub">SubmitHub - Indie Hackers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://codingvc.com/how-to-use-thought-experiments-to-de-risk-your-startup/">How to Use Thought Experiments to De-Risk Your Startup · Coding VC</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.upupgrow.com/blog/2016/12/20/how-to-validate-demand-for-your-product">How to Validate Demand for Your Product — Up Up Grow</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/businesses/discourse">Discourse - Indie Hackers</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://stephaniehurlburt.com/blog/2017/6/24/on-starting-a-software-business">On Starting a Software Business — Stephanie Hurlburt</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/businesses/scotts-cheap-flights">Scott’s Cheap Flights - Indie Hackers</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/business-40504764">The man who built a $1bn firm in his basement - BBC News</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.toomas.net/2017/07/18/reverse-engineering-a-successful-lifestyle-business-heres-everything-ive-learned-from-reading-indiehackers-com/">Reverse Engineering A Successful Lifestyle Business: Here’s Everything I’ve</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.sideprojectchecklist.com/marketing-checklist">https://www.sideprojectchecklist.com/marketing-checklist</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://stripe.com/atlas/guides/starting-sales">Stripe Atlas: Getting Your First 10 Customers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://search.firstround.com/lists">First Search</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://stripe.com/atlas/guides/business-of-saas">Stripe Atlas: Software as a Service, as a business</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=16482392">Ask HN: Successful one-person online businesses?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=4247615">tptacek on how to run a consultancy (rise your rates!)</a></li>
  <li>““Working harder” is a poor strategy which your competitors can trivially replicate. Instead, spend some time measuring what tasks add value to your business and at what imputed wages. Outsource those tasks which are below your desired imputed wage, automate any task where appropriate, and simply don’t do things which don’t add value.”<a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2009/10/04/work-smarter-not-harder/">patio11 on Working smarter, not harder</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://doubleyourfreelancing.com/">Double Your Freelancing Rate - Book</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170530020758/http://www.turbineroom.com/saas-idea-evaluation-checklist/">Checklist for Picking the Best SaaS Idea - Happy Bootstrapper</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://ryanbattles.com/post/blogs-for-bootstrappers">24 Blogs that Bootstrappers Won’t Want to Miss</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://fizzle.co/popular-posts">Most Popular Posts on Fizzle (site about running your business)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2010/03/20/running-a-software-business-on-5-hours-a-week/">Running A Software Business On 5 Hours A Week - patio11</a>
    <br />Some select quotes:
    <br /><br />
 	&gt; build time assets: things which will save you time in the future. Code that actually does something useful is a very simple time asset for programmers to understand: you write it once today, then you can execute it tomorrow and every other day, saving you the effort of doing manually whatever it was the code does. Code is far from the only time asset, though: systems and processes for doing your work more efficiently, marketing which scales disproportionate to your time, documentation which answers customers’ questions before they ask you, all of these things are assets. 
 	<br /><br />
 	&gt; around 90% of the effort, are caused by non-coding activities: dealing with pre-sales inquiries, marketing, SEO, marketing, customer support, marketing, website copywriting, marketing, etc. 
 	<br /><br />
 	&gt; Cutting your feature set to the bone is the single best advice I can give you which will get you to actually launching. 
 	<br /><br />
 	&gt; Another thing I’d look for prior to committing to building anything is a marketing hook — something you can take advantage of to market your product in a time-effective way. For bingo cards, I knew there were more activities possible than any one company could ever publish, and that gave me hope that I could eventually out-niche the rest of the market. (This is core idea still drives most of my marketing, four years later.) Maybe your idea has built-in virality (nice if you can get it — I really envy the Facebook crowd sometimes, although I suppose they probably envy having a customer base which pays money for software), a built-in hook for getting links, or something similar. If you can’t come up with anything, fix that before you build it. 
 	<br /><br />
 	(How to find ↑ this marketing ‘trick’ remains unknown to me)</li>
  <li><a href="https://training.kalzumeus.com/newsletters/archive/consulting_1">How I went from $100-an-hour programming to $X0,000-a-week consulting</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7994673">Ask HN: 16-hour work week jobs?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://timconley.co/FA/how-to-make-5000-to-10000-each-month-as-an-internet-marketing-consultant-fa083/">How to Make $5000 to $10,000 Each Month as an Internet Marketing Consultant</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2014/07/24/kalzumeus-podcast-episode-8-high-touch-software-sales-with-steli-efti/">Kalzumeus Podcast Episode 8: High Touch Software Sales with Steli Efti</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://stackingthebricks.com/how-do-you-stay-motivated-when-youre-not-making-any-money/?_r=uf">How do you stay motivated when you’re not making any money?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wired.com/2014/08/the-most-fascinating-profile-youll-ever-read-about-a-guy-and-his-boring-startup/">The Most Fascinating Profile You’ll Ever Read About a Guy and His Boring Startup</a></li>
  <li><del>How to Land Your First Customers When You’re Unknown https://productizeandscale.com/your-first-customers/</del></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2015/05/01/talking-about-money/">Talking About Money [Salary]</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://heidiroizen.tumblr.com/post/118473647305/how-to-build-a-unicorn-from-scratch-and-walk">How to Build a Unicorn From Scratch – and Walk Away with Nothing</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hellowebbooks.com/news/how-i-launched-my-learn-to-code-book-and-made-nearly-5000-in-pre-orders/">I self-published a learn-to-code book and made nearly $5,000 in pre-orders</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://theboomerbusinessowner.com/2015/04/tbbo-317-keith-perhac-build-online-course-increase-profits/">TBBO 317: Keith Perhac – Build an Online Course to Increase Profits</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://jacquesmattheij.com/ceo">CEO - Jacques Mattheij</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/interview/growing-a-community-for-digital-nomads-to-33-000-mo-126df0fc5e">Growing a Community for Digital Nomads to $33,000/mo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/interview/how-i-supported-myself-full-time-by-building-a-wordpress-plugin-c0ff60a5ca">How I Supported Myself Full Time by Building a WordPress Plugin</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/interview/how-charging-money-for-pro-features-allowed-me-quit-my-job-6e71309457">How Charging Money for Pro Features Allowed Me Quit My Job</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://tim.blog/2011/09/24/how-to-create-a-million-dollar-business-this-weekend-examples-appsumo-mint-chihuahuas/">How to Create a Million-Dollar Business This Weekend (Examples: AppSumo, Mint, Chihuahuas)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/interview/creating-an-ai-powered-logo-creator-and-earning-70k-mo-4ebecd547f">Creating an AI-Powered Logo Creator and Earning $70k/mo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://threadreaderapp.com/thread/1002103360646823936.html">Thread by @naval: How to Get Rich (without getting lucky)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/09/21/ramit-sethi-and-patrick-mckenzie-on-why-your-customers-would-be-happier-if-you-charged-more/">Ramit Sethi and Patrick McKenzie On Why Your Customers Would Be Happier If You Charged More</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2012/09/17/ramit-sethi-and-patrick-mckenzie-on-getting-your-first-consulting-client/">Ramit Sethi and Patrick McKenzie on Getting Your First Consulting Client</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200506074948/https://a16z.com/2015/08/21/16-metrics/">Andreessen Horowitz - 16 Startup Metrics</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.samaltman.com/the-post-yc-slump">The Post-YC Slump</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.bothsidesofthetable.com/2015/06/19/why-successful-people-focus-on-the-bottom-end-of-the-funnel/">Why Successful People Focus on the Bottom End of the Funnel</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://andrewchen.co/the-next-feature-fallacy-the-fallacy-that-the-next-new-feature-will-suddenly-make-people-use-your-product/">The Next Feature Fallacy: The fallacy that the next new feature will suddenly make people use your product</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.nickkolenda.com/psychological-pricing-strategies/">42 Pricing Tricks Based on Psychology &amp; Neuroscience</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.mobilejazz.com/working-remotely-from-a-tropical-island-in-thailand/">Working Remotely From A Tropical Island in Thailand</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://doubleyourfreelancing.com/guide-to-selling-ecommerce-clients/">The Complete Guide To Finding And Selling Ecommerce Clients</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://blog.close.io/not-to-do-list">Effective entrepreneurship: The not to-do list</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://tim.blog/2017/12/30/how-to-build-a-million-dollar-one-person-business/">How to Build a Million-Dollar, One-Person Business – Case Studies From The 4-Hour Workweek</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/@cliffordoravec/the-epic-guide-to-bootstrapping-a-saas-startup-from-scratch-by-yourself-part-1-4d834e1df8c1">The Epic Guide to Bootstrapping a SaaS Startup from Scratch — By Yourself (Part 1)</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.themacro.com/articles/2016/07/yc-summer-reading/">YC’s Summer Reading</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://keen.io/blog/135255657976/permission-to-fail">Permission to Fail</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://betterexplained.com/articles/understand-accounting-basics-aloe-and-balance-sheets/">Understanding Accounting Basics (ALOE and Balance Sheets)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://betterexplained.com/articles/understanding-debt-risk-and-leverage/">Understanding Debt, Risk and Leverage</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/@benediktdeicke/launching-a-product-in-just-3652-days-4d4e74e2dcd5">Launching a product,</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://lawrencehester.com/post/126668871331/fareharbor-bootstrap-success">We Started on a Couch: A Story of Growth from the Road Less Traveled</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://moz.com/blog/ecommerce-kpi-benchmark-study">E-Commerce KPI Study: There’s (Finally) a Benchmark for That</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://kaidavis.com/articles/">Articles on attracting leads to your consulting gig</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8800788">Ask HN: How do you stay motivated to work on side projects?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://bootstrappedweb.com/business-models-bootstrappers/">[47] Business Models for Bootstrappers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=8629919">Ask HN: How much recurring income do you generate and from what?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://doubleyourfreelancing.com/100kprojects/">The Business of Freelancing, Episode 20: Scott Yewell On His First $100k+ Project</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.startupsfortherestofus.com/episodes/episode-208-how-to-productize-your-service-with-brian-casel">Episode 208 | How To Productize Your Service with Brian Casel</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://hacktheentrepreneur.com/making-software-is-easy-patrick-mckenzie/">Making Software is Easy w/ Patrick McKenzie</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://stackingthebricks.com/how-do-you-create-a-product-people-want-to-buy/">How do you create a product people want to buy?</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.kalzumeus.com/2014/12/22/kalzumeus-software-year-in-review-2014/">Kalzumeus Software Year in Review 2014</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/die.html">How Not to Die</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.intercom.com/books/growth-handbook">The Growth Handbook by Intercom</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1ZJZbv4J6FZ8Dnb0JuMhJxTnwl-dwqx5xl0s65DE3wO8/edit#heading=h.u92txq7xuirk">Founder to CEO - How to build a great company from the ground up</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://tim.blog/2018/03/29/discipline-sex-psychedelics-and-more-the-return-of-drunk-dialing/">Tim Ferriss Drunk dialling</a> starting from 30 minute, on how to choose what to do (something you yourself will pay for)</li>
  <li><a href="https://a16z.com/2018/09/02/sales-startups-technical-founders/">All Things Sales! 16 Mini-Lessons for Startup Founders</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.browserless.io/blog/2018/08/01/running-an-indie-business.html">Things they don’t teach you running a business by yourself</a></li>
  <li><del>#30DayStartup https://www.newco.app/30daystartup</del></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.tfaforms.com/4697544">Emergent Ventures Fellowship Application</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=18047553">Ask HN: How to come up with monetizable side project ideas?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/everhour/growing-our-saas-company-to-1m-arr-7-people-3-years-no-vc-money-key-lessons-learned-2d53766507d2">Growing Our SaaS Company To $1M+ ARR: 7 People, 3 Years, No VC Money. Key Lessons Learned</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://blog.inkdrop.info/how-ive-attracted-the-first-500-paid-users-for-my-saas-that-costs-5-mo-7a5b94b8e820">How I’ve Attracted The First 500 Paid Users For My SaaS That Costs $5/mo</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.pipelinedb.com/blog/three-sales-mistakes-software-engineers-make">Three Sales Mistakes Software Engineers Make</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://t.me/newgameplusco/93">интервью Ильи Красинского Диме Думику про свой фреймворк погружения в новый продукт, масштабирование, как предпринимателю справляться с трудностями и как генерить идеи</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.cortes.design/post/best-saas-landing-page-examples-inspiration">The Best SaaS Landing page examples I’ve seen (+ their secrets for conversion)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=18400020">Ask HN: What are some hacks of real founders who did things that don’t scale?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://dothingsthatdontscale.com">Do Things That Don’t Scale - a crowdsourced collection of unscalable startup hacks</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/104qgagSsp2rQQEDORGbYC0uqt0neYHCPxu-aUl4CuSQ/preview">The First 100 - Measure the strength of your idea with real customers</a><br /><br />
 <br /><br /></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/01/11/technology/start-ups-rejecting-venture-capital.html">More Start-Ups Have an Unfamiliar Message for Venture Capitalists: Get Lost</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://stripe.com/atlas/guides/landing-page-copy">Stripe Atlas: Writing copy for landing pages</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://campfirelabs.co/blog-1/2019/1/10/how-i-built-a-5000-per-month-side-project">How I Built A $5,000 Per Month Side Project — Campfire Labs</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://postmake.io/open">Open Startups – Postmake</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.com/@shl/reflecting-on-my-failure-to-build-a-billion-dollar-company-b0c31d7db0e7">Reflecting on My Failure to Build a Billion-Dollar Company</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://conversionxl.com/blog/pricing-experiments-you-might-not-know-but-can-learn-from/">Pricing Experiments You Might Not Know, But Can Learn From</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19164037">Ask HN: How to find profitable side project idea? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.indiehackers.com/interview/how-i-hit-115k-mo-with-a-status-quo-improvement-c45d11ad17">How I Hit $115k/mo with a Status Quo Improvement - Indie Hackers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1wkJ6Ruh2IiR-caT-PS3n5Yt5VKcmIsVhuQwjgqK7030/preview">Summary: How to Start a Startup (YC) - Google Docs</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://book.nathanlatka.com/?ref=producthunt">How To Be a Capitalist Without Any Capital by Nathan Latka</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://hardclient.com/restaurants">Эталонный Сервис: Рестораны</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19455224">Ask HN: Resources/Steps for Becoming a Consultant? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=19876825">Ask HN: What was your experience starting a tech consultancy? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.derrickreimer.com/essays/2019/05/17/im-walking-away-from-the-product-i-spent-a-year-building.html">I’m Walking Away From the Product I Spent a Year Building</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://postmake.io/books">Founder Books – Postmake</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://medium.dave-bailey.com/why-visionary-founders-need-to-think-long-term-7ec4a5aae21a">The Art of Thinking Long-Term Even When Money is Running Out</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://foundationinc.co/lab/the-saas-opportunity-of-unbundling-excel/">The SaaS Opportunity Of Unbundling Excel</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://doist.com/blog/decision-making-flat-organization/">Principles for Decision-Making in a Flat Organization</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.defmacro.org/2019/03/26/startup-checklist.html">Startup idea checklist | defmacro</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.nngroup.com/articles/why-you-only-need-to-test-with-5-users/">Why You Only Need to Test with 5 Users</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20457758">Speakers tend to prefer either a high considerateness or high involvement s</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://habr.com/en/company/badoo/blog/458792/">«Сгоревшие» сотрудники: есть ли выход? / Badoo corporate blog / Habr</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://danshipper.com/nothing-happens-until-the-sale-is-made">How to get your first 10 customers</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://ottofeller.com/blog/how-to-conduct-research-and-successfully-launch-a-product">How to conduct research and successfully launch a product | ottofeller</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://uxdesign.cc/stop-designing-products-for-random-people-4734423cbfe6">Stop designing products for random people - UX Collective</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://zamesin.me/links-ycss19-how-to-talk-to-users/">SS19E2: Как разговаривать с клиентами</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://qz.com/work/1433979/how-to-be-good-at-sales-as-an-introvert/">How to be good at sales as an introvert — Quartz at Work</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://unawaz.github.io/stochastic-hill-climbing/tasks/">20,000 Startup Ideas</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://kevinlynagh.com/notes/pricing-niche-products/">Pricing niche products: Why sell a mechanical keyboard kit for $1,668?</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://habr.com/ru/company/hygger/blog/416683/">Что дальше? Или как правильно выбрать фичи для разработки</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21367151">Ask HN: How do B2B startups sell to corporations? | Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://chrisachard.com/how-to-find-consulting-clients">How to Find Consulting Clients</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://docs.sendwithses.com/random-stuff/the-internet-is-an-seo-landfill">The internet is an SEO landfill</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.howitactuallyworks.com/archives/future_you_masturbation.html">Future you mastrubation</a></li>
</ol>

<p>Last-updated: May 30, 2020</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/05/List-of-entrepreneur-related-links</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>4 Things You Believe That Mess Up Your Social Life</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/04/4-things-you-believe-that-mess-up-your-social-life</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I plan to start my <a href="http://www.comfortzonecrusher.com/">Comfort Zone Crusher course</a> some time this year.<br />
Here’s a few good citations about beliefs that hamper your social life:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You don’t need to make people like you. Learn to be okay with who you are, and you’re going to attract people who naturally like you.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The easier you are on yourself, the more likely you will say something that resonates with the people around you.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your social skills are good enough. Instead, work on overcoming your fear.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Fear is NOT the problem. Our reaction to fear is.
Instead of learning to get rid of fear, we need to learn to take action DESPITE feeling fear. This means saying “Hi” to a stranger, even though you have shaky knees, trembling hands, and a squeaky voice.
Take action despite feeling fear. This is what courage is all about.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.comfortzonecrusher.com/4-things-believe-mess-social-life/">http://www.comfortzonecrusher.com/4-things-believe-mess-social-life/</a></p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/04/4-things-you-believe-that-mess-up-your-social-life</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>The Acceleration of Addictiveness</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/03/Acceleration-of-Addictiveness</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>Paul Graham on acceleration of addictiveness:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>And unless the rate at which social antibodies evolve can increase to match the accelerating rate at which technological progress throws off new addictions, we’ll be increasingly unable to rely on customs to protect us. [3] Unless we want to be canaries in the coal mine of each new addiction—the people whose sad example becomes a lesson to future generations—we’ll have to figure out for ourselves what to avoid and how. It will actually become a reasonable strategy (or a more reasonable strategy) to suspect everything new.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/addiction.html">http://www.paulgraham.com/addiction.html</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/03/Acceleration-of-Addictiveness</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 03 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Good genes are nice, but joy is better</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/02/Good-genes-are-nice-but-joy-is-better</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <blockquote>
  <p>Researchers […] found a strong correlation between men’s flourishing lives and their relationships with family, friends, and community. Several studies found that people’s level of satisfaction with their relationships at age 50 was a better predictor of physical health than their cholesterol levels were.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/04/over-nearly-80-years-harvard-study-has-been-showing-how-to-live-a-healthy-and-happy-life/">https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2017/04/over-nearly-80-years-harvard-study-has-been-showing-how-to-live-a-healthy-and-happy-life/</a></p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/02/Good-genes-are-nice-but-joy-is-better</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>The Western Elite from a Chinese Perspective</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/01/Western-elite-from-Chinese-perspective</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://americanaffairsjournal.org/2017/11/western-elite-chinese-perspective/">The Western Elite from a Chinese Perspective</a> <em>by</em> Puzhong Yao</p>

<p>Though I think the author overgeneralizes in his conclusion, this article provided a very interesting tidbit of information: admission ratio in China Universities is around <strong>1500:1</strong>. That’s <em>extremely</em> competitive.</p>

<p>Quick google check found me <a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-admission-rate-at-Tsinghua-University">this Quora question</a> with answers like:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As rule of thumb - it’s 1 in 100 to 1 in 1000 (in some popular fields may be even 1 in 5000).</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>In most provinces, the admission rate ranges from nearly 0.04% to 0.1%</p>
</blockquote>

<p>O_O Wow</p>

<p>Yao describes his rise from the bottom of his class in China to the top of his class in England, seemingly only because the top level in England corresponds to low one in his University.<br />
I know there are a lot of assumptions embedded, nevertheless I have a newfound respect for those Chinese who make it though this sieve.</p>

<p>It will be really interesting to meet one of them.</p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/01/Western-elite-from-Chinese-perspective</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Why choices are bad</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/03/01/Why-choices-are-bad</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><em>Choosing</em> is an area of life that I plan to optimize by removing as much day-to-day choosing as possible (wakeup routine, outfit choice, meal choice, relaxation routine, etc)</p>

<p>In his two elegantly titled posts Zvi explains why: 1) <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/22/choices-are-bad/">Choices are Bad</a> and 2) <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/08/12/choices-are-really-bad/">Choices Are Really Bad</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A movie you would have enjoyed if it was just on makes you feel like a schmuck if you take twenty minutes choosing it from thousands at the video store.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thus, giving me a choice between a Snickers bar that I value at $1 and M&amp;Ms I value at 60 cents doesn’t only force me into choosing mode, lower my perceived value and help create decision fatigue (and potentially cost willpower). It also risks that if I’m not paying attention or thinking clearly, I will choose the M&amp;Ms, and that would be a tragedy.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I try to remove choosing in other people’s lives too. In situations where I know they do not value ability to choose that much: like what cafe should be go to, what street to turn to next, snickers or m&amp;ms, etc. Of course, I don’t force the choice on them - if they <em>want</em> to choose, it’s their right.</p>

<p>Also recommended read on somewhat similar topic:</p>

<h3 id="change-is-bad-too">Change is bad too</h3>

<p>The Zvi on why we should choose what we change very carefully. <strong>Every change has a cost.</strong> 
Sounds obvious but there were quite a few ‘aha’ moments while reading this. As usual with Zvi, this is delightfully all-encompassing.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Older people have had more time to optimize and have less time to optimize again, so it makes sense that they hate change even more than others. They should.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/20/change-is-bad/">https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/20/change-is-bad/</a></p>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/03/01/Why-choices-are-bad</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Dealing with internal conflict immediately</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/28/Dealing-with-internal-conflict-immediately</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>This feels extremely valuable. Adding this as a goal myself.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So I now have a double commitment: to act in each moment out of a sense of purposeful discipline, and also to not waste my energy fighting myself.</p>

  <p>And, as Dogen recommends: “to practise the Way as though saving my head from fire.”</p>

  <p>This means that if I notice myself feeling aimless, or I notice myself feeling stuck or oscillating, <strong>dealing with that immediately rather than acting <em>from</em> it</strong>. Focusing on addressing internal conflicts might yield less short-term output than if I were to stay focused on the object-level and push through with “willpower”, trying to win my internal conflict. Focusing on staying purpose-driven in each moment will almost certainly be less comfortable than a more calm spaciousness, but if I don’t then I can’t actually trust myself to resolve my conflicts in service of what I care about.</p>

  <p>Conflict is inherently wasteful, as energy is spent by both sides but the effects cancel each other out. Tiago Forte points out in The Throughput of Learning that Toyota’s production line aims for zero waste. They don’t expect to reach literally zero, but having that as a target makes it clear to the whole system that they’re playing a totally different game than mere waste mitigation or waste reduction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>Malcolm Ocean</em><br />
<a href="http://malcolmocean.com/2017/06/towards-being-purpose-driven-without-fighting-myself/">http://malcolmocean.com/2017/06/towards-being-purpose-driven-without-fighting-myself/</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/28/Dealing-with-internal-conflict-immediately</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Vigilant MVPing: the case of this blog</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/25/Vigilant-MVP-case-of-this-blog</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>During my day job I frequently have to optimize software development tasks to
leave only the most important, essential functionality and cut away all the bells and whistles.<br />
This is sometimes abbreviated as MVP — Minimal Viable Product.</p>

<p>This blog is an example of a situation where I slipped into wanting to build a <em>maximum</em> viable product but steadied myself, albeit I little late.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    OK, I need a new web-site
  </p>
  <footer><cite>Me, some time ago</cite></footer>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>The worst mistake</strong> was that I started working on a solution right away… without defining a problem. I slipped into <em>“ooh, shiny”</em> techie-tinker mindset and was dead set on exploring new and fascinating frontiers of static site generators. The more I researched the more bells and whistles I gathered in my wish-list. It was like a trance.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>
    Of course I need pagination! But not just any pagination, only the best kind: by categories, by tags, by months. Hm, maybe by music and mood too?  
	To do that I just need to quickly read on about Jekyll collections and another couple of posts about how to do it all in a Github-preferred way.
  </p>
  <footer><cite>Me, high on new tech</cite></footer>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s when my weekend ended and, still having nothing to show for it, I felt sad and disappointed. I gave up and decided that <em>if</em> I even were to get new site, I will hire a professional to do it.
Some weeks later I even started making a tech spec to post on a freelance exchange. Including the fancy pagination et al, of course.</p>

<p>There was a slight problem though. I noticed a strange thing: it was really hard for me to describe in technical language what was required. Interesting. How come? 
Realization struck: I just really didn’t see the end product. And when I tried probing questions to elicit requirements from myself I understood that I was the proverbial <em>perpetually-almost-satisfied</em> client with an unlimited number of edits and improvements because he doesn’t know what he wants.</p>

<p>That’s when a stray thought of MVP came to me and I understood how wrong I’ve been.
I don’t need fancy pagination or archived posts. I just need something to start pouring my thoughts into that also doesn’t look hideous.
That’s when I installed <a href="https://github.com/barryclark/jekyll-now">Jekyll-now</a> and slapped the <a href="https://github.com/johnotander/pixyll">Pixyll</a> theme on it and here we are.</p>

<h3 id="summary-of-what-i-learned">Summary of what I learned</h3>

<p>Before diving into a new sexy project</p>
<ol>
  <li>Describe the end result in necessary detail</li>
  <li>Remember why <em>do</em> you want to do this at all. Is this new project the best way to achieve your end goal?</li>
  <li>Cut out everything that is not essential</li>
</ol>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/25/Vigilant-MVP-case-of-this-blog</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Hello, World!</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/24/Hello-world</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p>I’ve bit the bullet and decided to create this thing.
I plan to use it to</p>

<ul>
  <li>post links to articles, images, videos — anything that I like, with a small comment or quote about what in particular got my attenton</li>
  <li>post about my [thought, goal-setting, etc]-processes with the goal of internal and external audit. As The Zvi <a href="https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/24/write-down-your-process/">put it</a>:</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Writing down your conclusions often makes you realize where your conclusions are wrong, or your techniques can be improved. Having to put  all of your justifications into precise words, in a place others could read them, makes most bad reasoning obvious if you are paying attention.</p>
</blockquote>


                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/24/Hello-world</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 24 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/17/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-consolation-of-philosophy"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1483979801-20170109.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-consolation-of-philosophy">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-consolation-of-philosophy</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/17/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 17 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/16/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/380/"><img src="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/05/sirenssm-e1495612384498.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/380/">http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/380/</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/16/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 16 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/15/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/power"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1498574982-20170627.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/power">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/power</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/15/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/14/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/bedtime"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1498658331-20170628%20(1).png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/bedtime">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/bedtime</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/14/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 14 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/13/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/wrestling"><img src="https://smbc-comics.com/comics/1507990450-20171014.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/wrestling">http://smbc-comics.com/comic/wrestling</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/13/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/12/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/a-window"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1516024741-20180115.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/a-window">http://smbc-comics.com/comic/a-window</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/12/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/11/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=3866"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1442658363-20150919%20fixedv2.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=3866">https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=3866</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/11/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 11 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/09/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/self-driving-car-ethics"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1467643530-20160704.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/self-driving-car-ethics">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/self-driving-car-ethics</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/09/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/08/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/heap-problems"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1466434160-20160620.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/heap-problems">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/heap-problems</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/08/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/07/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=4142"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1466002173-20160615.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=4142">https://www.smbc-comics.com/index.php?id=4142</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/07/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/06/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/machine-ethics"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/20160614.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/machine-ethics">http://smbc-comics.com/comic/machine-ethics</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/06/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/05/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-talk"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1454859358-20150207.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-talk">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/the-talk</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/05/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Mon, 05 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/04/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/false"><img src="https://smbc-comics.com/comics/1451228669-20151227.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/false">http://smbc-comics.com/comic/false</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/04/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sun, 04 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/03/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/philosophy"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1441809270-20150909.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://smbc-comics.com/comic/philosophy">http://smbc-comics.com/comic/philosophy</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/03/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Sat, 03 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/02/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/276/"><img src="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/IMG_20160517_201251-e1472103724988.jpg" alt="" /></a>
<a href="http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/276/">http://extrafabulouscomics.com/comic/276/</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/02/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
        
            <item>
                <title>Web comic</title>
                <link>https://www.lepekhin.com/2018/02/01/Web-comic</link>
                <content:encoded>
                    <![CDATA[
                    <p><a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/what39s-really-attractive"><img src="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comics/1467472087-20160702.png" alt="" /></a>
<a href="https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/what39s-really-attractive">https://www.smbc-comics.com/comic/what39s-really-attractive</a></p>

                    ]]>
                </content:encoded>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">/2018/02/01/Web-comic</guid>
                <description>
                    
                </description>
                <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
                <author>Andrey Lepekhin</author>
            </item>
        
    
  </channel>
</rss>
